<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <principal>George A. Kiraz</principal>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt><resp>XSLT transformations by</resp><name>Winona Salesky</name></respStmt>
            <respStmt><resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp><name>David A. Michelson</name></respStmt>
            <respStmt><resp>TEI encyclopedia schema by</resp><name>David A. Michelson and Daniel L. Schwartz</name></respStmt>
            <respStmt><resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp><name>George A. Kiraz</name></respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1">Electronic Edition Draft Version 0.1</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA
               www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference
               Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)
                     License.</p></licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>Aba I</head>
            <ab type="idnos">
               <idno type="uri">http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aba-I</idno>
               <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/10</idno>
               <idno type="entry">1</idno>
               <milestone unit="pages" n="1"/>
               <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/person/306</idno>
               <note type="type">person</note>
               <note type="abstract">Teacher of biblical interpretation, author, Cath. (540-52).</note>
               <note type="affiliation">Ch. of E.</note>
            </ab>
            <ab type="infobox"> (d. 552) [Ch. of E.]</ab>
            <div type="body"><p>Teacher of biblical interpretation, author, Cath. (540–52). Born from Zoroastrian
               parents, Aba converted to Christianity and studied at the <ref type="cr" target="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis-School-of">School of
                  Nisibis</ref>. He traveled to the Roman Empire and visited <ref type="cr" target="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa"
                     >Edessa</ref> (where he was taught Greek, probably by his later disciple <ref
                        type="cr">Toma of Edessa</ref>), Palestine, Egypt, and Constantinople. Upon his
               return, he became a teacher of biblical interpretation (<hi rend="italic"
                  >mpaššqānā</hi>) at the <ref type="cr">School of Nisibis</ref> and subsequently at
               the School of <ref type="cr">Seleucia-Ctesiphon</ref>, which he is said to have
               founded. Following the death of Cath. Pawlos, he was elected as his successor in 540.
               In 544 an itinerant synod was held, during which Aba, accompanied by a changing
               number of bishops, visited several dioceses, many of which still suffered from the
               division in the church that had existed prior to the short tenure of Cath. Pawlos.
               The <ref type="cr">Synodicon Orientale</ref> has preserved the following documents,
               which are related to this ecclesiastical visitation and, more broadly, to Aba’s
               reforms: 1. on reform of church governance; 2. on the orthodox faith; 3. on the <hi
                  rend="italic">politeia</hi> of correct behavior (focusing on Christian marriage
               and rejecting various kinds of illicit unions); 4. on the deposal of the initiators
               of division and schism; 5. on the various degrees in the ecclesiastical hierarchy; 6.
               a letter entitled <hi rend="italic">Practica</hi> (fragments); 7. canons (1–40;
               incomplete). Aba came into conflict with the Persian authorities and spent several of
               his years as Cath. in prison and in exile.</p>
            <p>The sources attribute to Aba several commentaries on OT and NT books, of which only
               fragments exist in later works, such as the commentaries of <ref type="cr">Ishoʿdad
                  of Merv</ref>. During his travels, around 530, he served as the instructor in
               biblical matters to the Egyptian author Cosmas Indicopleustes, who ca.  550 wrote his
               ‘Christian Topography’. Cosmas (in Book II.2) acknowledges Aba, whom he calls
               Patrikios (derived from the Greek word for ‘father’), as his source and is aware of
               Aba’s later election as Cath. in Persia. Interested in the Greek originals of <ref
                  type="cr">Theodore of Mopsuestia</ref>’s and <ref type="cr">Nestorius</ref>’s
               works, Aba may have gathered around him a team of translators. One of these may have
               been the Syriac translator of Nestorius’s ‘Book of Heraclides’, who dedicated his
               work to Aba. A comment in the Chronicle of<ref type="cr"> Siirt</ref> led Baumstark
               to suggest that Aba may have authored a Syriac translation of the Greek OT, but this
               cannot be substantiated.</p>
            <p>In addition to a number of Syriac and Arabic sources providing details of Aba’s life,
               there is an important Syriac Life (published by Bedjan), which presents itself as the
               work of one of Aba’s disciples. Two of Aba’s other disciples, <ref type="cr">Qiyore
                  of Edessa</ref> and Toma of Edessa (who died in Constantinople around 543), are
               known through their own writings.</p></div>
            <listBibl><listBibl><head type="subsection">Primary Sources</head>
            <bibl>P.  Bedjan, <title rend="italic">Histoire de Mar-Jabalaha, de trois autres
               patriarches, d’un prêtre et de deux laïques, nestoriens</title> (1895; repr. as <title
                  rend="italic">The history of Mar Jab-Alaha and Rabban Sauma</title>, 2007), 206–87.
               (Syr. of Life of Aba)</bibl>
            <bibl>Braun, <title rend="italic">Synodicon Orientale</title>, 93–145.</bibl>
            <bibl>idem, <title rend="italic">Ausgewählte Akten persischer Märtyrer</title>, 188–220. (GT
               of Life of Aba)</bibl>
            <bibl>Chabot, <title rend="italic">Synodicon Orientale</title>, 68–95 (Syr.), 318–51
               (FT).</bibl>
            <bibl>A.  Scher, <title rend="italic">Histoire nestorienne inédite (Chronique de
               Séert)</title>, vol. 2.1 (PO 7; 1909), 154–71.</bibl></listBibl>
            <listBibl><head type="subsection">Secondary Sources</head>
            <bibl>L.  Abramowski, <title rend="italic">Untersuchungen zum Liber Heraclidis des
               Nestorius</title> (CSCO 242; 1963), 7–13.</bibl>
            <bibl>A.  Baumstark, ‘Griechische und hebräische Bibelzitate in der Pentateucherklärung
               Išôʿdâds von Merw’, <title rend="italic">OC</title> 11 (1911), 1–19.</bibl>
            <bibl>Becker, <title rend="italic">Fear of God</title>, 35–8, 113–4, 157–8.</bibl>
            <bibl>Labourt, <title rend="italic">Le christianisme dans l’empire perse</title>,
               163–91.</bibl>
            <bibl>W.  F.  Macomber, <title rend="italic">Six explanations of the liturgical feasts by
               Cyrus of Edessa. An East Syrian theologian of the mid sixth century</title> (CSCO
               356; 1974), VII–XII.</bibl>
            <bibl>P.  Peeters, ‘Observations sur la vie syriaque de Mar Aba, catholicos de l’Église
               perse (540–552)’, in <title rend="italic">Miscellanea G. Mercati</title>, vol. 5 (SeT 125;
               1946), 69–112.</bibl>
            <bibl>Vööbus, <title rend="italic">History of the School of Nisibis</title>, 161–70.</bibl>
            <bibl>W.  Wolska, <title rend="italic">La «Topographie chrétienne» de Cosmas
               Indicopleustès. Théologie et science au VIe siècle</title> (1962), 63–73.</bibl></listBibl></listBibl>
            <byline><persName>L.  Van Rompay</persName></byline>
         </div>
         <div type="crossreference">
            <head>Abba Isaiah</head>
            <ab type="crossreference">see <ref type="cr">Isaiah of Scetis</ref></ab>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>Bar ʿAli, Ishoʿ</head>
            <ab type="idnos">
               <idno type="uri">http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ali-Isho</idno>
               <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/81</idno>
               <idno type="entry">72</idno>
               <milestone unit="pages" n="53-54"/>
               <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Ishoʿ Bar ʿAli</idno>
               <idno type="althead">ʿĪsā b. ʿAlī</idno>
               <idno type="althead">Yashūʿ b. ʿAlī</idno>
               <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/person/364</idno>
               <note type="type">person</note>
               <note type="abstract">Physician, scribe, and author of a Syriac-Arabic lexicon.</note>
               <note type="affiliation">Ch. of E.</note>
            </ab>
            <ab type="infobox">ʿĪsā b. ʿAlī, Yashūʿ b. ʿAlī (second half of the 9th cent.) [Ch. of
               E.]</ab>
            <div type="body"><p>Physician, scribe, and author of a Syriac-Arabic Lexicon. In spite of some confusion
               in the scholarly literature (see Butts), Ishoʿ bar ʿAli can in all likelihood be
               identified with ʿĪsā b. ʿAlī, student of the well-known translator <ref type="cr"
                  >Ḥunayn b. Isḥāq</ref> (d. 873). From Arabic sources, it is known that he was the
               personal physician of Caliph al-Muʿtamid (r. 870–892), and that he authored two works
               (in Arabic) in the field of medicine, the ‘Book of the benefits made use of from the
               organs of animals’ and the ‘Book of poisons’. In addition, he is mentioned as a
               scribe in the colophon of two mss. of the Arabic Diatessaron (Vatican, Borg. Arab.
               250; Oxford, Bodleian Arab. e 163).</p>
            <p>Bar ʿAli is, however, best known for his Syriac-Arabic Lexicon (ed. Hoffmann [<hi
               rend="italic">ʾālap</hi>through <hi rend="italic">mim</hi>]; Gottheil [<hi
                  rend="italic">nun</hi> through <hi rend="italic">taw</hi>]). In the preface to his
               Lexicon, Bar ʿAli states that he undertook its writing at the behest of a certain
               deacon Abraham. During his readings, Abraham had been employing the Lexicon of Ḥunayn
               b. Isḥāq as well as a Lexicon compiled by <ref type="cr">Ishoʿ of Merv</ref>. Abraham
               seems to have been happy with the former, but less so with the latter. In addition,
               according to Abraham, the lexicon of Ḥunayn b. Isḥāq and that of Ishoʿ of Merv
               differed at times in their definitions. Thus, Bar ʿAli undertook composing a new
               lexicon on the basis of these two previous works and supplemented by his own
               readings. At the end of the Preface, Bar ʿAli exhorts his future readers to expand
               and supplement his Lexicon with additional words. The name of one such expander is
               known from a postscript found in some mss., and it is none other than the
               aforementioned deacon Abraham.</p>
            <p>The Lexicon of Bar ʿAli is an important source for Syriac lexicography. Already in
               the 1830s, the Hebrew grammarian and lexicographer F. H. W. Gesenius pointed out the
               significance of Bar ʿAli’s Lexicon for Semitic studies. In addition, the Lexicon of
               Bar ʿAli — along with that of <ref type="cr">Ḥasan Bar Bahlul</ref> (mid-10th cent.)
               — was incorporated into R. Payne Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Syriacus
               </hi>and, to a lesser extent, C. Brockelmann’s <hi rend="italic">Lexicon
                  Syriacum</hi>.</p>
            <p>Finally, it should be noted that Bar ʿAli is to be distinguished from two other
               individuals with similar names: 1. ʿĪsā b. ʿAlī, who was the son of the ‘good vizier’
               ʿAlī b. ʿĪsā b. Dāʾūd b. al-Jarrāḥ (d. 946), who was a student of <ref type="cr"
                  >Yaḥyā b. ʿAdī</ref> (d. 974), and who died in 1001 (see J. L. Kraemer, <hi
                     rend="italic">Humanism in the Renaissance of Islam. The cultural revival during
                     the Buyid age</hi> [1986], 134–36); 2. ʿAlī b. ʿĪsā al-kaḥḥāl, who authored the
               ‘Prescription of Oculists’(<hi rend="italic">tadhkirat al-kaḥḥālīn</hi>), who was a
               student of <ref type="cr">Ibn al-Ṭayyib</ref> (d. 1043), and who died sometime after
               1010 (see E. Mittwoch, in <hi rend="italic">EI<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></hi>,
               vol. 1, 388).</p></div>
            <listBibl><listBibl><head type="subsection">Primary Sources</head>
            <bibl>R. J. H.  Gottheil, <title rend="italic">Bar ʿAli (Ishoʿ). The Syriac-Arabic
               Glosses</title> (2 vols.; Atti della R. Accademia dei Lincei. Classe di Scienzi
               morali, storiche e filologiche Ser. 5, vol. 13; 1910, 1928).</bibl>
            <bibl>G.  Hoffmann, <title rend="italic">Syrisch-Arabische Glossen. Autographie einer
               gothaischen Handschrift enthaltend Bar Ali’s Lexikon von Alaf bis Mim</title>
               (1874).</bibl></listBibl>
            <listBibl><head type="subsection">Secondary Sources</head>
            <bibl>Assemani, <title rend="italic">BibOr</title>, vol. 3.1, 257.</bibl>
            <bibl>Baumstark, <title rend="italic">Literatur</title>, 241–242. (with a different
               identification of Bar ʿAli)</bibl>
            <bibl>A. M. Butts, ‘The biography of the lexicographer Ishoʿ bar ʿAli (ʿĪsā b. ʿAlī)’,
               <title rend="italic">OC</title> 93 (2009), 59–70. (incl. further references)</bibl>
            <bibl>Duval, <title rend="italic">La littérature syriaque</title>, 297–8.</bibl>
            <bibl>F. H. W. Gesenius, <title rend="italic">De Bar Alio et Bar Bahlulo, lexicographis
               Syro-Arabicis ineditis, commentatio litteraria philologica</title>, 1–2 (1834,
               1839).</bibl></listBibl></listBibl>
            <byline><persName>A. M. Butts</persName></byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
