<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>Aba I</head>
            <!-- headword from GEDSH entries, may not always match TOC -->
            <div type="idnos">
               <ab>
                  <idno type="entry">1</idno>
                  <!-- This is the entry number in the GEDSH TOC -->
                  <idno type="URI">http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aba-I</idno>
                  <!-- This is the URI being declared for this entry as a biblographic item. It should be autogenerated from the headword replacing all non [a-z, A-Z] with "-" (eliminating duplicate "2x-" as needed)-->
                  <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/10</idno>
                  <!-- This is the URI for this entry as a biblographic item in Syriaca.org -->
                  <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/person/306</idno>
                  <!-- This is the Syriaca.org URI corresponding to the subject of this entry. -->
               </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="infobox">
               <ab>(d. 552) [Ch. of E.]</ab>
               <!-- information after the headword and before the first paragraph -->
            </div>
            <div type="body">
               <p><desc>Teacher of biblical interpretation, author, Cath. (540–52).</desc> <!-- Desc will be marked from matching on a separate file) --> Born from
                  Zoroastrian parents, Aba converted to Christianity and studied at the <ref
                     target="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis-School-of"> <!-- These refs will be filled in initially based on a matching script -->School of
                     Nisibis</ref>. He traveled to the Roman Empire and visited <ref>Edessa</ref>
                  (where he was taught Greek, probably by his later disciple <ref>Toma of
                     Edessa</ref>), Palestine, Egypt, and Constantinople. Upon his return, he became
                  a teacher of biblical interpretation (<hi rend="italic">mpaššqānā</hi>) at the <ref>School of
                     Nisibis</ref> and subsequently at the School of <ref>Seleucia-Ctesiphon</ref>,
                  which he is said to have founded. Following the death of Cath. Pawlos, he was
                  elected as his successor in 540. In 544 an itinerant synod was held, during which
                  Aba, accompanied by a changing number of bishops, visited several dioceses, many
                  of which still suffered from the division in the church that had existed prior to
                  the short tenure of Cath. Pawlos. The <ref>Synodicon Orientale</ref> has preserved
                  the following documents, which are related to this ecclesiastical visitation and,
                  more broadly, to Aba’s reforms: 1. on reform of church governance; 2. on the
                  orthodox faith; 3. on the <hi rend="italic">politeia</hi> of correct behavior (focusing on
                  Christian marriage and rejecting various kinds of illicit unions); 4. on the
                  deposal of the initiators of division and schism; 5. on the various degrees in the
                  ecclesiastical hierarchy; 6. a letter entitled <hi rend="italic">Practica</hi> (fragments); 7.
                  canons (1–40; incomplete). Aba came into conflict with the Persian authorities and
                  spent several of his years as Cath. in prison and in exile.</p>
               <p>The sources attribute to Aba several commentaries on OT and NT books, of which
                  only fragments exist in later works, such as the commentaries of <ref>Ishoʿdad of
                     Merv</ref>. During his travels, around 530, he served as the instructor in
                  biblical matters to the Egyptian author Cosmas Indicopleustes, who ca.  550 wrote
                  his ‘Christian Topography’. Cosmas (in Book II.2) acknowledges Aba, whom he calls
                  Patrikios (derived from the Greek word for ‘father’), as his source and is aware
                  of Aba’s later election as Cath. in Persia. Interested in the Greek originals of
                     <ref>Theodore of Mopsuestia</ref>’s and <ref>Nestorius</ref>’s works, Aba may
                  have gathered around him a team of translators. One of these may have been the
                  Syriac translator of Nestorius’s ‘Book of Heraclides’, who dedicated his work to
                  Aba. A comment in the Chronicle of<ref> Siirt</ref> led Baumstark to suggest that
                  Aba may have authored a Syriac translation of the Greek OT, but this cannot be
                  substantiated. </p>
               <p>In addition to a number of Syriac and Arabic sources providing details of Aba’s
                  life, there is an important Syriac Life (published by Bedjan), which presents
                  itself as the work of one of Aba’s disciples. Two of Aba’s other disciples,
                     <ref>Qiyore of Edessa</ref> and Toma of Edessa (who died in Constantinople
                  around 543), are known through their own writings. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
               <label>Bibliography</label>
               <!-- This div and label should be inserted after the final p element in each entry -->
               <div type="Primary-Sources">
                  <label>Primary Sources</label>
                  <!-- The @type and label is generated from the Subsection element textnode, it may vary -->
                  <bibl>P.  Bedjan, <title>Histoire de Mar-Jabalaha, de trois autres patriarches,
                        d’un prêtre et de deux laïques, nestoriens</title> (1895; repr. as
                        <title>The history of Mar Jab-Alaha and Rabban Sauma</title>, 2007), 206–87.
                     (Syr. of Life of Aba)</bibl>
                  <bibl>Braun, <title>Synodicon Orientale</title>, 93–145.</bibl>
                  <bibl>idem, <title>Ausgewählte Akten persischer Märtyrer</title>, 188–220. (GT of
                     Life of Aba)</bibl>
                  <bibl>Chabot, <title>Synodicon Orientale</title>, 68–95 (Syr.), 318–51
                     (FT).</bibl>
                  <bibl>A.  Scher, <title>Histoire nestorienne inédite (Chronique de Séert)</title>,
                     vol. 2.1 (PO 7; 1909), 154–71. </bibl>
               </div>
               <div type="Secondary-Sources">
                  <label>Secondary Sources</label>
                  <!-- The @type and label is generated from the Subsection element textnode, it may vary -->
                  <bibl>L.  Abramowski, <title>Untersuchungen zum Liber Heraclidis des
                        Nestorius</title> (CSCO 242; 1963), 7–13.</bibl>
                  <bibl>A.  Baumstark, ‘Griechische und hebräische Bibelzitate in der
                     Pentateucherklärung Išôʿdâds von Merw’, <title>OC</title> 11 (1911),
                     1–19.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Becker, <title>Fear of God</title>, 35–8, 113–4, 157–8.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Labourt, <title>Le christianisme dans l’empire perse</title>, 163–91.</bibl>
                  <bibl>W.  F.  Macomber, <title>Six explanations of the liturgical feasts by Cyrus
                        of Edessa. An East Syrian theologian of the mid sixth century</title> (CSCO
                     356; 1974), VII–XII.</bibl>
                  <bibl>P.  Peeters, ‘Observations sur la vie syriaque de Mar Aba, catholicos de
                     l’Église perse (540–552)’, in <title>Miscellanea G. Mercati</title>, vol. 5
                     (SeT 125; 1946), 69–112.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Vööbus, <title>History of the School of Nisibis</title>, 161–70.</bibl>
                  <bibl>W.  Wolska, <title>La «Topographie chrétienne» de Cosmas Indicopleustès.
                        Théologie et science au VIe siècle</title> (1962), 63–73.</bibl>
               </div>
            </div>
            <byline><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/9999 http://viaf.org/viaf/sourceID/SRP|person_9999">L.  Van Rompay</persName></byline>
            <!-- generated from author, refs will need to be created -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
