<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Aramaic</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename> 
                  <surname>Van Rompay</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Aramaic</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aramaic</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/52</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">43</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="28-30"/>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Language belonging to the Northwest Semitic
                        subfamily within the larger family of Semitic languages. <note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Aramaic language belongs to the Northwest Semitic subfamily within the
                        larger family of Semitic languages. To the same subfamily belong among
                        others Hebrew, Phoenician, and Ugaritic. Aramaic itself consists of a great
                        number of language forms (and indeed languages), spoken and written in many
                        different scripts over a period of 3000 years. Aramaic always co-existed and
                        interacted with other, related or non-related, languages. Among the Aramaic
                        languages <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syriac-Language">Syriac</ref> is by far the best documented
                        language. Geographically, Aramaic first was used in various locations of the
                        ‘Fertile Crescent’, in Syria and Mesopotamia. It later spread all over the
                        Middle East and well into Central Asia. From the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr> BC to the 7th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> AD, Aramaic, in a variety of interrelated language forms, or
                        ‘dialects’, was the most widespread language of the Middle East, co-existing
                        first with Old Persian (6th–4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> BC), and then with Greek (3rd  cent.
                        BC – 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr> AD), and Middle Persian (3rd– 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr> AD). Under the
                        dominance of Arabic and Islam, Aramaic lived on among various religious
                        minorities, Syriac Christianity being the most important among them. In the
                        third millennium AD, Aramaic and Syriac are used by a few million people —
                        Christians, Jews, Samaritans, and Mandaeans — in liturgy, literature, and/or
                        in spoken dialects in the Middle East, Southern India, and the worldwide
                        diasporas.</p>
                    <p>Various scholarly attempts have been made at classifying the Aramaic
                        languages. One among them, first proposed by J. Fitzmyer, and slightly
                        adapted by S. Kaufman among others, has become widely used. It is based on a
                        five-fold division of Aramaic linguistic history.</p>
                    <p>1. Old Aramaic (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 900 – <abbr>ca.</abbr> 600 BC). Aramaic was used by semi-autonomous
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Arameans">Aramean</ref> tribes in Syria, Palestine, and
                        Mesopotamia. Royal and funerary inscriptions of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aleppo">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/18">Aleppo</placeName>
                        </ref> region
                        exhibit a relatively, but not entirely, unified language in the Phoenician
                        sphere of influence, while the bilingual inscription of the Tell Fakhariyya
                        statue (northeast Syria) points to an Akkadian linguistic and cultural
                        context. The script is nearly identical to the one found in the Phoenician
                        inscriptions, from which it was borrowed.</p>
                    <p>2. Imperial, or Official Aramaic (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 600 – <abbr>ca.</abbr> 200 BC). Already in the later
                        days of the Neo-Assyrian Empire (following the loss of independence of the
                        Aramean city states), Aramaic began to be used for trade and communication.
                        The expansion of Aramaic went on in the Neo-Babylonian Empire and culminated
                        in the ‘official’ status that Aramaic achieved (along with Persian and
                        Elamite) in the Achaemenid Persian Empire (mid-6th <abbr>cent.</abbr> – 330 BC). Along
                        with inscriptions, a great number of texts on papyrus, parchment, and
                        ostraca have been unearthed in Egypt. They evidence the use of Aramaic in
                        official documents issued by, and addressed to, the Persian administration,
                        in correspondence of a more private character, and in literary compositions.
                        The Aramaic documents in the biblical book of Ezra and their narrative
                        framework represent the same type of language. The official use of Aramaic
                        implied that there was a certain linguistic and orthographical standard,
                        even if individual texts often deviated from it. This standard remained
                        authoritative for several centuries after the fall of the Persian Empire.
                        Its literary variant has been called ‘Standard Literary Aramaic’.</p>
                    <p>3. Middle Aramaic (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 200 BC – <abbr>ca.</abbr> 250 AD). First, there is the continued
                        use of the earlier standardized language, in such texts as the Aramaic
                        chapters of the biblical book of Daniel, the Aramaic portions of the Dead
                        Sea documents, and the earliest layer of the Jewish Targumim, or
                        translations of the Hebrew Bible (Targum Onkelos for the Pentateuch and
                        Targum Jonathan for the Prophets). Second, there are corpora of Aramaic
                        inscriptions, produced in the Nabataean Empire (which had Petra as its
                        capital), and in the city states of Ḥaṭra, Palmyra, and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref>. These lost
                        their independence in the 2nd and 3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr> AD. The languages of these
                        places each slightly differ from one another and they are written in
                        slightly different scripts, derived from the script used in the Persian
                        period. Nabataean Aramaic exhibits features that are due to contact with Old
                        North Arabian, which was widely spoken throughout the Nabatean Empire.</p>
                    <p>4. Late Aramaic (3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr> to <abbr>ca.</abbr> 1200 AD). From this period literary texts
                        are preserved which received classical status in at least four different
                        religious communities. At the same time, a clear distinction emerges between
                        West-Aramaic and East-Aramaic dialects.</p>
                    <p>West-Aramaic texts were produced by Jews (Palestinian Targumim, Aramaic
                        portions in the Palestinian Talmud and in the Midrashim, Aramaic
                        compositions preserved among the Cairo Genizah documents  — many of the
                        texts mentioned represent the Galilean Aramaic dialect), Samaritans
                        (Targumim, hymns, and prose compositions); and Christians of the Jerusalem
                        area (<ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Christian-Palestinian-Aramaic">Christian Palestinian Aramaic</ref>).</p>
                    <p>East-Aramaic texts were produced by Jews (parts of the Babylonian Talmud and
                        Gaonic literature), Mandaeans (classical Mandaic literature), and Christians
                        (Syriac). The status of Syriac has been somewhat disputed. While Syriac
                        traditionally has been considered the westernmost of the East-Aramaic
                        languages, some scholars now tend to classify it as a separate branch of
                        late Aramaic. The language of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mani">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/608">Mani</persName>
                        </ref> and of the early
                        Manicheans must have been close to Syriac, but next to nothing has
                        survived.</p>
                    <p>Jewish Aramaic texts are written in the Hebrew square script, which itself is
                        an adaptation of the earlier Aramaic script. Samaritan Aramaic is written in
                        a separate script, which derives from the earlier Hebrew script.
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Christian-Palestinian</sic>
                            <corr>Christian Palestinian</corr>
                        </choice> Aramaic is written in a <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Script-Syriac">script</ref>
                        that is related to Esṭrangela, and Mandaic has its own script, likely
                        derived from the Parthian/Late Iranian scripts. An interesting genre that
                        existed across religious borders is that of the incantations written on
                        ‘magic bowls’: texts that are very similar exist in Jewish (Babylonian)
                        Aramaic, Mandaic, and Syriac (written either in Esṭrangela or in a different
                        script, which has been called ‘Proto-Manichean’).</p>
                    <p>Each of these languages had its heyday in the pre-Islamic period, when the
                        literary languages to a large extent reflected, and were nourished by, the
                        spoken languages. In the Islamic period, when Arabic became more prominent,
                        the literary languages gradually became disconnected from the waning spoken
                        dialects, which survived in geographical and social isolation.</p>
                    <p>5. Modern Aramaic, or Neo-Aramaic (to the present day). While the classical
                        languages, shaped and standardized in the previous period, continued to be
                        transmitted and written — and do so up to the present day  — the spoken
                        variants started having their own history, much of which went unrecorded. It
                        is only in the 17th <abbr>cent.</abbr> that some dialects began to be written for the
                        first time. This happened in Northern Iraq with Modern Jewish Aramaic and
                        with Modern Syriac (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sureth">Sureth</ref>), which was
                        written in and around <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Alqosh">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/19">Alqosh</placeName>
                        </ref>. In the 19th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr>, under the impulse of American missionaries, a new literary language
                        was created for the Christians of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Urmia">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/206">Urmia</placeName>
                        </ref> and its
                        surroundings. First used for a new translation of the Bible, Literary Urmia
                        Aramaic later was adapted and upgraded to serve as the vehicle of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Assyrians">Assyrian</ref> identity. As such it is still used today
                        among E.-Syr. Christians in the Middle East and in the worldwide <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diaspora">diaspora</ref>.</p>
                    <p>The modern spoken dialects are generally subdivided as follows:</p>
                    <p>a. West-Neo-Aramaic, spoken in Maʿlula and in a few neighboring villages to
                        the north of Damascus by Christians (Greek Orthodox and Greek Catholic) and
                        by some Muslims. This language may be seen as an offshoot of West-Aramaic,
                        described under 4. Some texts are available in contemporary scholarly
                        transliterations.</p>
                    <p>b. Central-Neo-Aramaic, of which the main dialect is <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Turoyo">Ṭuroyo</ref>, spoken in
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tur-Abdin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/221">Ṭur
                            ʿAbdin</placeName>
                        </ref>, mainly by <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Christians. The language is now
                        widespread among the Syr. Orth diaspora. There have been a few attempts to
                        write it down, most successfully among the Swedish communities (in Latin
                        script).</p>
                    <p>c. North-East-Neo-Aramaic, spoken to the east of the Tigris, in Eastern
                        Turkey, Persian Kurdistan, and Northern Iraq (north of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mosul">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/139">Mosul</placeName>
                        </ref>) by both
                        Christians and Jews. Due to massive relocation throughout the 20th <abbr>cent.</abbr>,
                        originally distinct languages have been mixed and cases of Koine formation
                        have emerged. Here again, many speakers live in the diaspora; Jewish Aramaic
                        lives on in Israel.</p>
                    <p>d. South-East-Neo-Aramaic, represented by much endangered Mandaic dialects,
                        spoken in southern Iraq and western Iran.</p>
                    <p>Each of these many modern dialects carries its own cultural and religious
                        tradition. Linguistically they share a number of features, particularly in
                        the radical transformation of the verbal system. In the lexicon, many
                        loanwords were borrowed from the surrounding languages along with phonetic,
                        morphological, and syntactical features.</p>
                    <p>In the Syriac tradition the term <hi rend="italic">ārāmāyā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">oromoyo</hi>) is often used, along with <hi rend="italic">suryāyā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">suryoyo</hi>), to denote the Syriac
                        language. Syriac rewriting of texts originally composed in other Aramaic
                        languages may be found in the Aramaic sections of the Old Testament and in
                        such texts as the story of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ahiqar">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/323">Aḥiqar</persName>
                        </ref>. An awareness
                        of an Aramean unity, based on the language (<hi rend="italic">leššānā</hi> /
                            <hi rend="italic">lešono</hi>) and the written tradition (<hi rend="italic">seprā</hi> / <hi rend="italic">sepro</hi>), extending from
                        the first Chaldean and Assyrian kings to the Christian Syrians, can be found
                        in the second Appendix added to the Chronicle of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Michael-Badoqa">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/637">Michael
                            Rabo</persName>
                        </ref>, which deals with ‘the kingdoms that have been established in
                        Antiquity by our race, (that of) the Arameans, namely the descendants of
                        Aram, who were called Syrians or inhabitants of Syria’ (<abbr>ed.</abbr> J. B. Chabot,
                        text in vol. 4, 748–51; <abbr>FT</abbr> in vol. 3, 442–7). Among the present-day
                        Syr. Christians the Aramaic heritage is particularly emphasized by the Syr.
                        Orth.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>K.  Beyer, <title rend="italic">Die aramäischen Texte vom Toten
                                Meer</title> (1984); <title rend="italic">Ergänzungsband</title>
                            (1994).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>K. Beyer</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">The Aramaic language</title> (1986). (= <abbr>ET</abbr>
                            by J. F. Healey of p. 23–76 of Beyer’s 1984 publication)</bibl>
                        <bibl>D.  Boyarin, ‘An Inquiry into the formation of the Middle Aramaic
                            dialects’, in <title rend="italic">Bono homini donum. Essays in
                                historical linguistics in memory of J. A. Kerns</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> Y. L.
                            Arbeitman and A. R. Bomhard, vol. 2 (1981), 613–49.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. P.  Brock, ‘Three thousand years of Aramaic literature’, <title rend="italic">ARAM</title> 1 (1989), 11–23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, esp. vol.
                            1. <title rend="italic">The ancient Aramaic heritage</title>; vol.  2.
                            (with W.  Balicka-Witakowski and W.  Witakowski) <title rend="italic">The heirs of the ancient Aramaic heritage</title>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>R.  Contini, ‘Hypothèses sur l’araméen manichéen’, <title rend="italic">Annali di Ca’ Foscari</title> 34 (1995),
                            65–107.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>R. Contini</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘L’orizzonte linguistico della Chiesa di Persia: considerazioni
                            preliminari’, <choice>
                                <sic/>
                                <corr>in </corr>
                            </choice>
                            <title rend="italic">Storia, cristologia e tradizioni
                                della Chiesa Siro-orientale</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> E. Vergani and S. Chialà
                            (2006), 47–77.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. A.  Fitzmyer, ‘The phases of the Aramaic Language’, in <title rend="italic">A Wandering Aramean. Collected Aramaic Essays</title>
                            (<abbr>SBL</abbr> Monographs 25; 1979), 57–84.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. C. Greenfield, ‘Standard Literary Aramaic’, in <title rend="italic">Actes du premier congrès international de linguistique sémitique et
                                chamito-sémitique</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Caquot and D. Cohen (1974),
                            280–89.</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Gzella and M. L.  Folmer (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Aramaic in
                                its historical and linguistic setting</title> (Akademie der
                            Wissenschaften und der Literatur, Mainz. Veröffentlichungen der
                            Orientalischen Kommission 50; 2008).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. F. Healey, <title rend="italic">Aramaic inscriptions and documents
                                of the Roman period</title> (Textbook of Syrian Semitic Inscriptions
                            4; 2009).</bibl>
                        <bibl>W.  Heinrichs (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Studies in
                                Neo-Aramaic</title> (Harvard Semitic Studies 36; 1990).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Huehnergard, ‘What is Aramaic?’, <title rend="italic">ARAM</title>
                            7 (1995), 261–282.</bibl>
                        <bibl>O. Jastrow, ‘Neo-Aramaic Dialectology. The state of the art’, <title rend="italic">Israel Oriental Studies</title> 20 (2002),
                            365–77.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. A.  Kaufman, ‘Aramaic’, in <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>AB</abbr>D</title>, vol. 4
                            (1992), 173–8.</bibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Lipiński, <title rend="italic">The Arameans. Their ancient
                                history, culture, religion</title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 100; 2000).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Mengozzi, <title rend="italic">Israel of Alqosh and Joseph of
                                Telkepe. A story in a truthful language. Religious poems in
                                vernacular Syriac (North Iraq, 17th century)</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 589–90;
                            2002).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H. L.  Murre-van den Berg, <title rend="italic">From a spoken to a
                                written language. The introduction and development of Literary Urmia
                                Aramaic in the nineteenth century</title> (Publications of the De
                            Goeje Fund 28; 1999).</bibl>
                        <bibl>F.  Rosenthal, <title rend="italic">Die aramaistische Forschung seit
                                Th. Nöldeke’s Veröffentlichungen</title> (1939).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Weltecke, <title rend="italic">Die «Beschreibung der Zeiten»</title>,
                            222–32.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename> 
                  <surname>Van Rompay</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
