<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Art and architecture</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename> 
                  <surname>Van Rompay</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Art and architecture</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Art-and-architecture</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/59</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">50</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="37-43"/>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">A comprehensive study of Syr. Christian art and
                        architecture is still missing, and only a few subfields are relatively well
                        covered in overview monographs. This entry offers a survey of several key areas.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>A comprehensive study of Syr. Christian art and architecture is still
                        missing, and only a few subfields are relatively well covered in overview
                        monographs, such as the architecture of Syria west of the Euphrates (Butler;
                        Lassus; Tchalenko), floor mosaics in churches of Syria and Lebanon
                        (Donceel-Voûte), manuscript illumination (Leroy 1964), and wall paintings in
                        Syria and Lebanon (Cruikshank Dodd; Immerzeel 2009). Given Syr.
                        Christianity’s intertwinement, throughout its history, with other
                        linguistic, cultural, and religious traditions, the definition of what
                        constitutes ‘Syr. Christian’ art or architecture is somewhat elusive and
                        should not be attempted here. In the early period much of Syr. Christianity
                        was situated in the Roman Empire, in which there was a great deal of overlap
                        between Syr. Christian and Greek Christian art and culture. In the Islamic
                        period certain forms of art were shared between Syr. Christians and Muslims.
                        In addition, the proximity of Byzantine Christianity or even Western
                        Christianity (esp. in the period of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Crusades">Crusades</ref>) had its
                        impact on themes and forms of expressions. There is some evidence in the
                        early Syr. tradition of the use of portable icons (the image of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref>,
                        which was believed to be a portrait of Jesus, being the most famous of
                        these), but it is only among the Christians of the Chalcedonian traditions
                        (Melkite and Maronite) that the art of icon painting flourished and that
                        local styles emerged, such as in the 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> in Tripoli and in the 17th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aleppo">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/18">Aleppo</placeName>
                        </ref>. In the other Syr. traditions (<abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> and <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr>)
                        the cult of images in whatever form never became as prominent as it was in
                        the Byzantine tradition, even though there is no evidence of any opposition
                        to the use of figurative art, and suggestions that Syr. Christianity was
                        somehow connected to the iconoclastic movement within the Byzantine
                        tradition or to any other an-iconic tradition should be rejected (Brock
                        2004; Teule). In general, the study of Syr. Christian art and architecture
                        is seriously hampered by the fact that the surviving remains are fragmentary
                        and mostly deprived of their original context. Accompanying <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Inscriptions">inscriptions</ref>, occasionally containing dates and names, may
                        provide crucial information. In the present overview only a few areas will
                        be highlighted.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">1. Pre-Christian Edessa</label>
                    <p>The art of the semi-independent kingdom of Edessa is accessible to us in a
                        number of funerary mosaics, dated or datable to the first three <abbr>cent.</abbr> AD
                        (prior to the mid–3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr>). Some of these show portraits of the deceased,
                        often with their family; others have topics or figures from Greco-Roman
                        antiquity, such as the Phoenix or Orpheus playing the lyre. Reflecting the
                        life of the urban aristocracy, the mosaics show the proximity of the
                        Parthian world, in particular in the costumes (Leroy 1957). Most of the
                        mosaics (some of which are dated in their inscriptions) are contemporaneous
                        with the nascent Christian communities in Edessa, and with our earliest
                        Christian authors, such as <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bardaisan">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bardaiṣan</persName>
                        </ref>, but
                        none of them can be identified as specifically Christian (Drijvers and
                        Healey; Healey; Segal).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">2. Christian Architecture in Syria, Ṭur ʿAbdin, and
                        Mesopotamia</label>
                    <p>The earliest dated church in the Syr. Christian area is the church of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Nisibis">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/811">Yaʿqub of Nisibis</persName>
                        </ref> which in a baptistery inscription that survives
                        to the present day is dated to 359, <choice>
                            <sic>i.e. </sic>
                            <corr>i.e., </corr>
                        </choice>the time when <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ephrem">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem</persName>
                        </ref> lived in the
                        city. Even though we are in the easternmost corner of the Roman Empire and
                        in the heartland of Syr. Christianity, the inscription is not in Syriac, but
                        in Greek.
                    </p>
                    <p>Most of the evidence for churches between the 4th and 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr> is from the
                        region between <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Antioch">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>
                        </ref> and Aleppo.
                        Known as the ‘Dead cities’, because they were abandoned in the early Islamic
                        period due to shifting patterns of economy and trade (and are still largely
                        deserted today), numerous sites show the secular and religious buildings of
                        villages and medium-size communities. Several churches are impressive, and
                        the architectural skeleton of some of them is well-preserved, having been
                        exposed to the forces of nature only, not to re-use or destruction by
                        humans. Some churches are very small (such as the single-aisled church of
                        Qirqbize). Other churches derive their importance from their role as pilgrim
                        destinations, such as the church of Qalbloze, and above all the magnificent
                        church of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemun-the-Stylite">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/744">Shemʿun the
                            Stylite</persName>
                        </ref>, which was built in the late 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> and which consists
                        of four three-aisled basilicas converging on the saint’s pillar. Even today
                        the scattered ruins and the very refined capital sculptures evoke the
                        church’s former majesty. Another popular pilgrim destination, which
                        flourished in the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, is the shrine of Mar Sargis (St. Sergius) in
                        Resafa, more eastwards in the Syrian steppe (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 160  km. southeast of
                        Aleppo).</p>
                    <p>The region of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tur-Abdin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/221">Ṭur ʿAbdin</placeName>
                        </ref> and
                        the wider area around it also preserve some of the earliest churches of Syr.
                        Christianity, some of which were expanded throughout the centuries and are
                        still in use today. The well-preserved main church of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Zafaran-Dayr">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/69">Dayr
                            al-Zaʿfarān</placeName>
                        </ref> dates back to the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, while some of the
                        rebuilding and refurbishment of the church of the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Gabriel-Monastery-of-Mor">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/226">Monastery of Mor Gabriel</placeName>
                        </ref> can be dated to the reign of the
                        Byzantine emperor Anastasius (<abbr>r.</abbr> 491–518). Several other churches in this
                        area go back to the early Islamic period, such as the church of Ḥaḥ and the
                        church of the Holy Cross, in the monastery of the same name (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Salib-Dayr">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/68">Dayr
                            al-Ṣalīb</placeName>
                        </ref>).</p>
                    <p>A special architectural feature in some of the earliest churches is the bema.
                        This is a raised platform, usually horseshoe-shaped and with low walls,
                        which is located in the middle of the nave and on which the liturgy of the
                        Word was performed. The above-mentioned churches of Qirqbize, Qalbloze, and
                        Resafa provide interesting examples, while detached pieces of the bema
                        construction have found their way to modern museums, such as the stone bema
                        lectern of Bennawi, which is presently shown in the garden of the National
                        Museum of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Damascus">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/66">Damascus</placeName>
                        </ref> (Brock and Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</hi>,
                        vol. 2, 43). In recent years the bema has received considerable attention,
                        both from liturgists and archeologists (Cassis, Loosley, Renhart, and
                        Taft).</p>
                    <p>Several other detached pieces of church decoration, chancel panels, or door
                        lintels, exhibiting ornamental motifs or iconographical themes, are found
                        scattered all over the world. Two chancel panels in stone, uncovered at Rasm
                        al-Qanafez (to the east of Salamiyya, Syria) and presently in the National
                        Museum of Damascus, show Daniel among the lions and the three Magi
                        approaching the Virgin with Child (<hi rend="italic">Syrie</hi>, 358–59;
                        Peña, 84).</p>
                    <p>Floor mosaics as well often have left their original location. Most of the
                        mosaics belonging to churches in Syria and Lebanon have conveniently been
                        brought together by P. Donceel-Voûte, with the ‘Adam mosaic’ in the
                        Michaelion of Huarte (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 15 km. north-northeast of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Apamea">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/11">Apamea</placeName>
                        </ref>) as one of
                        the highlights (Donceel-Voûte, 105), to be compared with the royal Adam
                        shown on a mosaic panel in the Museum of Ḥama, the latter with a Greek and
                        Syriac caption (ibid., 113; also in Brock and Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</hi>, vol. 2, 41). More recently beautiful mosaics have
                        been uncovered at Tall Biʿa, near Raqqaʿ/Kallinikos, in the church of a
                        monastery that may have been the Monastery of Mar Zakkay, to which <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yuhanon-of-Tella">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/50">Yuḥanon of Tella</persName>
                        </ref> once belonged (Kalla, with further
                        references).</p>
                    <p>While by far the largest part of our evidence for the early period belongs to
                        the W.-Syr. tradition (in particular <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> and Melkite), there has been
                        in recent years considerable and promising archeological activity in the
                        geographical area of the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> (Hauser; Kröger, with further
                        references). The Christian monuments of Iraq (belonging to either the Ch. of
                        E. or the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> tradition), a number of which go back to the first
                        millennium, have been surveyed by Fiey in his three-volume publication <hi rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne</hi>, while the same scholar devoted a
                        separate volume to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mosul">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/139">Mosul</placeName>
                        </ref> (1959). Sites
                        of particular significance are the city of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tagrit">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/193">Tagrit</placeName>
                        </ref> (Harrak
                        2001), <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Matay-Dayro-d-Mor">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/227">Dayro d-Mor
                            Matay</persName>
                        </ref> and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Behnam-Dayro-d-Mor">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/225">Dayro d-Mor
                            Behnam</placeName>
                        </ref> (nowadays <abbr>Syr. Cath.</abbr>), with its exceptional 13th-cent.
                        carvings on the main entrance door. There is also some evidence of building
                        activity associated with the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> in the Holy Land, in particular a
                        hermitage near Jericho (Fiey 1983, and Brock and Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</hi>, vol. 2, 46) and possibly a monastic complex at Tel
                        Masos, in the northern Negev (Fritz and Maiberger).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">3. Manuscript Illumination</label>
                    <p>An excellent survey of illuminated <abbr>mss.</abbr> kept in Western and Middle-Eastern
                        libraries, with detailed analysis, is available in Leroy 1964. The most
                        significant set of early illuminations is found in the opening quire of the
                        6th-cent. <abbr>ms.</abbr> that contains the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Rabbula-Gospels">Rabbula
                            Gospels</ref> (named after the scribe of the Gospel text), with its
                        richly decorated canon tables and its full-page illuminations. Of the same
                        period, or possibly slightly later, is the so-called ‘Syriac Bible from
                        Paris’ (Paris, Bibl. Nat. Syr. 341), which contains mostly <abbr>OT</abbr> themes and
                        figures (Sörries). The art of <abbr>ms.</abbr> illumination came to full fruition in the
                        11th to 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr>: along with biblical <abbr>mss.</abbr>, such as the ‘Buchanan Bible’
                        (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Cambridge, Univ. Libr. <choice>
                     <reg>Oo. I.1,2</reg>
                     <orig>Oo.I.1,2</orig>
                  </choice>; on which, see Hunt), there are a
                        number of lectionaries, most of them belonging to the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> tradition.
                        The number of E.-Syr. illuminated <abbr>mss.</abbr> is very limited (for some 15th-cent.
                        examples, see Leroy, 417–18 and 393–403; Brock and Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</hi>, vol. 2, 237–38). In the 16th <abbr>cent.</abbr> the tradition of
                        <abbr>ms.</abbr> illumination was given new life among the Chaldeans (see e.g. <abbr>ms.</abbr> Borgia
                        Syr. 169, Leroy, 404–8). For more recent studies, esp. on the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        <abbr>mss.</abbr> of the 11th–13th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, see e.g. Doumato. It should also be noted that
                        <abbr>ms.</abbr> illumination is not limited to the <abbr>mss.</abbr> of the mainstream ecclesiastical
                        traditions, but is also found, e.g., in magic <abbr>mss.</abbr> (Balicka-Witakowska
                        2008).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">4. Wall Paintings</label>
                    <p>Most of the late antique churches must have contained painting, either of a
                        purely ornamental nature or intended to provide instruction or to impart
                        devotion. Remains of painting can be found on some of the ruins, but no full
                        Christian wall paintings from the first millennium have survived. The <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Wall-paintings-in-Syria-and-Lebanon">wall paintings in Syria and Lebanon</ref> deserve separate attention,
                        with those of <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Musa-al-Habashi-Dayr-Mar">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/228">Dayr Mār
                            Mūsā al-Ḥabashī</placeName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Qara">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/161">Qara</placeName>
                        </ref>, and the Lebanese
                        Qadisha Valley as unmistakable highlights. Most of these belong to the
                        period between the 11th and 13th century. To the same period in all
                        likelihood belongs a newly discovered wall painting in the church of Mar
                        Gewargis in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Qaraqosh">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/262">Qaraqosh</placeName>
                        </ref>, near Mosul, representing the Baptism of Jesus (Snelders
                        2007). The art of wall painting continued well into the modern area.
                        Interesting 18th-cent. examples are found in the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> church of
                        Sergius and Bacchus in Ṣadad, <abbr>ca.</abbr> 100 km. north east of Damascus (Brock and
                        Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</hi>, vol. 2, 147–50).</p>
                    <p>In addition to the heartlands of Syr. Christianity, wall paintings reflecting
                        Syriac Christianity may be found in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Suryan-Dayr">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/360">Dayr
                            al-Suryān</placeName>
                        </ref> in Egypt, which from the early 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> onwards had a
                        mixed Coptic and Syriac monastic population. While the earliest paintings in
                        the main Church of the monastery predate the arrival of Syr. monks, some of
                        the later paintings must reflect the interests and taste of the Syr. monks.
                        This may be the case for the probably 10th-cent. painting of the Three
                        Patriarchs (Innemée 1998), and even more so for the very fragmentarily
                        preserved paintings of Emperor Constantine and King Abgar (holding the <hi rend="italic">mandylion</hi>), both of which are accompanied by Syriac
                        inscriptions and may also belong to the 10th  cent. (Innemée and Van
                        Rompay). Fully preserved paintings in three half-domes of the church, with
                        Syriac inscriptions, belong to the early 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> (Leroy 1982).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">5. Liturgical Vessels and Accessories</label>
                    <p>A large number of 5th- or 6th-cent. liturgical objects from Syria have been
                        uncovered in the course of the 20th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, in the area south-west of Aleppo
                        (Mundell Mango). In some cases inscriptions provide information on the date
                        and on the church to which the objects belonged: Kaper Koraon (the exact
                        location of which is uncertain) and Beth Misona (three chalices and a paten,
                        now in the Cleveland Museum of Art). While the link with Syriac Christianity
                        seems to be obvious, the inscriptions are in Greek, not in Syriac. A rare
                        Syriac inscribed silver dish from the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, in the collection of the
                        Hermitage Museum, St. Petersburg, has been made popular among Syr. scholars
                        by R. Murray’s <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom</hi> (1975
                        and 2004). It represents the Ascension, the women at the tomb, and the
                        Crucifixion, along with soldiers, Peter and the cock, and Daniel in the
                        lions’ den.</p>
                    <p>To a slightly later period, perhaps 8th or 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, belongs a very well
                        preserved bronze incense burner uncovered in Takrit (now in the National
                        Museum of Baghdad); it has nine scenes from the life of Jesus (Harrak 2006),
                        but no inscriptions.</p>
                    <p>From the early 13th-cent. a bronze liturgical fan is preserved (<hi rend="italic">marwḥā</hi> or <hi rend="italic">marwaḥtā</hi>,
                        ‘flabellum’), now housed in the Belgian Museum of Mariemont. The Syr.
                        inscription reports that it was made in 1202/3 for Dayr al-Suryān in Egypt;
                        it may have been produced in a workshop in the Mosul area (Snelders and
                        Immerzeel). To the same period belongs the church treasure of Resafa, which
                        includes a skillfully decorated silver chalice and a paten, both bearing
                        inscriptions in Syriac (even though the objects may have been of Western
                        origin or inspiration). The paten was a gift to the church of St. Sergius at
                        Resafa by Ḥasnon of Edessa. These objects had probably been buried in order
                        to be saved from the Mongol invasions of 1259/60 (Ulbert; Brock and Taylor,
                            <hi rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</hi>, vol. 2, 212).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">6. Liturgical Vestments</label>
                    <p>While some information on liturgical vestments may be extracted from literary
                        sources and from depictions in <abbr>ms.</abbr> illuminations and wall paintings, a rare
                        piece, presently housed in the New York Metropolitan Museum of Art, has
                        recently been studied: a bishop’s stole (<hi rend="italic">batrashil</hi>),
                            bearing inscriptions in Syriac and Arabic. It was made for
                        <abbr>Bp.</abbr> Athanasius Abraham Yaghmur of Nabk in 1534–35 (Ball).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">7. Syr. Christian Art in the 21st Century</label>
                    <p>While the precious remains of ancient Syr. Christian art and architecture
                        nowadays are receiving more attention from Syr. scholars and Syr. Christians
                        alike, Syr. Christians at the same time are creating their own art forms,
                        often inspired by the treasures of the past, to which they add new layers of
                        interpretation and meaning according to their present-day situation.
                        Churches are being renovated or new churches are being built in the Middle
                        East, in India, and in the worldwide <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diaspora">
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Diaspora</sic>
                                <corr>diaspora</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </ref>. In many
                        of these churches the ancient art of wall painting is brought to new life,
                        while present-day liturgical publications often reflect the illuminated
                        manuscripts of the past (for the Maronite tradition, see e.g. Badwi).</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/1">Fig. 1</ref>, <choice>
                            <sic>9–15</sic>
                            <corr>
                                <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/9">9</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/10">10</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/11">11</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/12c">12c</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/13">13</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/14">14</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/15">15</ref>
                            </corr>
                        </choice>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/62">62</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/63">63</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/64">64</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/65">65</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/71c">71c</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/77c">77c</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/80">80</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/86">86</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/88c">88c</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/101">101</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/104c">104c</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/112">112</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/115">115</ref>, <choice>
                            <sic>and 116–118</sic>
                            <corr>
                                <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/116">116</ref>,
                                    <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/117">117</ref>,
                                and <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/118">118</ref>
                            </corr>
                        </choice>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Badwi, <title rend="italic">The liturgical year iconography
                                of the Syro-Maronite Church</title> (2006).</bibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Balicka-Witakowska, ‘Illustrating charms: A Syriac manuscript with
                            magic drawings in the collection of the British Library’, in <title rend="italic">Malphono w-Rabo d-Malphone</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> G. A. Kiraz,
                            779–808.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. L.  Ball, ‘A sixteenth-century Batrashil in the Metropolitan Museum
                            of Art’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                            </title> 9.1 (2006).</bibl>
                        <bibl>S.<choice>
                        <reg>P.</reg>
                        <orig/>
                     </choice>  Brock, ‘Iconoclasm and the Monophysites’, in <title rend="italic">Iconoclasm. Papers given at the ninth Spring Symposium of Byzantine
                                Studies</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Bryer and J. Herrin (1977), 53–7.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>S. P. Brock</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Transformations of the Edessa portrait of Christ’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JAAS</abbr>
                            </title> 18 (2004), 46–56.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, vol. 2,
                            esp. 209–41. (‘The arts: Architecture, wall painting and manuscript
                            illumination’)</bibl>
                        <bibl>H. C.  Butler, <title rend="italic">Early Churches in Syria</title>
                            (1929).</bibl>
                        <bibl>M.  Cassis, ‘The bema in the East Syriac church in light of new
                            archaeological evidence’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                            </title> 5.2
                            (2002).</bibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Cruikshank Dodd, <title rend="italic">Medieval Painting in the
                                Lebanon</title> (2004).</bibl>
                        <bibl>P.  Donceel-Voûte, <title rend="italic">Les pavements des églises
                                byzantines de Syrie et du Liban. Décor, archéologie et
                                liturgie</title> (Publications d’histoire de l’art et d’archéologie
                            de l’Université catholique de Louvain 69; 1988).</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.  Doumato, ‘Patriarch Michael the Great: iconoclast or art patron’,
                                <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>CahArch</abbr>
                            </title> 49 (2001), 29–38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.  Doumato, ‘The illustrated pontifical of Patriarch Ignatius II:
                            text, image and reader in the Syriac tradition’, <title rend="italic">Arte cristiana</title> 91 (2003), 423–36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Drijvers and Healey, <title rend="italic">The Old Syriac
                                inscriptions</title>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fiey, <title rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne</title>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Doumato</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Mossoul chrétienne. Essai sur l’histoire,
                                l’archéologie et l’état actuel des monuments chrétiens de la ville
                                de Mossoul</title> (Recherches publiées sous la direction de
                            l’Institut de lettres orientales de Beyrouth 12; 1959).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Doumato</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Rabban Bûya de Shaqlâwâ et de Jéricho’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>POC</abbr>
                            </title> 33 (1983), 34–8.</bibl>
                        <bibl>V.  Fritz and P.  Maiberger, ‘Das nestorianische Kloster’, in <title rend="italic">Ergebnisse der Ausgrabungen auf der Hirbet al-Msas
                                (Tel Masos) 1972–1975</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> V. Fritz and A. Kempinski,
                            (1983), 138–216.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Harrak, ‘Recent archaeological excavations in Takrit and the
                            discovery of Syriac inscriptions’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JCSSS</abbr>
                            </title> 1
                            (2001), 11–40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>A.  Harrak</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘The incense burner of Takrit: An iconographical analysis’,
                                <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 3 (2006), 47–52.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. R.  Hauser, ‘Christliche Archäologie im Sasanidenreich: Grundlagen
                            der Interpretation und Bestandsaufnahme der Evidenz’, in <title rend="italic">Inkulturation des Christentums im
                                Sasanidenreich</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A.  Mustafa, J.  Tubach, and G. S.
                            Vashalomidze (2007), 93–136.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. F.  Healey, ‘A new Syriac mosaic inscription’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JSS</abbr>
                            </title> 51 (2006), 313–27.</bibl>
                        <bibl>N.  Hélou, ‘À propos d’une école syro-libanaise d’icônes au XIII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title>
                            3 (2006), 53–72.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.-A.  Hunt, ‘The Syriac Buchanan Bible in Cambridge: Book
                            illumination in Syria, Cilicia and Jerusalem of the later twelfth
                            century’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OCP</abbr>
                            </title> 57 (1991), 331–69.</bibl>
                        <bibl>M.  Immerzeel, <title rend="italic">Identity puzzles. Medieval
                                Christian art in Syria and Lebanon</title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 184; 2009).</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. Immerzeel and N. Hélou, ‘Icon painting in the County of Tripoli of
                            the thirteenth century’, in <title rend="italic">Interactions. Artistic
                                interchange between the eastern and western worlds in the Medieval
                                period</title> (The Index of Christian Art Occasional Papers 9;
                            2007), 67–83.</bibl>
                        <bibl>K. C.  Innemée, ‘Recent discoveries of wall-paintings in Deir
                            al-Surian’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                            </title> 1.2 (1998).</bibl>
                        <bibl>K. C.  Innemée and L.  Van Rompay, ‘Deir al-Surian (Egypt): New
                            discoveries of 2001–2002’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                            </title> 5.2
                            (2002).</bibl>
                        <bibl>G. Kalla, ‘Christentum am oberen Euphrat. Das byzantinische Kloster
                            von Tall Biʿa’, <title rend="italic">Antike Welt</title> 30 (1999),
                            131–42.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Kröger, ‘Die Kirche auf dem Hügel Qaṣr bint al-Qāḍī und weitere
                            Zeugnisse christlichen Lebens im Bereich des sasanidischen Metropole
                            Ktesiphon’, in <title rend="italic">Inkulturation des Christentums im
                                Sasanidenreich</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Mustafa, J. Tubach, and G. S.
                            Vashalomidze (2007), 137–57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Lassus, <title rend="italic">Sanctuaires chrétiens de Syrie. Essai
                                sur la genèse, la forme et l’usage liturgique des édifices du culte
                                chrétien, en Syrie, du III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle à la
                                conquête musulmane</title> (Institut français d’archéologie de
                            Beyrouth. Bibliothèque archéologique et historique 42; 1947).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Leroy, ‘Mosaïques funéraires d’Édesse’, <title rend="italic">Syria</title> 34 (1957), 306–342, with plates XXI–XXII.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J. Leroy</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Les manuscrits syriaques à peintures
                                conservés dans les bibliothèques d’Europe et d’Orient. Contribution
                                à l’étude de l’iconographie des églises de langue syriaque</title>
                            (Institut français d’archéologie de Beyrouth. Bibliothèque archéologique
                            et historique 77; 1964) (with separate Album).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Leroy, <title rend="italic">Les peintures des couvents du Ouadi
                                Natroun</title> (= La peinture murale chez les Coptes 2; Mémoires
                            publiés par les membres de l’Institut français d’archéologie orientale
                            du Caire 101; 1982).</bibl>
                        <bibl>E. Loosley, <title rend="italic">The architecture and liturgy of the
                                bema in fourth- to sixth-century Syrian churches</title> (Patrimoine
                            syriaque 2; 2003).</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. Mundell Mango, <title rend="italic">Silver from early Byzantium.
                                The Kaper Koraon and related treasures</title> (1986).</bibl>
                        <bibl>I. Peña, <title rend="italic">The Christian art of Byzantine
                                Syria</title> (1996).</bibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Renhart, <title rend="italic">Das syrische Bema.
                                Liturgisch-archäologische Untersuchungen</title> (Grazer Theologische
                            Studien 20; 1995).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Rumscheid, ‘Familienbilder im Haus der Ewigkeit. Zu Grabmosaiken
                            aus Edessa’, in <title rend="italic">Edessa in hellenistisch-römischer
                                Zeit. Religion, Kultur und Politik zwischen Ost und West</title>,
                            <abbr>ed.</abbr> L. Greisiger <abbr>et al.</abbr> (<abbr>BTS</abbr> 116; 2009), 255–65.</bibl>
                        <bibl>E. M.  Ruprechtsberger (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Syrien. Von den
                                Aposteln zu den Khalifen</title> (Linzer archäologische Forschungen
                            21; 1993).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A. Schmidt and S. Westphalen (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Christliche
                                Wandmalereien in Syrien. Qara und das Kloster Mar Yakub</title>
                            (<abbr>SKCO</abbr> 14; 2005).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. B. Segal, <title rend="italic">Edessa, the blessed city</title>
                            (1970).</bibl>
                        <bibl>B. Snelders, ‘A newly discovered wall painting in the Church of Mar
                            Giworgis in Qaraqosh, Iraq’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 4 (2007),
                            27–48.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>B. Snelders</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Identity and Christian-Muslim interaction.
                                Medieval art from the Syrian Orthodox in the Mosul area</title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr>
                            198; 2010).</bibl>
                        <bibl>B.  Snelders and M.  Immerzeel, ‘The thirteenth-century flabellum from
                            Deir al-Surian in the Musée Royal de Mariemont (Morlanwelz, Belgium).
                            With an appendix on the Syriac inscriptions by L. Van Rompay’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 1 (2004), 113–39.</bibl>
                        <bibl>R. Sörries, <title rend="italic">Die Syrische Bibel von Paris. Paris,
                                Bibliothèque Nationale, syr. 341. Eine frühchristliche
                                Bilderhandschrift aus dem 6. Jahrhundert</title> (1991).</bibl>
                        <bibl>C.  Strube, <title rend="italic">Baudekoration im nordsyrischen
                                Kalksteinmassiv</title> (Damaszener Forschungen 5; 1993).</bibl>
                        <bibl>eadem, <title rend="italic">Die „Toten Städte“. Stadt und Land in
                                Nordsyrien während der Spätantike</title> (1996).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <title rend="italic">Syrie. Mémoire et civilisation</title> (Exhibition
                            catalogue Institut du monde arabe, Paris; 1993).</bibl>
                        <bibl>R.  Taft, ‘Some notes on the Bema in the East and West Syrian
                            traditions’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OCP</abbr>
                            </title> 34 (1968), 326–59.</bibl>
                        <bibl>G. Tchalenko, <title rend="italic">Villages antiques de la Syrie du
                                Nord. Le massif du Bélus à l’époque romaine</title>, I–III (Institut
                            français d’archéologie de Beyrouth. Bibliothèque archéologique et
                            historique 50; 1953–8).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Teule, ‘The veneration of images in the East Syriac tradition’, in
                                <title rend="italic">Die Welt der Götterbilder</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> B.
                            Groneberg and H. Spieckermann (Beihefte zur <abbr>ZAW</abbr> 376; 2007),
                            324–46.</bibl>
                        <bibl>T. Ulbert, <title rend="italic">Der kreuzfahrerzeitliche Silberschatz
                                aus Resafa-Sergiupolis</title> (Resafa 3; 1990).</bibl>
                        <bibl>G. Wiessner, <title rend="italic">Christliche Kultbauten im Tur
                                Abdin</title> (<abbr>GOF</abbr> II.4; 1982).</bibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Zayat and M. Immerzeel (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Documentation
                                and conservation of art in Syria. Papers of the workshop held at
                                Damascus University 16–19 September 1996</title> (2000). (in English
                            and Arabic)</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename> 
                  <surname>Van Rompay</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
