<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Crusades</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Dorothea</forename> 
                  <surname>Weltecke</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Crusades</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Crusades</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/150</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">141</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="107-109"/>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">A specific form of Holy War initiated by
                        the pope directed towards the conquest of Jerusalem and elsewhere, that resulted in temporary establishment of Latin rule in regions of the Levant.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Crusades were a specific form of Holy War initiated by the pope. The
                        canonical legitimacy of the Crusades was constituted by the papal
                        convocation, the papal indulgences, and the vows taken by the participating
                        knights. For the Syr. Christians the Crusades at the time had simultaneously
                        positive and negative effects. In the long term the Crusades enhanced
                        religious polarization and undermined the position of Christians in Muslim
                        countries.</p>
                    <p>At the Council of Piacenza, in March 1095, the Byzantine Emperor Alexios I
                        Komnenos (1081–1118) requested Latin military aid against the expanding
                        Muslim forces. With a view of restoring the union of the church and claiming
                        for himself universal ecclesiastical authority, Pope Urban II (1088–99)
                        began to campaign for a war aimed at liberating the Holy Places. He appealed
                        to already existing conceptions of Holy War and developed them into a theory
                        of an armed pilgrimage. At the Council of Clermont-Ferrand, in Nov. 1095,
                        his idea of fighting a war for God met with immense religious enthusiasm.
                        When the knights set out for <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Jerusalem">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>
                        </ref> in
                        1096, they were joined by pilgrims and ardent non-combatants of different
                        origins. Pope Urban had ignited a formidable movement, which was difficult
                        to control and which resulted in fundamental political, cultural, and
                        economical changes in Europe and the Middle East.</p>
                    <p>Several vast military campaigns ensued, which were often led by the most
                        powerful crowned heads of Europe. The Crusade of 1096 being the first, the
                        next ones are traditionally counted as the Second Crusade (1145–1149), the
                        Third Crusade (1187–92), the Fourth Crusade (1198–1204), the so-called
                        Children’s Crusade of 1212, the Fifth Crusade (1217–1221), the Crusade of
                        Frederick II (1228–1229) and the Crusades of King Louis  IX the Pious of
                        France (1248–54, 1267–70). In addition, many more military campaigns with
                        papal authorization were waged against Muslims between the 12th and the 15th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> None of these, however, succeeded in bringing the expansion of the
                        Turks to a halt, nor did they prevent the conquest of Constantinople in
                        1453. In Europe Crusades were waged against pagan peoples, against heretical
                        movements, as well as against political enemies of the pope. The Reconquista
                        on the Iberian Peninsula also became part of the Crusade movement. Even
                        though criticism flared up against individual wars, the concept of Crusades
                        as well as the ideal of the virtuous knightly Crusader remained strong.</p>
                    <p>Jerusalem was first captured in the year 1099. Against the wishes of the
                        Byzantine emperor, who had expected the return of the re-conquered regions
                        to his own rule, Latin Crusader States were established in the Levant as a
                        result of the First Crusade (Kingdom of Jerusalem, County of Tripoli,
                        Principality of Antioch, County of Edessa). The ruling French and Norman
                        families by and large implemented the legal traditions of their homelands.
                        Within the Crusader States all non-Latins were legally subordinated. On the
                        local level traditional forms of autonomy and jurisdiction remained intact.
                        The descendents of the first Crusaders developed a new Middle-Eastern
                        identity and specific forms of relations to, as well as agreements with,
                        Eastern Christians and Muslims. These Crusader States, although much reduced
                        toward the coast, were sustained until the year 1291, which saw the fall of
                        Acre.</p>
                    <p>As for the Christians, the discriminating poll tax under Muslim rule was
                        lifted. The Greek Orthodox hierarchy was forced under the supremacy of a new
                        Latin hierarchy built up in the Crusader states. Local Christians of the
                        Greek Orthodox denomination are known as the ‘Suriani’ in the Latin sources.
                        They made up a considerable part of the Christian population all over the
                        Levant. Albeit speaking Arabic in daily use, they themselves cherished their
                        Syrian or Aramean origin. Their liturgy was byzantinized during the Crusader
                        period.</p>
                    <p>As the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> were considered heretical by the Latin Church, their
                        hierarchy as well as the hierarchy of the Maronites on the whole was left
                        intact. Almost all the areas of Maronite population fell under Latin rule in
                        the County of Tripoli. Their patriarch resided in monasteries in the
                        Maronite diocese of Jubail. Due to an extreme scarcity of sources, the
                        history of the Maronites in this period is much disputed. The Latin
                        chronicler William of Tyre regarded them as fine warriors and as allies of
                        the Latins.</p>
                    <p>The <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> archdioceses of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref>, Samosata,
                        Manbij, Tarsus, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Antioch">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>
                        </ref>, and
                        Jerusalem, as well as important bishoprics such as Acre, Tripoli, Cyprus,
                        Marʿash, Raban, Kesoun, and Saruj became part of the Crusader states. In the
                        County of Edessa the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> became involved in the Latin administration
                        and also in military action. The capture of Edessa by the Zengid army in
                        1144 and the failed Latin attempt to regain the city caused much hardship
                        among the Christian population. Massacres and slavery ended a short-lived
                        period of pride and affluence. A spiritual crisis among the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> and
                        theological debates flared up as a consequence.</p>
                    <p>The <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> came into contact with the Latins only on its periphery. Under
                        the authority of the metropolitan of the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Damascus">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/66">Damascus</placeName>
                        </ref> and
                        probably a second metropolitan of Jerusalem and Tripoli, members of this
                        church lived also in Edessa, on Mount Lebanon, in Cyprus, in Antioch, and in
                        the merchant towns on the sea coast. The communities were perhaps also
                        enlarged by refugees, who had moved to the West during the Mongol invasions
                        in Central Asia and Mesopotamia.</p>
                    <p>The intensity of theological relations between the Eastern Churches and the
                        Latins depended on dogmatic positions as well as on their geographical
                        dispersion and on political constellations. A general climate of theological
                        openness led Eastern Christians and Latins in the 12th and 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> to
                        study each other’s theological propositions and also to seek common ground,
                        with different outcomes. While the union between the Latin and the Greek
                        Church still was officially upheld in the Levant, Latin ecclesiastical
                        supremacy and conflicts alienated the two Churches. During the 12th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        almost no contacts between the Latins and the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> are recorded. At the
                        same time, the most isolated of the Syriac churches during that period, the
                        Maronites, were officially united with the Roman Church. The Maronite
                        patriarch Jeremiah II (1199–1230) was accepted as Primate of the Maronite
                        Church and invited to the <choice>
                            <sic>4th</sic>
                            <corr>Fourth</corr>
                        </choice> Lateran Council in 1215. Some opposition
                        against Latinization however flared up, most notably towards the end of the
                        Latin rule in the Levant.</p>
                    <p>The <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Church sought a pragmatic understanding without giving up its
                        independence, maintaining contact with the Latins and with the Byzantine
                        Emperor Manuel. At the council of Jerusalem in 1141 the dogmatic differences
                        between Latins, Armenians, and <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> were not felt as grave as
                        previously expected. Joint religious practice as well as theological
                        disputations took place. The <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> used the advantages of a government
                        that was often unfavorable to the Greek Orthodox. In turn, several instances
                        of direct church governance by the Latins can be detected in which the Latin
                        authorities overruled internal decisions by the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> patriarchs or
                        synods.</p>
                    <p>During the 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> the Pope intensified his diplomatic and missionary
                        efforts among the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> and the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Church. The generally
                        tolerant attitude of the Mongols towards Christians raised Latin hopes for
                        new allies against the Muslims. The residences of the mendicants in the
                        Crusader States served as bridgeheads for the missions, while the local
                        Latin Church seems to have been little involved. Individual prelates of the
                        <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Church and the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> maintained close relations with the
                        Latins. No Syr. source, however, corroborates Roman claims that some Syrian
                        metropolitans or patriarchs recognized Roman primacy at that time. Such
                        claims could be due to a misunderstanding of the Syrian attitudes. Such
                        unions were in any case ephemeral and not supported by the communities.</p>
                    <p>The frequent wars, their economical effects on local trade and agriculture,
                        roaming bandits, and encroachments on the Eastern Christians caused
                        hardship. Refugees fled to the coast especially after the final Muslim
                        conquest of Edessa in 1146. A slow deterioration of the relations between
                        the Christian and Muslim population is noticeable. Neither Muslims nor
                        Latins sufficiently secured the indigenous population. At the same time for
                        Syriac Christians this was a period of most important achievements in all
                        fields of art and culture, for which the term ‘<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Renaissance-Syriac">Syriac
                            Renaissance</ref>’ has been often used (see in particular Kawerau 1960
                        and Teule <abbr>et al.</abbr>, 2010).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>M. Amouroux-Mourad, <title rend="italic">Le Comté d’Edesse.
                                1089–1150</title> (1988).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.-D.  von  den  Brincken, <title rend="italic">Die “Nationes
                                Christianorum Orientalium” im Verständnis der lateinischen
                                Historiographie von der Mitte des 12. bis in die zweite Hälfte des
                                14. Jahrhunderts</title> (1973).</bibl>
                        <bibl>K.  Ciggaar and H.  Teule (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">East and West in
                            the Crusader states. <choice>
                                    <sic>Context-contacts-confrontations</sic>
                                    <corr>Context — contacts — confrontations</corr>
                                </choice>
                            </title>, vol.
                            2–3 (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 92, 125; 1999, 2003).</bibl>
                        <bibl>K.  Ciggaar and M.  Metcalf (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">East and West
                                in the Medieval Eastern Mediterranean</title>, vol. 1. <title rend="italic">Antioch from the Byzantine reconquest until the end of
                                the Crusader Principality</title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 147; 2006).</bibl>
                        <bibl>R. Ellenblum, <title rend="italic">Frankish Rural Settlement in the
                                Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem</title> (1998).</bibl>
                        <bibl>B.  Hamilton, <title rend="italic">The Latin Church in the Crusader
                                States: The Secular Church</title> (1980).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Kaufhold, ‘Zur syrischen Kirchengeschichte des 12. Jahrhunderts.
                            Neue Quellen über Theodoros bar Wahbûn’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OC</abbr>
                            </title>
                            74 (1990), 115–51.</bibl>
                        <bibl>P.  Kawerau, <title rend="italic">Die jakobitische Kirche im Zeitalter
                                der syrischen Renaissance: Idee und Wirklichkeit</title>
                            (1960).</bibl>
                        <bibl>C. H.  MacEvitt, <title rend="italic">The Crusades and the Christian
                                world of the East: Rough tolerance</title> (2008).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H. E.  Mayer, <title rend="italic">The Crusades</title> (2nd <abbr>ed.</abbr>
                            1988).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Palmer, ‘The History of the Syrian Orthodox in Jerusalem, Part
                            Two: Queen Melisende and the Jacobite Estates’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OC</abbr>
                            </title> 76 (1992), 74–94.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Pahlitzsch, <title rend="italic">Graeci und Suriani im Palästina
                                der Kreuzfahrerzeit</title> (Berliner Historische Studien 33;
                            2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl>K. M.  Setton <abbr>et al.</abbr> (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">A History of the
                                Crusades</title> (6 vols.; 2nd <abbr>ed.</abbr> 1969–1989).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Teule, K.  Ciggaar, and A.  Davids (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">East and West in the Crusader states.
                            <choice>
                                    <sic>Context-contacts-confrontations</sic>
                                    <corr>Context — contacts — confrontations</corr>
                                </choice>
                            </title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 75; 1996).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Teule <abbr>et al.</abbr> (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">The Syriac
                                Renaissance</title> (<abbr>ECS</abbr> 9; 2010).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Weltecke, <title rend="italic">Die «Beschreibung der
                            Zeiten»</title>.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Dorothea</forename> 
                  <surname>Weltecke</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
