<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Diaspora</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Sebastian P.</forename> 
                  <surname>Brock</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Diaspora</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diaspora</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/172</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">163</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="119-122"/>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Prior to the 19th <abbr>cent.</abbr> There had been very little
                        emigration from the Middle East, whereas today there are more Christians
                        from the Syriac (and other Middle Eastern) Churches living in the Diaspora
                        than remain in the homelands.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>Prior to the late 19th <abbr>cent.</abbr> there had been very little emigration from the
                        Middle East, whereas today there are more Christians from the Syriac (and
                        other Middle Eastern) Churches living in the Diaspora than remain in the
                        homelands. The two main causes of this massive demographic change are 1. the
                        massacres in Syria and Lebanon of 1860, and especially those in Eastern
                        Turkey of 1895/6 and of 1915 (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sayfo">Sayfo</ref>) and following
                        years; and 2. the continuing unsettled political situation, involving wars
                        and civil strife, in many countries of the Middle East, where certain events
                        in particular have given rise to renewed waves of emigration, notably in
                        1933 after the end of the British Mandate in Iraq (1932), involving the
                        Assyrians; the creation of the state of Israel in 1948 and the three
                        subsequent wars (1956, 1967, 1973), involving the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> in Palestine;
                        the Lebanese civil war (1975–1990), involving the Maronites and other Syr.
                        communities in Lebanon; the Turkish-Kurdish conflict in Eastern Turkey,
                        involving mainly the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>; the Iraqi-Kurdish conflict, followed by the
                        Iraq-Iran war (1980–88), the Gulf war (1990–1), and the invasion of Iraq
                        (2003), involving the Chaldeans, Assyrians, Syr. Catholic, and <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> In
                        all these upheavals displacement and emigration has also been to other
                        countries within the Middle East (or even within the same country), as well
                        as to countries outside it (with or without refugee status). A further cause
                        of emigration has been the lack of educational or employment opportunities
                        in the countries of origin; this had already led to the earliest immigration
                        to the United States (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Chicago">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/471">Chicago</placeName>
                        </ref>, New
                        Britain, CT) from north-west Iran (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Urmia">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/206">Urmia</placeName>
                        </ref> region) in the
                        late 19th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                    </p>
                    <p>The massacres of 1895/6 and 1915–18 led to large scale emigration, both
                        within the Middle East (mainly to Syria, Lebanon, Palestine in the case of
                        the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>; to Iraq, Iran, and the Caucasus [and thence, to Russia] in
                        the case of the Chaldeans and Assyrians) and to the West, above all at this
                        stage to the Americas, both North and South. The flight of Assyrians from
                        Iraq in 1933 resulted in new settlements in eastern Syria, while others
                        emigrated to Britain and especially the United States. The Americas were
                        also the goal of most of those emigrating after the creation of Israel, and
                        it has only been in the last 50 years that large numbers from all the Syr.
                        Churches have emigrated to countries of western Europe, with a preponderance
                        of <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> settling in Germany (where the first priest was ordained in
                        1977) and Sweden, and of Chaldeans and Maronites in France. An important
                        development in the case of the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> was the founding of three
                        monasteries by the late <abbr>bp.</abbr> 
                  <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Cicek-Julius-Yeshu">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/422">Julius Çiçek</persName>
                        </ref> (Mor Ephrem,
                        Netherlands, 1984; Mor Augen, Switzerland, 1999; Mor Yaʿqub da-Srug,
                        Germany, 2000). Smaller communities from the different Syr. Churches are
                        also found in Russia, Denmark, the Netherlands, Belgium, Switzerland,
                        Austria, Italy, Britain, and Greece. More recently emigration on a large
                        scale has also been to Australia. A pattern followed in many cases has been
                        for emigrés from a particular village to settle together in their new home.
                        Since 2003 it has been Syria, Jordan, and Turkey that have been the
                        immediate goals of those fleeing from the dangerous situation in Iraq.</p>
                    <p>The increasing sizes of the Diaspora communities has led to the creation of
                        new dioceses outside the Middle East, following on from the earlier
                        establishment of church communities in the different countries. The main
                        topic of the 16th Congress of Catholic Patriarchs of the Middle East in 2006
                        was emigration. The following listing of Diaspora dioceses gives some idea
                        of the geographical spread for each of the Syr. Churches; figures for
                        numbers, where given, are inevitably only approximate (these can vary
                        considerably from one source to another).</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Ancient Church of the East</hi>: Germany (Mainz), Western
                        USA (Modesto, California), and Australia and New Zealand.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Assyrian Church of the East</hi>: Europe (Norsborg,
                        Sweden); Canada (Weston, Ontario); Eastern USA (Chicago; residence of the
                        <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr>), Western USA (Glendale, Arizona); Western California (San Jose);
                        Australia and New Zealand (Sydney). With communities in several other
                        countries, including Denmark, Germany, Great Britian, Greece, and Russia.
                        Whereas some 150,000 now live in the Diaspora (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 90,000 in USA, and 10,000
                        in Australia/New Zealand), only <abbr>ca.</abbr> 100,000 remain in the Middle East.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chaldean Catholic Church</hi>: USA (Southfield, Michigan;
                        San Diego [since 2002]), with <abbr>ca.</abbr> 170,000 faithful; Australia and New
                        Zealand (since 2006), with <abbr>ca.</abbr> 15,000. There are sizeable communities in
                        Canada (Montreal, Toronto, Windsor), and in Europe (especially France, with
                        communities in Paris, Lyon, and Marseille; but also Sweden, Germany,
                        Belgium, and smaller ones in Greece, Netherlands, Denmark, and Great
                        Britain).</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Maronite Church</hi>: USA (Brooklyn, Los Angeles); Canada
                        (Montreal); Brazil (Sao Paolo); Argentina (Buenos Aires [since 1990]);
                        Mexico (since 1995); Australia (Strathfield, NSW); and sizeable communities
                        in Europe, especially France. Estimates ranging between one million and two
                        and a half million are given for Maronites in the Diaspora (a high
                        proportion are in South America), while little over half a million remain in
                        the Middle East.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Syrian Catholic Church</hi>: USA (Newark NJ [since 1995])
                        and Venezuela (since 2001); with communities <choice>
                            <sic>in in </sic>
                            <corr>in </corr>
                        </choice>USA in Detroit, Los
                        Angeles, San Diego, and Jacksonville (Florida). In Canada there are
                        communities in Toronto and Montreal; in Europe, notably in Amsterdam,
                        London, and Paris; in Australia, in Sydney. An estimated 50,000 (out of a
                        total of <abbr>ca.</abbr> 100,000) live in the Diaspora.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Syrian Orthodox Church</hi>: Europe: Sweden and
                        Scandinavia (Södertälje and Klockarvägen); Germany (Warburg); Netherlands
                        (Glane); Belgium (Brussels); Great Britain (London); with further
                        communities in France, Switzerland, Italy, and Austria; USA (Teaneck, New
                        Jersey; Burbank, California); Canada (Saint Laurent, Québec); Australia and
                        New Zealand (Lidcombe, NSW); Argentina (La Plata). Some 150,000 live in the
                        Diaspora, while roughly the same number remain in the Middle East (by far
                        the largest numbers are in India).</p>
                    <p>The different Indian Churches of Syr. tradition also have considerable
                        diasporas all over the world, and several now have a North American diocese
                        (Syro-Malabar: Chicago, since 2001; Syro-Malankara: for America and Europe,
                        since 2005; Syrian Orthodox: Cartaret, New Jersey; Orthodox Syrian: Alma,
                        Michigan, and Belrose, New York). There are communities in several European
                        countries from all the Syr. Churches in India (especially Great Britain,
                        Ireland, Germany, Switzerland, and Austria). Many from Kerala go as
                        temporary workers to the Gulf states, in some of which churches have been
                        built.</p>
                    <p>The above locations only cover countries where church communities have been
                        established; for individuals from the Syr. Churches of the Middle East, the
                        scatter is much wider, and includes countries of Africa and East Asia.</p>
                    <p>The move to secular societies where ethnic and cultural, rather than
                        religious, identity is paramount has caused much dispute in the search for
                        appropriate names to use (Aramaean, Assyrian, Chaldean, Assyro-Chaldean,
                        Syriac, <hi rend="italic">Suryoyo</hi>, etc.), and the issue has often
                        proved sadly divisive, especially among the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> On the other hand,
                        many new opportunities have been opened up, for the creation of cultural and
                        other associations, and for new educational possibilities. In the 1930s when
                        for a time it was Soviet policy to encourage minority languages, the written
                        use of Modern Syriac (in Latin script) was encouraged; a more recent
                        adaptation of the spoken language to western script has taken place with
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Turoyo">Turoyo</ref> in Sweden. Especially important has been the freedom to
                        publish in western countries. This has given rise to a great many cultural
                        magazines, often multilingual (and including both Classical and Modern
                        Syriac), as well as the creation of television channels (such as Suryoyo
                        SAT, Suroyo TV, Assyrian TV); it has also made it possible to publish
                        information about <choice>
                            <sic/>
                            <corr>the </corr>
                        </choice>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sayfo</hi>. Another notable development
                        has been in the creation of music groups, both church-based and secular, the
                        latter using lyrics in both Classical and Modern Syriac; though this
                        development had its origins in the Middle East (<choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>Qamishli in the 1960s,
                        and rather earlier in Iran), it has been greatly developed in the
                        Diaspora.</p>
                    <p>See <choice>
                            <sic>Fig. 40–42</sic>
                            <corr>
                                <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/40">Fig. 40</ref>,
                                    <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/41">41</ref>, and
                                    <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/42">42</ref>
                            </corr>
                        </choice>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Acar, <title rend="italic">Menschen zwischen Kulturen —
                            aramäische Jugendliche in Deutschland</title> (1997).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Alichoran, ‘Assyro-Chaldeans in the 20th century: From genocide to
                            diaspora’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JAAS</abbr>
                            </title> 8:2 (1994), 45–79.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Y. Benjamin, ‘Assyrians in Middle America’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JAAS</abbr>
                            </title> 10:2 (1996), 18–45.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.-M. Billioud, <title rend="italic">Les chrétiens d’Orient en
                                France</title> (1998).</bibl>
                        <bibl>U. Björkland, <title rend="italic">North to another country. The
                                formation of a Suryoyo community in Sweden</title> (1981).</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. P. Brock, ‘The Syrian Orthodox Church in modern history’, in <title rend="italic">Christianity in the Middle East. Studies in Modern
                                History, Theology and Politics</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. O’Mahony (2008),
                            17–38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, vol. 3,
                            65–153.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Y.  Çiçek, ‘I cristiani siro-occidentali nella diaspora:
                            L’emigrazione dei siro-aramaici’, in <title rend="italic">Le Chiese Sire
                                tra IV e VI secolo</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> E.  Vergani and S.  Chialà (2005),
                            41–8. (<abbr>ET</abbr> in <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Sobornost/ECR</abbr>
                            </title> 28:2 [2006],
                            19–27)</bibl>
                        <bibl>C.  Hélou, ‘La diaspora maronite en Europe’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JEastCS</abbr>
                            </title> 54 (2002), 51–63.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Ishaya, ‘Assyrian Americans: A study in ethnic reconstruction and
                            dissolution in Diaspora’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JAAS</abbr>
                            </title> 17:2 (2003),
                            19–38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>eadem, ‘Settling into Diaspora: A history of Urmia Assyrians in the
                            United States’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JAAS</abbr>
                            </title> 20 (2006),
                            3–27.</bibl>
                        <bibl>X.  Jacob and A. G.  Calonghi, <title rend="italic">Les Chrétiens du
                                Proche Orient. Après deux millénaires</title> (2002). (for
                            demography)</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Jacoub, ‘La diaspora assyro-chaldéenne’, <title rend="italic">Istina</title> 40 (1995), 191–202.</bibl>
                        <bibl>K.  Merten, <title rend="italic">Die syrisch-orthodoxen Christen in
                                der Türkei und in Deutschland</title> (1997).</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Murre-van den Berg, ‘Migration of Middle Eastern Christians to
                            Western countries and Protestant missionary activities in the Middle
                            East’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JEastCS</abbr>
                            </title> 54 (2002), 39–49.</bibl>
                        <bibl>E. Naveau, ‘Les orthodoxes syriaques d’Indonésie’, <title rend="italic">Les Cahiers de l’Orient</title> 93 (2009),
                            111–24.</bibl>
                        <bibl>G.  Rabo, ‘Die <choice>
                                <sic>Grundung</sic>
                                <corr>Gründung</corr>
                            </choice> der <choice>
                                <sic>Syrisch-Orthodoxen</sic>
                                <corr>syrisch-orthodoxen</corr>
                            </choice> Kirchen in der
                            Diaspora’, in <title rend="italic">Ego sum qui sum. Festschrift für J.
                                Martikainen</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> T. Martikainen (2006), 89–105.</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. al-Rasheed, <title rend="italic">Iraqi Assyrian Christians in
                                London: The Construction of ethnicity</title> (1998).</bibl>
                        <bibl>E. Safa, <title rend="italic">L’émigration libanaise</title>
                            (1960).</bibl>
                        <bibl>D. Sarkisov, ‘Assyrian settlements in Caucasia’, <title rend="italic">Nineveh</title> 22:1–2 (1999), 4–12.</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. C.  Sengstock, <title rend="italic">Chaldeans in Chicago</title>
                            (2005).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Sh.  Talay, ‘Bericht über die Lage der Apostolischen Kirche des Ostens
                            in Syrien’, in <title rend="italic">Zu Geschichte, Theologie, Liturgie
                                und Gegenwartslage der syrischen Kirchen</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> M.  Tamcke and
                            A.  Heinz (2000), 447–67.</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. Tamcke, ‘Nach Russland, Deutschland ... Streitfluchter aus
                            deutschen Akten zur ersten Migrationswelle der Ostsyrer
                            (Assyrer/<choice>
                                <sic>‘Nestorianer’</sic>
                                <corr>“Nestorianer”</corr>
                            </choice>)’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JEastCS</abbr>
                            </title> 54
                            (2002), 25–38.</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Teule, ‘Middle Eastern Christians and migrations, some
                            reflections’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JEastCS</abbr>
                            </title> 54 (2002),
                            1–23.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Thiry, <title rend="italic">Mechelen aan de Tigris</title>
                            (2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>A.  Thiry</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Mechelen on the Tigris. The renaissance of an Assyrian
                            village’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Harp</abbr>
                            </title> 20:2 (2006), 23–57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.-P. Valognes, <title rend="italic">Vie et mort des chrétiens
                                d’Orient</title> (1994).</bibl>
                        <bibl>D.  Wolk, ‘Church colony vs. congregation: A struggle for control of
                            the Church of the East in Chicago during the 1940s’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JAAS</abbr>
                            </title> 22:1 (2008), 15–58.</bibl>
                        <bibl>G. Yonan, <title rend="italic">Journalismus bei den Assyrern</title>
                            (1985).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Zeitoune, <title rend="italic">Music Pearls of Beth Nahrin. An
                                Assyrian/Syriac Discography</title> (2007).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Sebastian P.</forename> 
                  <surname>Brock</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
