<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Ethiopic Christianity, Syriac contacts with</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Aaron M.</forename> 
                  <surname>Butts</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Ethiopic Christianity, Syriac contacts with</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ethiopic-Christianity-Syriac-contacts-with</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/209</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">200</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="148-153"/>
                    <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Syriac contacts with Ethiopic
                        Christianity</idno>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Throughout its history, Ethiopic Christianity has had
                        various contacts with Syriac Christianity.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>Christianity reached the Kingdom of Aksum, on the northern edge of the great
                        Ethiopian plateau, by the reign of ʿĒzānā in the middle of the 4th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        According to Rufinus (4th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), the introduction of Christianity was
                        facilitated by a certain Frumentius from Tyre (later known in the Ethiopic
                        tradition as Salāmā Kaśātē Berhān), who was ordained <abbr>bp.</abbr> of ‘India’ (<choice>
                            <sic>i.e.</sic>
                            <corr>i.e.,</corr>
                        </choice>
                        Ethiopia) by <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Athanasius-of-Alexandria">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/354">Athanasius of Alexandria</persName>
                        </ref>. In the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, the traveler Cosmas
                        Indicopleustes reported that there were a large number of churches in
                        Ethiopia as well as numerous bishops, martyrs, and monks. In time, Ethiopic
                        Christianity became associated with the Oriental Orthodox Churches, which
                        include the Coptic, Armenian, <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syriac-Orthodox-Church">Syriac
                            Orthodox</ref>, and <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Malankara-Syriac-Orthodox-Church">Malankara Syriac Orthodox</ref> Churches, all of which accept the
                        Councils of Nicea, Constantinople, and Ephesus, but reject the Council of
                        Chalcedon (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ecumenical-dialogue">Ecumenical
                            dialogue</ref>). Throughout its history, Ethiopic Christianity has had
                        various contacts with Syriac Christianity. In general, the influence of
                        Ethiopic Christianity on Syriac Christianity seems to have been rather
                        limited, though it was certainly not non-existent. The influence of Syriac
                        Christianity on Ethiopic Christianity, on the other hand, was more
                        substantial. This influence can be divided into two basic time periods: the
                        Aksumite Period (4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> – <abbr>ca.</abbr> 900) and the Solomonic Period
                        (1270–1770).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Aksumite Period</label>
                    <p>In the scholarly literature, a great deal of attention has been focused on
                        possible Syriac influences on Ethiopic Christianity in the Aksumite period.
                        Although Christianity reached Ethiopia in the 4th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, the spread of
                        Christianity throughout Ethiopia is traditionally attributed to the efforts
                        of a group of foreign missionaries active in the late 5th to early 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        These missionaries include the Ṣādeqān, Maṭāʿ, and especially the so-called
                        Nine Saints (see A. Brita, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 3, 1188–91).
                        A number of scholars, including I. Guidi (1888, 33–4 with n. 1; 1932, 13–5)
                        and especially C. Conti Rossini (1928, esp. 155–65), have argued that these
                        foreign missionaries originated from Syriac-speaking areas. Based on this
                        connection, a theory was developed that attributed a great deal of Syriac
                        influence to the development of Christianity in Ethiopia, including the
                        introduction of monasticism as well as the translation of the Bible into
                        Geʿez, the classical language of Ethiopic Christianity. The association of
                        these missionaries with Syriac-speaking areas was based on three principal
                        arguments, all of which have been seriously challenged in more recent
                        scholarship.</p>
                    <p>First, it was argued that the personal names of the missionaries and the
                        geographical names from which they are said to originate are of Syriac
                        origin (Guidi 1888, 33–4 n. 1; Conti Rossini 1928, 161). More recently,
                        however, Marrassini (1990, 35–8; 1999, 326–8) has shown that few, if any, of
                        these names are actually of Syriac origin.</p>
                    <p>Second, it was proposed that the transcription of Greek names in Geʿez,
                        especially in translations of the Bible, was based on the pattern of Aramaic
                        (Guidi 1888, 33–34 n. 1; Conti Rossini 1928, 156). Marrassini (1990, 39–41;
                        1999, 329–30) has, however, pointed out that this pattern is not restricted
                        to Aramaic, but rather it is the typical way in which Greek is transcribed
                        in Semitic languages.</p>
                    <p>The third argument adduced in favor of Syriac influence on Ethiopic
                        Christianity in the Aksumite period involves Syriac loanwords in Geʿez. More
                        than a century ago, Th. Nöldeke drew attention to a number of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aramaic">Aramaic</ref>
                        loanwords in Geʿez. Guidi (1932, 14) and especially Conti Rossini (1928,
                        155) argued that some of these Aramaic loanwords in Geʿez are more
                        specifically of Syriac origin, <choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>Geʿez <hi rend="italic">hāymānot</hi>
                        ‘faith’ (often translating Greek <hi rend="italic">pístis</hi>) from Syriac
                            <hi rend="italic">haymānutā</hi>. In an influential study, however,
                        Polotsky showed that several of these Aramaic loanwords were not borrowed
                        from Syriac, but rather from Jewish Aramaic, <choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>Geʿez <hi rend="italic">meṣwāt</hi> ‘alms, charity’ (no such word exists in Syriac) and Geʿez <hi rend="italic">ṭāʿot</hi> ‘idol’ (Syriac has <hi rend="italic">ṭāʿyutā</hi>, which not only preserves the third root consonant <hi rend="italic">y</hi>, but means ‘error, mistake’). Further research by
                        Ullendorff (1967, 120–5), Witakowski (1989–90, 191–2; forthcoming), and
                        Marrassini (1990, 38–9; 1999, 328–9) has raised additional questions about
                        some of the purported Syriac loanwords in Geʿez while at the same time
                        suggested several new possible examples. In the current state of research,
                        it can only be conclusively stated that Geʿez contains a number of Aramaic
                        loanwords, some of which are certainly not Syriac, but others of which may
                        potentially be Syriac. Before any meaningful historical conclusions can be
                        drawn, an updated analysis of all the Aramaic loanwords in Geʿez is needed,
                        taking into account recent developments in Aramaic dialectology as well as
                        the increasingly robust methodology of contact linguistics.</p>
                    <p>In the end, the evidence for significant Syriac influence on Ethiopic
                        Christianity in the Aksumite period is rather slim. Nevertheless, it does
                        seem all but certain that there were contacts between Ethiopic Christianity
                        and Syriac Christianity at this time, especially given that the Aksumite
                        kingdom was involved in various power struggles with South Arabian kingdoms
                        in the Arabian Peninsula, a place where Syriac-speaking Christians are known
                        to have resided. In one instance of particular importance to contacts
                        between Syriac and Ethiopic Christianity, the Aksumite <hi rend="italic">neguś</hi> Kālēb (<abbr>fl.</abbr> first half of the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>) intervened against
                        the king of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Himyar">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/474">Ḥimyar</placeName>
                        </ref> on behalf of miaphysite Christians who where being
                        persecuted in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nagran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/464">Nagran</placeName>
                        </ref> (see recently Nebes).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Solomonic Period</label>
                    <p>Setting aside the problematic evidence of the Aksumite period, Syriac
                        influence on Ethiopic Christianity can be firmly established for Geʿez
                        literature from the Solomonic period. In this case, however, Syriac
                        influence was almost always mediated by Arabic Christianity, which inherited
                        a great deal from the Syriac heritage.</p>
                    <p>Alongside original compositions, Geʿez literature contains a significant body
                        of translations which were made from Greek in the Aksumite period and from
                        Arabic in the Solomonic period; there is little evidence for literary
                        activity in the intervening time of the Zāg<hi rend="superscript">w</hi>ē
                        dynasty (900–1270). In many cases, the Arabic literature was itself
                        translated from Greek, Coptic, and Syriac. While there may be a few rare
                        cases in which Syriac literature in Geʿez was translated directly from
                        Syriac, in most cases Arabic was the bridge by which Syriac literature
                        reached Ethiopic Christianity.</p>
                    <p>The Bible is the earliest piece of literature associated with Ethiopic
                        Christianity. At least part of the Bible was already translated into Geʿez
                        by the end of the 4th to the early 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> as can be deduced from biblical
                        quotations in the Aksumite inscriptions (Knibb, 46–54). Though there is now
                        general consensus that the Geʿez <abbr>OT</abbr> and <abbr>NT</abbr> were both translated from Greek,
                        a number of different <hi rend="italic">Vorlagen</hi>, including Syriac,
                        have been proposed throughout the history of scholarship. A. Vööbus, for
                        instance, argued that the Geʿez Gospels were translated from Syriac and then
                        revised against the Greek text. It is now clear, however, that Syriac
                        influence on the Geʿez Bible occurred at a later stage (probably in the 14th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr>) when the Geʿez biblical text was revised against a Syriac biblical
                        text or, more likely, an Arabic version of a Syriac biblical text (see
                        Knibb, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 1, 565 and more extensively Knibb
                        1999). Evidence of interest in the comparison of Syriac and Ethiopic
                        biblical texts (along with Coptic, Arabic, and Armenian) is found in <abbr>ms.</abbr>
                        Vat. Barberini Or. 2, a 15th-cent. polyglot Psalter in five languages, which
                        was owned by a <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> priest named Ṣalib (see S. P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac tradition</hi> [2nd <abbr>ed.</abbr> 2006],
                        145).</p>
                    <p>Moving beyond the Bible, a number of Syriac-speaking authors appear in Geʿez
                        literature. Two demonstrations by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aphrahat">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/10">Aphrahaṭ</persName>
                        </ref> (<abbr>fl.</abbr>
                        336–45) are found in the Ethiopic tradition (see W. Witakowski, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 1, 287). In 1906, F. M. Esteves Pereira
                        published a Geʿez version of Dem. 5. In this text, the author is
                        (incorrectly) identified as <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Nisibis">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/811">Yaʿqub of
                            Nisibis</persName>
                        </ref>, an attribution which is also found in the earliest Syriac
                        <abbr>ms.</abbr> of Aphrahaṭ (London, Brit. Libr. Add. 17,182; dated 474), as well as in
                        the Armenian translation. In 1964, E. Cerulli published a text on the
                        resurrection of the dead, which was subsequently identified as a portion of
                        Aphrahaṭ’s Dem. 8 by T. Baarda.</p>
                    <p>A number of Geʿez texts are attributed to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ephrem">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 373),
                        including both homilies and prayers (a list is provided by Weninger, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 1, 331–2); it is, however, unclear whether
                        any of these are among Ephrem’s genuine writings. Several homilies
                        attributed to Ephrem are extracted in the <hi rend="italic">Hāymānota
                            ābaw</hi> ‘Faith of the Fathers’, which is a large compendium of
                        patristic writings, synodical statements, and canons (unedited; see A.  Wion
                        and E.  Fritsch, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 2, 1073–5 and Graf). In
                        addition, Ephrem is said to have composed the <hi rend="italic">Weddāsē
                            Māryām</hi> ‘Praise of Mary’ (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>FT</abbr> Velat), a collection of hymns
                        to Mary for each day of the week, which is found in Ethiopic Psalter <abbr>mss.</abbr> as
                        well as in the <hi rend="italic">Meʿerāf</hi>, a liturgical text which forms
                        part of the Divine Office. Due to his association with the <hi rend="italic">Weddāsē Māryām</hi>, Ephrem is usually depicted in Ethiopic iconography
                        standing at the feet of an enthroned Mary (see Hammerschmidt and Jäger,
                        101–8). Ephrem also sometimes bears the sobriquet <hi rend="italic">labḥāwi</hi> ‘the potter’ in the Ethiopic tradition, likely due to a
                        conflation with <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemun-Quqoyo">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/37">Shemʿun
                            Quqoyo</persName>
                        </ref>.</p>
                    <p>The legend of Abgar V Ukkama (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abgarids-of-Edessa">Abgarids</ref>), which is
                        found in Syriac in the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Addai-Teaching-of">Teaching of
                            Addai</ref>, exists in at least four Geʿez versions, two of which are
                        associated with the <hi rend="italic">Taʾāmmera Iyasus</hi> ‘The miracles of
                        Jesus’ (see Weninger, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 1, 40–41 and
                        especially Haile). Most of the <hi rend="italic">Taʾāmmera Iyasus
                        </hi>consists of a translation of the Arabic Apocryphal Gospel of John (<abbr>ed.</abbr>
                        with <abbr>LT</abbr> I. Galbiati, <hi rend="italic">Iohannis evangelium apocryphum
                            arabice</hi> [1957]), which is itself based on a variety of sources,
                        including the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Cave-of-Treasures">Cave of
                            Treasures</ref> and the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Methodius-Apocalypse-of-Pseudo-">Apocalypse of
                            Pseudo-Methodius</ref> (see Witakowski 1995).</p>
                    <p>No less than twenty texts are attributed to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Serugh">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Yaʿqub of
                            Serugh</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 521) in the Ethiopic tradition (inventories are
                        provided in W. Witakowski, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 2, 263 and
                        Uhlig 1999, 13–16). A majority of these belong to the genre of <hi rend="italic">dersān</hi> ‘homily’, the Geʿez equivalent of Syriac <hi rend="italic">memrā</hi>. While only one of these homilies has thus far
                        been edited (Uhlig 1999), it seems that many of them were translated from
                        Arabic, and at least some may go back to Syriac originals. Others, however,
                        were only ascribed to Yaʿqub in the Geʿez ms. tradition, <choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>the <hi rend="italic">Dersāna sanbat</hi> ‘Homily on the Sabbath’ (see Wurmbrand
                        1963). Interestingly, Yaʿqub’s ‘Homily on the death of
                        Aaron’ formed the basis for the <hi rend="italic">Mota Āron</hi> ‘Death of
                        Aaron’, a Geʿez text that is found not only in the literary tradition of the
                        Ethiopian Orthodox Church, but also in that of the Bēta Esrāʾēl (or Falāšā)
                        (see Wurmbrand 1961). In addition to homilies, an anaphora, <choice>
                            <sic>incipit</sic>
                            <corr>
                                <hi rend="italic">incipit</hi>
                            </corr>
                        </choice> ‘Stand
                        up in the fear of the Lord’, is also attributed to Yaʿqub (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>GT</abbr>
                        Euringer), but again it is probably pseudonymous (see Hammerschmidt,
                        47–8).</p>
                    <p>A Profession of Faith attributed to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-Burdoyo">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/69">Yaʿqub
                            Burdʿoyo</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 578) is preserved in Geʿez in the <hi rend="italic">Hāymānota ābaw</hi> (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>GT</abbr> Cornill; see J. Tubach, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 3, 261–2). This text is not extant in
                        Syriac, but is found in Arabic (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>DT</abbr> H. G. Kleyn, <hi rend="italic">Jacobus Baradaeüs. De stichter der syrische monophysietische
                        kerk</hi> [1882], 121–63), from which the Geʿez was translated.</p>
                    <p>Geʿez preserves the ‘Conflict of Severus’ by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Athanasios-I-Gamolo">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/88">Athanasios I
                            Gamolo</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 631) (<abbr>ed.</abbr> Goodspeed and Crum), which deals with the
                        life of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Severus-of-Antioch">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of
                            Antioch</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 538). Though not extant in Syriac, this text is found
                        in Arabic as well as in Coptic fragments. Several texts attributed to
                        Severus also exist in Geʿez, some of which may ultimately derive from Syriac
                        originals (see Witakowski 2004).</p>
                    <p>Several Syriac authors feature prominently in the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa
                            manakosāt </hi>‘Book of monks’, which is one of the central collections
                        of Ethiopic monasticism (see A. Bausi, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol.
                        2, 997–9). This collection consists of three distinct texts, each of which
                        is directly associated with at least one Syriac-speaking author. Included in
                        the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa manakosāt </hi>is the <hi rend="italic">Āragāwi manfasāwi</hi> ‘Spiritual Elder’, which is the name by which the
                        <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> mystical writer <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yohannan-of-Dalyatha">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/826">Yoḥannan of
                            Dalyatha</persName>
                        </ref> (8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), or Yoḥannan Saba (‘Elder’), is known in
                        Geʿez. The <hi rend="italic">Āragāwi manfasāwi</hi> was translated from an
                        Arabic version of Yoḥannan’s original Syriac composition (see E.  Lucchesi,
                        in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol.  1, 309–10). Another text found in the
                            <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa manakosāt</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Filkesyos</hi> (see Witakowski 2006; idem, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 2, 541–2). Though attributed to the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> theologian
                            <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Philoxenos-of-Mabbug">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/44">Philoxenos
                            of Mabbug</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 523), the <hi rend="italic">Filkesyos</hi> is
                        actually a Geʿez version (via Arabic) of the commentary of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dadisho-Qatraya">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/434">Dadishoʿ
                            Qaṭraya</persName>
                        </ref> (late 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>) on the ‘Paradise of the Fathers’ by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Enanisho">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/474">ʿEnanishoʿ</persName>
                        </ref> (7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>). ʿEnanishoʿ’s work is in turn a large
                        compilation of monastic texts, which includes <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Palladius">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/668">Palladius</persName>
                        </ref>’s
                        ‘Lausiac history’, the ‘History of the monks in Egypt’, and various
                        apophthegmata. The final book that makes up the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa
                            manakosāt</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa Mār Yesḥaq</hi> ‘The book
                        of Mar Isaac’ (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>GT</abbr> Berhanu; see S. Weninger, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 2, 193–4). As the title suggests, this text is
                        attributed to the famous <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> monastic author <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ishaq-of-Nineveh">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/550">Isḥaq of
                            Nineveh</persName>
                        </ref> (late 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>). More specifically, the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa Mār Yesḥaq</hi> is a Geʿez translation of the Arabic collection
                        attributed to Isḥaq. The Arabic version is in turn a translation from a
                        Greek version of writings attributed to Isḥaq, which consists of most of the
                        ‘First Part’ of the original Syriac writings of Isḥaq as well as four
                        homilies by Yoḥannan of Dalyatha and an abbreviated version of the ‘Letter
                        to Patricius’ by Philoxenos of Mabbug. Thus, although the <hi rend="italic">Filkesyos </hi>is incorrectly ascribed to Philoxenos, the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa manakosāt</hi> does still contain a text by this
                        <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> theologian. Outside of the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa
                            manakosāt</hi>, Geʿez monastic literature preserves a number of sayings
                        attributed to Syriac-speaking authors, including Ephrem, Yoḥannan of
                        Dalyatha, and Isḥaq of Nineveh, in various collections of apophthegmata (<abbr>ed.</abbr>
                        with <abbr>LT</abbr> Arras 1963, 1967, 1984, 1986, 1988).</p>
                    <p>Geʿez biblical exegesis has also been influenced by Syriac-speaking authors,
                        especially those belonging to the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr>, such as <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ahob-Qatraya">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/324">Aḥob Qaṭraya</persName>
                        </ref>
                        (late 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>?), <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoros-bar-Koni">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/783">Theodoros bar
                            Koni</persName>
                        </ref> (<abbr>fl.</abbr> end of the 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Isho-bar-Nun">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/552">Ishoʿ bar Nun</persName>
                        </ref>
                        (d.  828), and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ishodad-of-Merv">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/555">Ishoʿdad of
                            Merv</persName>
                        </ref> (<abbr>fl.</abbr>
                        <abbr> ca.</abbr> 850). This contact was mediated by the Christian
                        Arabic tradition, in particular the exegetical works of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ibn-al-Tayyib">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/543">Ibn al-Ṭayyib</persName>
                        </ref>
                        (d. 1043), especially his <hi rend="italic">Firdaws al-naṣrāniyya </hi>‘The
                        Paradise of Christianity’. In its Geʿez version, E.-Syr. biblical exegesis
                        was transmitted to the Andemta commentary tradition (Cowley 1983, 1988). The
                        Andemta commentaries contain a translation of the Geʿez biblical text into
                        Amharic, the official language of present-day Ethiopia, as well as a wealth
                        of traditional exegetical material (Psalms <abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>ET</abbr> Stoffregen Pedersen;
                        Hosea <abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>IT</abbr> Andeberhan). Several anonymous Syriac exegetical homilies
                        are also extant in Geʿez. The Syriac verse homily on Abraham and Sarah in
                        Egypt (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>ET</abbr> S. P. Brock and S. Hopkins, ‘A verse homily on Abraham
                        and Sarah in Egypt: Syriac original with early Arabic translation’, <title rend="italic">
                            <abbr>LM</abbr>
                        </title> 105 [1992], 87–146), for instance, found its way
                        via Arabic into Geʿez (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>FT</abbr> Caquot), where it is attributed to
                        Ephrem. Similarly, the Geʿez <hi rend="italic">Zenāhu la-Yosef</hi> ‘History
                        of Joseph’ (<abbr>ET</abbr> Isaac; an edition of the Geʿez is in preparation by the
                        current author) ultimately derives (via Arabic) from a Syriac version, which
                        is attributed to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Basil-of-Caesarea">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/376">Basil of
                            Caesarea</persName>
                        </ref> (see Heal; <abbr>ed.</abbr> M. Weinberg, <hi rend="italic">Die
                            Geschichte Josefs angeblich verfasst von Basilius dem Grossen aus
                            Caesarea</hi> [1893]; S. W. Link, <hi rend="italic">Die Geschichte
                            Josefs angeblich verfasst von Basilius dem Grossen aus Cäsarea</hi>
                        [1895]; K.  Heal, ‘A Missing leaf from the <hi rend="italic">Syriac History
                            of Joseph</hi>’, forthcoming).</p>
                    <p>Finally, a number of Syriac individuals appear in Geʿez hagiographic
                        literature. The <hi rend="italic">Senkessar</hi> ‘Synaxary’, for instance,
                        commemorates, among others, Abgar V Ukkama, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Barsawmo">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/370">Barṣawmo</persName>
                        </ref>, Ephrem
                        (cf. Pérès), <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Marutha-of-Maypherqat">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/25">Marutha of
                            Maypherqaṭ</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemun-the-Stylite">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/744">Shemʿun the
                            Stylite</persName>
                        </ref>, and Yaʿqub of Nisibis (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>FT</abbr> by various authors in
                        <abbr>PO</abbr>; for full references, see Colin; <abbr>ET</abbr> Budge 1928). More developed
                        hagiographic works, such as the Life of Barṣawmo (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with
                        <abbr>FT</abbr> Grébaut), are also extant in Geʿez.</p>
                    <p>Among the many interesting aspects of this large body of Geʿez literature
                        that is attributed to Syriac-speaking authors is the fact that several
                        E.-Syr. authors are represented in the Ethiopic tradition, especially in
                        texts related to biblical exegesis and monasticism. The appearance of these
                        E.-Syr. authors is intriguing given that Ethiopic Christianity has
                        throughout its history been dogmatically aligned with the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Church,
                        not with the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> In some cases, a work by a <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> author seems to
                        have been stripped of its distinctive E.-Syr. features before it passed into
                        Geʿez. This is, for instance, the case with Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s ‘Commentary on
                        the Gospels’, which is extant both in an original form as well as in an
                        adapted, miaphysite version (<abbr>ed.</abbr> Y. Manquriyūs, <hi rend="italic">Tafsīr
                            al-mašriqī</hi> [1908–10]; see Faultless), which served as the textual
                        basis for the Geʿez translation. In other cases, however, it is less clear
                        how Syriac-speaking authors belonging to the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> found their way into
                        Geʿez.</p>
                    <p>In addition to the Geʿez literature that is attributed to Syriac-speaking
                        authors, there are a number of originally Greek works that passed through
                        Syriac on their way to the Ethiopic tradition, again almost always with
                        Arabic standing in between. This is, for instance, likely the case with the
                            <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Didascalia-Apostolorum">Didascalia
                            Apostolorum</ref> (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>ET</abbr> Platt; <abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>ET</abbr> Horner), the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Testament-of-our-Lord-Jesus-Christ">Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ</ref> (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>FT</abbr> Beylot 1984), and
                        several texts related to the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Alexander-Cycle">Alexander
                            cycle</ref> (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>ET</abbr> Budge 1896; see G. Lusini, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 1, 195). Likewise, the Sayings of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ahiqar">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/323">Aḥiqar</persName>
                        </ref> seem to have
                        traveled through Syriac (and then Arabic) on their way to the Ethiopic
                        tradition, where they are transmitted in late <abbr>mss.</abbr> of the <hi rend="italic">Maṣḥafa falāsfa ṭabibān</hi> ‘Book of the wise philosophers’ (see U.
                        Pietruschka, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 2, 485–6). A similar
                        trajectory is likely for the related narrative about Aḥiqar that is
                        preserved in Geʿez (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>FT</abbr> Schneider).</p>
                    <p>It is clear then that Geʿez literature from the Solomonic period, which
                        includes a number of texts that are attributed to Syriac-speaking authors as
                        well as texts that passed through Syriac on their way to Geʿez, provides an
                        example of Syriac influence on Ethiopic Christianity. It must be stressed,
                        however, that this Syriac influence was in most, if not all, cases mediated
                        by Arabic Christianity.</p>
                    <p>The Syriac influence on Ethiopic Christianity in the Solomonic period can be
                        explained by various points of contact. During the reign of Yekunno Amlāk
                        (1270–85) at the beginning of the Solomonic period, it appears that a
                        ‘Syrian’ became head of the Ethiopian Church, a position normally restricted
                        to Coptic monks (see Tamrat, 69–72). Though this seems to have been short
                        lived, it clearly demonstrates a Syriac presence in Ethiopia at this time.
                        Outside of Ethiopia, contacts between Ethiopic and Syriac Christianity
                        occurred at various locations. Ethiopic monks are known to have lived in
                        several monastic communities in Egypt alongside Syriac monks (in general,
                        see O. Meinardus, in <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                        </hi>, vol. 2, 243–5). Both Syriac
                        and Ethiopic monks also resided at the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Catherine-Monastery-of-St">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/368">Monastery of St.
                            Catherine</placeName>
                        </ref> (Cerulli, 1943–7, vol. 1, 148 and 151). In addition,
                        contacts between Syriac and Ethiopic monks took place in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Jerusalem">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>
                        </ref>, where
                        the various Christian communities were represented (Cerulli 1943–7).
                        Finally, moving closer to the Syriac homeland, Ethiopic monks were present
                        from the 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> onwards in Lebanon and Syria, and some may have possibly
                        played a role in the renaming of <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Musa-al-Habashi-Dayr-Mar">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/228">Dayr Mār
                            Mūsā al-Ḥabashī</placeName>
                        </ref> (‘Monastery of St. Moses the Ethiopian’) (Cerulli
                        1943–7, vol. 1, 325–33; Cruikshank Dodd, 19–25; Kaufhold, 54–9).</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/48">Fig. 48</ref> and <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/49c">49c</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Primary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>W. Andeberhan, <title rend="italic">Commentari etiopici sul Libro
                                    del Profeta Osea</title> (<abbr>ÄF</abbr> 40; 1994). (Amharic with <abbr>IT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>V. Arras, <title rend="italic">Collectio monastica</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr>
                                238–9; 1963). (Geʿez with <abbr>LT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>V. Arras</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Patericon aethiopice</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr>
                                277–8; 1967). (Geʿez with <abbr>LT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>V. Arras</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Asceticon</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 458–9; 1984).
                                (Geʿez with <abbr>LT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>V. Arras</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Geronticon</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 476–7; 1986).
                                (Geʿez with <abbr>LT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>V. Arras</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Quadraginta historiae
                                    monachorum</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 505–506; 1988). (Geʿez with <abbr>LT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>D. Berhanu, <title rend="italic">Das Mashafa Mar Yeshaq von
                                    Ninive</title> (1997). (Geʿez with <abbr>GT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>R. Beylot, <title rend="italic">Testamentum Domini
                                    éthiopien</title> (1984). (Geʿez with <abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>E. A. W. Budge, <title rend="italic">The life and exploits of
                                    Alexander the Great being a series of Ethiopic texts …</title> (2
                                vols.; 1896). (Geʿez with <abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>E. A. W. Budge</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">The book of the saints of the Ethiopian
                                    church</title> (4 vols.; 1928). (<abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Caquot, ‘Une homélie éthiopienne attribuée à Saint Mar Éphrem
                                sur le séjour d’Abraham et Sara en Égypte’, in <title rend="italic">Mélanges Antoine Guillaumont. Contributions à l’étude des
                                    christianismes orientaux</title> (Cahiers d’orientalisme 20;
                                1988), 173–85. (Geʿez with <abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  Cerulli, ‘ “De resurrectione mortuorum” opuscolo della chiesa
                                Etiopica del sec. XIV’, in <title rend="italic">Mélanges Eugène
                                    Tisserant</title>, vol. 2. <title rend="italic">Orient
                                    chrétien</title> (<abbr>SeT</abbr> 232; 1964), 1–27. (Geʿez with <abbr>IT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>C. H. Cornill, ‘Das Glaubensbekenntniss des Jacob Baradaeus in
                                äthiopischer Uebersetzung’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>ZDMG</abbr>
                                </title> 30
                                (1876), 417–466. (Geʿez with <abbr>GT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>F. M.  Esteves Pereira, ‘Jacobi, episcopi Nisibeni, Homilia de
                                adventu regis Persarum adversus urbem Nisibis’, in <title rend="italic">Orientalische Studien Theodor Nöldeke zum
                                    siebzigsten Geburtstag (2. März 1906) gewidmet …</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> C.
                                Bezold, vol. 2 (1906), 877–92. (Geʿez)</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. Euringer, <title rend="italic">Die äthiopischen Anaphoren des
                                    hl. Evangelisten Johannes des Donnersohnes und des hl. Jacobus
                                    von Sarug</title> (<abbr>OCA</abbr> 90; 1934), 79–122. (Geʿez with <abbr>GT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  J.  Goodspeed and W. E. Crum, <title rend="italic">The
                                    Conflict of Severus, patriarch of Antioch, by Athanasius</title>
                                (<abbr>PO</abbr> 4.6; 1909). (Geʿez with <abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>S.  Grébaut, ‘Vie de Barsoma le Syrien’, <title rend="italic">ROC</title> 13 (1908), 337–345; 14 (1909), 135–42, 264–75,
                                401–16. (Geʿez with <abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. Haile, ‘The legend of Abgar in Ethiopic tradition’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OCP</abbr>
                                </title> 55 (1989), 375–410. (Geʿez with
                                <abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Horner, <title rend="italic">The statutes of the Apostles or
                                    Canones Ecclesiastici</title> (1904), 1–87 (Geʿez), 127–232
                                (<abbr>ET</abbr>).</bibl>
                            <bibl>E. Isaac, ‘The Ethiopic History of Joseph’, <title rend="italic">Journal for the Study of the Pseudepigrapha</title> 6 (1990),
                                3–125. (<abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>T. P. P. Platt, <title rend="italic">The Ethiopic
                                    Didascalia</title> (1834). (Geʿez with <abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>R.  Schneider, ‘L’histoire d’Ahiqar en éthiopien’, <title rend="italic">Annales d’Éthiopie</title> 11 (1978), 141–52.
                                (Geʿez with <abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>K. Stoffregen Pedersen, <title rend="italic">Traditional Ethiopian
                                    exegesis of the Book of Psalms</title> (<abbr>ÄF</abbr> 36; 1995). (Amharic
                                with <abbr>ET</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. Uhlig, ‘Dersan des Yaʿqob von Serug für den vierten Sonntag im
                                Monat Taḫśaś’, <title rend="italic">Aethiopica</title> 2 (1999),
                                7–52. (Geʿez with <abbr>GT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>B. Velat, <title rend="italic">Études sur le Meʿerāf. Commun de
                                    l’office divin éthiopien</title> (<abbr>PO</abbr> 33; 1966), 284–96.
                                (<abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>B. Velat, <title rend="italic">Meʿerāf. Commun de l’office divin
                                    éthiopien pour toute l’année</title> (<abbr>PO</abbr> 34.1–2; 1966), 76–91.
                                (Geʿez)</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Wurmbrand, ‘Le “Dersâna sanbat”. Une homélie éthiopienne
                                attribuée à Jacques de Saroug’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OS</abbr>
                                </title> 8
                                (1963), 343–394. (<abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>T.  Abraha, ‘Quotations from patristic writings and references to
                                early Christian literature in the <title rend="italic">Books of St.
                                    Yared</title>’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>LM</abbr> 
                        </title> 122 (2009),
                                331–404.</bibl>
                            <bibl>T. Baarda, ‘Another treatise of Aphrahat the Persian sage in
                                Ethiopic translation’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>NTS</abbr>
                                </title> 27 (1980–81),
                                632–40.</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  Cerulli, <title rend="italic">Etiopi in Palestina. Storia
                                    della comunità etiopica di Gerusalemme</title> (2 vols.;
                                1943–47).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. Colin, <title rend="italic">Le synaxaire éthiopien. Index
                                    généraux</title> (<abbr>PO</abbr> 48.3; 1999).</bibl>
                            <bibl>C. Conti Rossini, <title rend="italic">Storia
                                d’Etiopia</title> (1928).</bibl>
                            <bibl>R. W. Cowley, <title rend="italic">The traditional interpretation
                                    of the Apocalypse of St John in the Ethiopian Orthodox
                                    Church</title> (1983).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>R. W. Cowley</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Ethiopian biblical interpretation. A
                                    study in exegetical traditions and hermeneutics</title>
                                (1988).</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  Cruikshank Dodd, <title rend="italic">The frescoes of Mar Musa
                                    al-Habashi. A study in medieval painting in Syria</title>
                                (Studies and Texts 139; 2001).</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  Faultless, ‘The two recensions of the Prologue to John in Ibn
                                al-Ṭayyib’s <title rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospels</title>’,
                                in <title rend="italic">Christians at the heart of Islamic rule.
                                    Church life and scholarship in ʿAbbasid Iraq</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> D. R.
                                Thomas (The History of Christian-Muslim Relations 1; 2003),
                                177–98.</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Graf, ‘Zwei Dogmatische Florilegien der Kopten, B. Das
                                Bekenntnis der Väter’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OCP</abbr>
                                </title> 3 (1937),
                                345–402.</bibl>
                            <bibl>I. Guidi, <title rend="italic">Le traduzioni degli Evangeli in
                                    arabo e in etiopico</title> (1888).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>I. Guidi</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Storia della letteratura
                                    etiopica</title> (1932).</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  Hammerschmidt, <title rend="italic">Studies in the Ethiopic
                                    Anaphoras</title> (<abbr>ÄF</abbr> 25; 2nd revised <abbr>ed.</abbr> 1987).</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  Hammerschmidt and O. A.  Jäger, <title rend="italic">Illuminierte äthiopische Handschriften</title> (Verzeichnis der
                                orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland 15; 1968).</bibl>
                            <bibl>K. S.  Heal, ‘Identifying the Syriac <title rend="italic">Vorlage</title> of the Ethiopic <title rend="italic">History of
                                    Joseph</title>’, in <title rend="italic">Malphono w-rabo
                                    d-malphone</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> G. A. Kiraz (2008), 205–10.</bibl>
                            <bibl>H.  Kaufhold, ‘Notizen über das Moseskloster bei Nabk und das
                                Julianskloster bei Qaryatain in Syrien’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OC</abbr>
                                </title> 79 (1995), 48–119.</bibl>
                            <bibl>M. A.  Knibb, <title rend="italic">Translating the Bible. The
                                    Ethiopic version of the Old Testament</title> (1999).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P.  Marrassini, ‘Some considerations on the problem of the “Syriac
                                influences” on Aksumite Ethiopia’, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                                    Ethiopian Studies</title> 23 (1990), 35–46.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>P.  Marrassini</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Ancora sul problema degli influssi siriaci in età
                                aksumita’, in <title rend="italic">Biblica et semitica. Studi in
                                    memoria di Francesco Vattioni</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> L. Cagni (1999),
                                325–37.</bibl>
                            <bibl>N.  Nebes, ‘Die Märtyrer von Nagrān und das Ende der Ḥimyar. Zur
                                politischen Geschichte Südarabiens im frühen sechsten Jahrhundert’,
                                    <title rend="italic">Aethiopica </title>11 (2008), 7–40.</bibl>
                            <bibl>Th.  Nöldeke, ‘Lehnwörter in und aus dem Äthiopischen’, in his
                                    <title rend="italic">Neue Beiträge zur semitischen
                                    Sprachwissenschaft</title> (1910), 31–66.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.-N. Pérès, ‘Saint Éphrem dans le Sinaxaire éthiopien’, in <title rend="italic">Saint Éphrem, un poète pour notre temps</title>
                                (Patrimoine syriaque, Colloque XI; 2007), 255–63.</bibl>
                            <bibl>H. J.  Polotsky, ‘Aramaic, Syriac, and Geʿez’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JSS</abbr>
                                </title> 9 (1964), 1–10.</bibl>
                            <bibl>T. Tamrat, <title rend="italic">Church and state in Ethiopia.
                                    1270–1527</title> (1972).</bibl>
                            <bibl>S.  Uhlig (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Encyclopaedia
                                    Aethiopica</title> (2003–). (3 vols. of a projected 5 have
                                appeared)</bibl>
                            <bibl>E.  Ullendorff, <title rend="italic">Ethiopia and the
                                    Bible</title> (1967).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A. Vööbus, <title rend="italic">Die Spuren eines älteren
                                    aethiopischen Evangelientextes im Lichte der literarischen
                                    Monumente</title> (<abbr>PETSE</abbr> 2; 1951).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>A. Vööbus</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>  ‘Taʾāmera Iyasus. Zeuge eines älteren äthiopischen
                                Evangelientypus’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OCP</abbr>
                                </title> 17 (1951),
                                462–67.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>A. Vööbus</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>  
                        <title rend="italic">Early versions of the New
                                    Testament</title> (<abbr>PETSE</abbr> 6; 1954), 243–69.</bibl>
                            <bibl>W.  Witakowski, ‘Syrian influences in Ethiopian culture’, <title rend="italic">Orientalia Suecana</title> 38–39 (1989–90),
                                191–202.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>W.  Witakowski</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>  ‘The Miracles of Jesus: An Ethiopian apocryphal Gospel’,
                                    <title rend="italic">Apocrypha</title> 6 (1995), 279–98.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>W.  Witakowski</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Severus of Antioch in Ethiopian tradition’, in <title rend="italic">Studia Aethiopica in honour of Siegbert
                                    Uhlig</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> V.  Böll <abbr>et al.</abbr> (2004), 115–25.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>W.  Witakowski</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Filekseyus, the Ethiopic version of the Syriac Dadisho
                                Qatraya’s Commentary on the Paradise of the Fathers’, <title rend="italic">Rocznik Orientalistycny</title> 59 (2006),
                                281–96.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>W.  Witakowski</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Syrian influences in Ethiopia’, in <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>EAe</abbr>
                                </title>, vol. 4. Forthcoming.</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Wurmbrand, ‘Homélie de Jacques de Saroug sur la mort d’Aaron’,
                                    <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OS</abbr>
                                </title> 6 (1961), 255–78.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Aaron M.</forename> 
                  <surname>Butts</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
