<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Exegesis, Old Testament</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Bas</forename> 
                  <surname>ter Haar Romeny</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Exegesis, Old Testament</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Exegesis-Old-Testament</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/215</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">206</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="156-160"/>
                    <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Old Testament Exegesis</idno>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">The Bible and its interpretation have always played a
                        major world-view of Syriac-speaking Christians.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Bible and its interpretation have always played a major role in the
                        world-view of Syriac-speaking Christians. A great number of texts are
                        preserved in which the Bible is retold or explained. Biblical interpretation
                        is found not only in commentaries, but also in many other genres.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Earliest Syriac Literature</label>
                    <p>The <abbr>OT</abbr> was translated into Syriac at a very early stage, probably even before
                        the New Testament: though the Book of the Laws of Countries (see under <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bardaisan">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bardaiṣan</persName>
                        </ref>) quotes Gen. 9:6 in a form that stands closer to Targum
                        Onqelos, the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Peshitta">Peshitta</ref>
                        <abbr> OT</abbr> is
                        already cited in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tatian">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/771">Tatian</persName>
                        </ref>’s <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diatessaron">Diatessaron</ref> (written in the 170s; Joosten). Neither these works,
                        nor any of the other texts written before the 4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> that have come down
                        to us, is dedicated to the exegesis of the <abbr>OT</abbr>, though such compositions as
                        the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Solomon-Odes-of">Odes of Solomon</ref> and the Hymn of the Pearl (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Thomas-Acts-of">Acts of
                            Thomas</ref>) may certainly have been influenced by it, for instance in
                        the way they describe Paradise.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Fourth- and Early Fifth-Cent. Exegesis</label>
                    <p>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aphrahat">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/10">Aphrahaṭ</persName>
                        </ref>’s twenty-three Demonstrations (between 337 and 345) are
                        treatises based to a large extent on biblical quotations. Aphrahaṭ discusses
                        issues that must have been important to his community, which lived in the
                        Persian Empire. In addition to subjects such as faith, love, fasting,
                        prayer, wars, conversion, humility, and death, he also wrote on themes which
                        suggest that his community had to defend its position vis-à-vis Jewish
                        groups or rather Judaizing tendencies within Christianity. Thus he
                        discusses, among others, circumcision, Pesach, Sabbath, food laws,
                        virginity, and sanctity. Although he wrote against the Jews, especially in
                        his historical interpretation he used Jewish traditions. His spiritual
                        interpretation is mainly typological.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ephrem">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem</persName>
                        </ref>
                        (d. 373) wrote a Commentary on Genesis and an Explanation of Exodus (he may
                        have written commentaries on other books of the <abbr>OT</abbr> as well, as the monk <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Severos-Commentary-of-the-monk">Severos</ref> and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abdisho-bar-Brikha">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/310">ʿAbdishoʿ bar
                            Brikha</persName>
                        </ref> claim, but this can no longer be ascertained). He retells
                        the biblical narrative, while filling the gaps and trying to establish what
                        happened and why. Method and content show a clear affinity with Jewish
                        biblical interpretation; still, no Jewish sources known today are quoted.
                        Although he himself would call most of his exegesis in these commentaries
                        ‘factual’, he did aim at a refutation of Manichean and Marcionite
                        interpretations. He seems less interested here in spiritual exegesis, though
                        there are a number of passing references to Christ. By way of exception, he
                        adds a spiritual interpretation to his factual (historical) exegesis of Gen.
                        49. In marked contrast to these commentaries, his <hi rend="italic">memre</hi> (homilies, mostly in verse) and <hi rend="italic">madrāše</hi> (often translated as ‘hymns’) show a wealth of symbols. In
                        the Hymns on Paradise (11.6–7) he explains that in addition to the factual
                        meaning one should try to find the ‘hidden power’ of the plain terms, or
                        ‘pale colors’, which God uses in order to communicate with human beings. In
                        these hymns the horizon is not the end of the <abbr>OT</abbr> period, but the eschaton.
                        Still, the commentaries and the poetic works remain connected through a
                        common basis, formed by Ephrem’s factual interpretation as well as his
                        theological interests.</p>
                    <p>The particular genre of Ephrem’s commentaries (close to that of the
                        ‘rewritten Bible’) was not commonly followed by later Syriac exegetes, but
                        his poetry became a great source of inspiration. In the 5th and 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>,
                        and even later, many <hi rend="italic">memre</hi> and <hi rend="italic">madrāše</hi> were written (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Poetry">Poetry</ref>), of which
                        some were attributed to Ephrem. Most of these <hi rend="italic"> memre</hi> are sermons in verse, but some are rather narrative poems in
                        which a biblical story is retold. A special form of <hi rend="italic">madrāšā</hi> is formed by the genre of the dialogue poem, in which two
                        biblical characters speak in alternating verses. The oldest Syriac
                        representatives of this ancient genre were indeed written by Ephrem himself,
                        but many others are anonymous. In Greek numerous works survive under the
                        name of Ephrem, but most of these are not authentic.</p>
                    <p>Not long after Ephrem, the anonymous author of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Book-of-Steps">Book of Steps</ref>
                        uses biblical interpretation to teach about a perfect, ascetic way of life.
                        The author has a number of ideas in common with Aphrahaṭ and Ephrem, but in
                        contrast to them he does not incorporate Jewish traditions in his work. The
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Cave-of-Treasures">Cave of
                            Treasures</ref> recounts biblical history from the Creation to
                        Pentecost. Its use of apocryphal traditions (<choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>on Adam and Eve) has led
                        some scholars to assume an early date for this composition, but in its
                        present state it certainly does not antedate the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> (Leonhard 2004).
                        Though the author clearly used Jewish traditions, his reconstruction of
                        history omits parts which are important for Judaism, such as the time of
                        Moses.</p>
                    <p>Commentaries on Qohelet and Job are attributed to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yohannan-Ihidaya">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/827">Yoḥannan
                            Iḥidaya</persName>
                        </ref>. The latter is, however, a text translated from Greek (Van
                        Rompay 2006b). The Qohelet commentary, however, which was quoted by both
                        East and West Syrians, could have well been written by Yoḥannan Iḥidaya in
                        the first half of the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> He paraphrases the text and discusses its
                        historical setting and purpose; at the same time, he does not shun
                        allegorical interpretation.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Parting of the Ways: From the Middle of the Fifth <abbr>Cent.</abbr>
                        until the Advent of Islam</label>
                    <p>The <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa-School-of">School of Edessa</ref> played a pivotal role in the further development
                        of the Syr. exegetical tradition. It was probably here that the works of
                            <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodore-of-Mopsuestia">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/780">Theodore
                            of Mopsuestia</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 428) were translated into Syriac. This Greek
                        Antiochene theologian and exegete was one of the main sources of inspiration
                        for the Dyophysites. Even during his lifetime his works were already studied
                        in the School and his hermeneutic principles and terminology were taken
                        over, together with his Christology and his view on history as a
                        manifestation of God’s pedagogic interaction with humankind. A loyal
                        follower of Theodore was <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Narsai">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/650">Narsai</persName>
                        </ref> (d. <abbr>ca.</abbr> 500),
                        the author of many <hi rend="italic">memre</hi> discussing <abbr>OT</abbr> passages. He
                        was head of the School of Edessa until he had to flee to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/142">Nisibis</placeName>
                        </ref>, probably
                        around 471, where he became head of the newly founded <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis-School-of">School of
                            Nisibis</ref>. Narsai knew Theodore’s works very well, and almost
                        totally and exclusively adhered to his views. Theodore was considered the
                        Interpreter <hi rend="italic">par excellence</hi> by him as well as in the
                        later E.-Syr. tradition.</p>
                    <p>The adoption of Theodore’s Christology and anthropology also met with
                        resistance, however. The early miaphysite exegete and poet <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Serugh">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Yaʿqub of Serugh
                        </persName>
                        </ref> (d. 521), for example, felt more at home with Ephrem’s views and those
                        of moderate Alexandrians. Like Narsai, he mainly wrote <hi rend="italic">memre</hi>, many of which interpret the <abbr>OT</abbr>. Yet Yaʿqub and Narsai had
                        more in common. First of all, they shared a common Edessene tradition. In
                        addition, it seems that the miaphysite opposition to Theodore did not
                        necessarily lead to the acceptance of the radical allegorizing trend of some
                        Alexandrians, who were ready to abandon the plain sense of Scripture
                        altogether. Though Yaʿqub and other Miaphysites protested against certain
                        parts of Theodore’s thought, through their connections with the School of
                        Edessa they were influenced by his exegetical method and sought to achieve a
                        balance between the Antiochene ‘historical’ approach and spiritual exegesis.
                        Early translations of the Antiochene exegete <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/John-Chrysostom">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/573">John
                            Chrysostom</persName>
                        </ref> were also widely read by Miaphysites and Dyophysites
                        alike.</p>
                    <p>From the 6th- and 7th-cent. E.-Syr. tradition we know names such as <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ahob-Qatraya">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/324">Aḥob
                            Qaṭraya</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nathniel-of-Sirzor">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/651">Nathniel of
                                Sirzor</persName>
                        </ref>, and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Henana">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/530">Ḥenana of Adiabene</persName>
                        </ref>, but we have
                        no more than fragments of their exegesis. We do know that there was a crisis
                        connected to the latter, who directed the School of Nisibis from 572 to 610.
                        Much of the background to this crisis is no longer clear to us. His
                        Christological views were condemned at a meeting of bps. in 612. His views
                        may also have been more accommodating toward allegorical interpretations of
                        the <abbr>OT</abbr>. However, as Reinink (2010) has indicated, the popular statement that
                        Ḥenana rejected Theodore’s exegesis in favor of that of John Chrysostom is
                        an oversimplification. The main problem seems to have been that Ḥenana
                        showed some openness toward sources other than Theodore of Mopsuestia.</p>
                    <p>The mid-6th-cent. Commentary on the Psalms by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Daniel-of-Salah">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/59">Daniel of Ṣalaḥ
                        </persName>
                        </ref> gives us insight into the developing miaphysite tradition. Its
                        interest in the historical setting and purpose of each Psalm reminds one of
                        the Antiochene approach of Theodore of Mopsuestia. On the other hand, his
                        exegesis often leads to an allegorical interpretation, which becomes quite
                        prominent in his commentary. As the Psalms were read daily in the
                        monasteries, it was important to control their interpretation. Daniel
                        supplied the miaphysite leadership with a commentary in the form of 150
                        coherent, self-contained homilies, which were ideally suited to this
                        purpose. They helped shape his community’s doctrine but also addressed
                        larger political issues. It is here that we find the first serious attacks
                        on the position of the emperor (Taylor 2010).</p>
                    <p>As an alternative to the dyophysite use of Theodore of Mopsuestia, the
                        Miaphysites used a wider selection of Greek Fathers. Long and short versions
                        of commentaries by authors such as <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Athanasius-of-Alexandria">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/354">Athanasius</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Cyril-of-Alexandria">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/430">Cyril of Alexandria</persName>
                        </ref>, and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Gregory-of-Nyssa">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/512">Gregory of
                            Nyssa</persName>
                        </ref> have come down to us. It appears that the shorter ones
                        constitute abbreviations of the longer ones, which date back to the 5th and
                        6th <abbr>cent.</abbr> 
                  <hi rend="italic">Terminus ad quem</hi> for the abbreviated
                        versions of the three authors just mentioned is the so-called London
                        Collection (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Brit. Libr. Add. 12,168), which was composed probably in the
                        second quarter of the 7th  cent. The London Collection consists of extracts
                        from various, primarily Greek, authors in Syriac translation, forming a
                        commentary on most of the <abbr>OT</abbr> and <abbr>NT</abbr>. It is a work of encyclopedic scope. It
                        would seem that the compiler is offering miaphysite readers a digest of
                        Greek material in a form that is meant to replace earlier Syriac material.
                        He often quotes Athanasius, Cyril, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Severus-of-Antioch">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of
                            Antioch</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Gregory-of-Nazianzus">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/511">Gregory of
                            Nazianzus</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Basil-of-Caesarea">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/376">Basil the
                            Great</persName>
                        </ref>, Gregory of Nyssa, and John Chrysostom; Ephrem and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/John-bar-Aphtonia">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/52">John bar Aphtonia</persName>
                        </ref> are the only Syriac authors mentioned. The
                        compiler took as the basis for his commentary the Syriac translation of the
                        Greek biblical text of his sources as well as the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syro-Hexapla">Syro-Hexapla</ref>.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Later E.-Syr. Exegetical Tradition</label>
                    <p>Even though Theodore of Mopsuestia was known as <hi rend="italic">the</hi>
                        Interpreter among the East Syrians, only fragments of the original 5th-cent.
                        translations have come down to us. It seems that he was soon deemed too
                        difficult to read. The simplification, explication, and defense of Theodore
                        of Mopsuestia therefore formed a large part of the E.-Syr. exegetical
                        efforts in the 8th and 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> The witnesses to this process of
                        simplification include some unedited question-and-answer collections
                        attributed to Theodore himself, the Psalter commentaries of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Denha">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/97">Denḥa</persName>
                        </ref>-Grigor and of
                        <abbr>ms.</abbr> Sachau 215, and the works to be discussed presently.</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoros-bar-Koni">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/783">Theodoros bar Koni</persName>
                        </ref>’s Book of the Scholion (<hi rend="italic">Ktābā d-eskoliyon</hi>), written <abbr>ca.</abbr> 792, explains problems in the form
                        of questions and answers. It is in fact a systematic introduction to the
                        entire E.-Syr. intellectual tradition. The author presents his work as an
                        aid to understanding the commentaries of the Blessed Interpreter for those
                        who have only just embarked on the study of his works. Theodoros bar Koni
                        was indeed a very loyal follower of Theodore of Mopsuestia. One of his main
                        sources must have been a collection of traditional material representing the
                        common stock of E.-Syr. exegesis, in which problems in Theodore’s exegesis
                        were dealt with, as well as objections against him.</p>
                    <p>Around the same time as Bar Koni, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Isho-bar-Nun">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/552">Ishoʿ bar Nun</persName>
                        </ref>
                        wrote his Selected Questions on the entire Bible. This collection follows
                        the biblical text without adding the kind of non-exegetical material that
                        Bar Koni supplies. If these two authors used the same or a comparable
                        collection of traditional exegesis at all, we must conclude that Ishoʿ bar
                        Nun reworked this collection more thoroughly than Bar Koni did. The number
                        of literal agreements between the two authors is very small. Another
                        characteristic that sets Ishoʿ bar Nun apart from Bar Koni and Theodore of
                        Mopsuestia is the use of the concept of <hi rend="italic">theoria</hi> in a
                        way that most Antiochenes would denounce as allegory.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps the closest we can get to the exegetical collection that may have
                        been used at least by Bar Koni is the anonymous Commentary on Genesis–Exodus
                        9:32 of the <abbr>ms.</abbr> (<choice>
                     <reg>
                        <hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                     </reg>
                     <orig>olim</orig>
                  </choice>) Diyarbakır 22. Like Ishoʿ bar Nun’s Selected
                        Questions, this work does not have the encyclopedic character of the
                        commentaries by Bar Koni and Ishoʿdad. It presents itself as an independent,
                        original commentary, though it is clear that its core goes back to Theodore
                        of Mopsuestia. As the Diyarbakır Commentary is not reworked in the form of
                        questions and answers, we are often — but not always — closer to the
                        original words of Theodore.</p>
                    <p>In its present form the Diyarbakır Commentary covers only a very small part
                        of the Bible (Gen.–Ex. 9:32), but Van Rompay (1977) has been able to show
                        that this work formed the core of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ishodad-of-Merv">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/555">Ishoʿdad of
                            Merv</persName>
                        </ref>’s commentaries on these parts of the Bible (9th-cent.).
                        Ishoʿdad added other material to this and also used Ishoʿ bar Nun. Even
                        though Ishoʿdad may occasionally have had access to the original Syriac
                        translations of Theodore of Mopsuestia’s works, his knowledge of the
                        Interpreter was often mediated by the Diyarbakır Commentary and other
                        sources. A unique feature of Ishoʿdad’s work is its use of authors that did
                        not commonly belong to the E.-Syr. tradition, among whom are even the
                        Miaphysites Severus of Antioch and Cyril of Alexandria.</p>
                    <p>The Diyarbakır Commentary also formed the basis of the so-called Anonymous
                        Commentary on the Pentateuch. In <abbr>ms.</abbr> (<choice>
                     <reg>
                        <hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                     </reg>
                     <orig>olim</orig>
                  </choice>) Diyarbakır 22 we find a version
                        of the latter work which includes the rest of the <abbr>OT</abbr> as well. For the
                        sections where the Diyarbakır Commentary is extant, the Anonymous Commentary
                        summarizes Diyarbakır while adding a limited amount of material from other
                        sources, including Ishoʿdad. One source almost identical to the Diyarbakır
                        Commentary and another close to Ishoʿdad and the Anonymous Commentary were
                        employed in the <abbr>OT</abbr> sections of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Gannat-Bussame">Gannat
                            Bussāme</ref> (‘Garden of Delights’), together with fragments of the
                        exegetical <hi rend="italic">memre</hi> of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aba-II-of-Kashkar">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/307">Aba II of
                            Kashkar</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 751). The <hi rend="italic">Gannat Bussāme</hi> is
                        probably a 10th-cent. commentary on the pericopes read in the liturgy,
                        arranged according to the liturgical year.</p>
                    <p>Ishoʿdad was probably also the main source for the Paradise of Christianity
                        by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ibn-al-Tayyib">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/543">Ibn
                            al-Ṭayyib</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 1043), a commentary on a large part of the Bible.
                        This E.-Syr. author wrote in Arabic and became the intermediary of the
                        Theodorian tradition not only to other Christian-Arabic authors, but also to
                        <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ethiopic-Christianity-Syriac-contacts-with">Ethiopic Christianity</ref>. A different voice is heard
                        in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Eliya-of-al-Anbar">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/471">Eliya of al-Anbār</persName>
                        </ref>’s Book of Instruction (<hi rend="italic">Ktābā
                            d-durrāšā</hi>; 10th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), in which a number of <abbr>OT</abbr> passages receive
                        allegorical interpretations. In contrast to him, his contemporary <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Emmanuel-bar-Shahhare">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/473">Emmanuel bar Shahhare</persName>
                        </ref>’s Hexaemeron is inspired by Narsai, even in
                        the form of the work, which consists of 28 <hi rend="italic">memre</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The last two E.-Syr. works to be mentioned, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shlemon-of-Basra">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/745">Shlemon of
                            Baṣra</persName>
                        </ref>’s Book of the Bee (13th <abbr>cent.</abbr>) and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ishaq-Shbadnaya">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/551">Isḥaq
                            Shbadnaya</persName>
                        </ref>’s Poem on the Divine Economy (15th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), discuss the
                        entire history of salvation in prose. These works contain much exegetical
                        material, while the latter author also adds a prose commentary with
                        quotations from the earlier exegetical tradition.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Later W.-Syr. Exegetical Tradition</label>
                    <p>As we have seen above, in the 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr> W.-Syr. exegesis was very much
                        dominated by a number of Greek authors who were read in Syriac translation.
                        The great polymath <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Edessa">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/113">Yaʿqub of Edessa</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 708) and his
                        followers adopted many of their interpretations. He is not only the author
                        of a revision of the Peshitta, but he also wrote a Commentary in short on
                        the Octateuch (Kruisheer), a large number of Scholia, a Commentary on the
                        Hexaemeron, and a number of letters of exegetical content. The works of
                        Athanasius, Cyril, and Gregory of Nyssa were thus ‘Syriacized’ in three
                        stages: after the full translation, an abbreviated version was produced;
                        finally later Syriac authors such as Yaʿqub wrote their own
                        commentaries using either the shorter or the full version, and appropriating
                        interpretations often without indicating their sources. Though the 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        was the heyday of the very precise and literal mirror translations, at the
                        same time a movement began that aimed to make the main exegetical texts more
                        accessible and especially more compact.</p>
                    <p>The <abbr>OT</abbr> part of the Commentary by the monk Severos (written in 861) likewise
                        represents the movement just mentioned. Severos’s work consists, as he
                        himself states, of a commentary on difficult words of the <abbr>OT</abbr>, based mainly
                        on Ephrem and Yaʿqub of Edessa, and a commentary on the <abbr>NT</abbr>, based mainly on
                        John Chrysostom. There are a number of longer additions in this text, and in
                        addition Shemʿun, the scribe of <abbr>ms.</abbr> Vat. Syr. 103, added a number of
                        marginal comments. The biblical text quoted is that of the Peshitta, and for
                        the <abbr>OT</abbr>, the number of explicit references to Greek exegetes (most of which
                        were added by Shemʿun rather than Severos) is low. All in all, the work
                        seems to be the opposite of the London Collection: this is the best of
                        Syriac exegesis on the authentic Syriac Bible, with rather limited use of
                        Greek sources. This fits very well with the atmosphere among the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        in the 8th and 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, when Greek learning had become less popular and
                        even suspect.</p>
                    <p>From the period of Severos, one should also mention the work of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mushe-bar-Kipho">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/173">Mushe
                            bar Kipho</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 903), which also builds on predecessors, including
                        Yaʿqub of Edessa. He must have written a commentary on most of the Bible,
                        but on the <abbr>OT</abbr> mainly a Commentary on the Hexaemeron and a Commentary on
                        Psalms have survived. Interestingly, he also quotes ‘Theodore the
                        Nestorian’.</p>
                    <p>The 10th and 11th <abbr>cent.</abbr> show little activity in the field of W.-Syr.
                        exegesis. It was not until the period of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Renaissance-Syriac">Syriac
                            Renaissance</ref> in the 12th and 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> that <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysios-bar-Salibi">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/212">Dionysios
                            bar Ṣalibi</persName>
                        </ref> and <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/239">Bar ʿEbroyo</persName>
                        </ref> compiled new
                        exegetical collections. These works lean on earlier collections, but also
                        show evidence of further ‘cultivation’ and ‘pruning’ of the tradition. A
                        notable feature, for instance, is Bar ʿEbroyo’s openness toward the E.-Syr.
                        tradition. After the 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, hardly any new material was added to the
                        W.-Syr. exegetical tradition.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Conclusion</label>
                    <p>Syriac biblical interpretation shows a unique richness of metaphors and depth
                        of spirituality. At the same time, its typological and symbolic
                        interpretations are usually based on an explanation of the plain sense,
                        answering the simple questions of what happened and why. Based on a long
                        literary tradition Syriac-speaking Christians developed their own genres,
                        both in prose and poetry. Yet from its very beginning Syriac exegesis has
                        also shown openness to other traditions. Ephrem already knew about different
                        versions of the biblical text, and the use of alternative readings would
                        remain a feature of many later Syriac commentaries. He and his
                        contemporaries also used Jewish exegetical traditions. In the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        Greek interpretations were taken over that may have appeared more precise
                        and systematic than the earlier Syriac tradition, but they were actually
                        quite similar in terms of their general approach to the biblical text. Greek
                        sources became so popular that the exegetes of the 6th and 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr> even
                        seem to have lost sight of the earlier Syriac tradition.</p>
                    <p>The balance was redressed, however, after the 7th  cent., paradoxically when
                        Arab rule gradually began to weaken the position of the Syr. Churches. In
                        this period, their members started editing anthologies and summaries of
                        earlier exegetical literature. In the process of sifting, selecting, and
                        summarizing, choices were made and new elements were added. Thus they built
                        authoritative interpretative traditions that helped to give answers to
                        questions posed by the political and religious circumstances of the period.
                        Though the translation of Greek texts in the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> can be associated
                        with the split between the Syr. Churches, later exegetes would also
                        recognize the common ground formed by the teaching of Ephrem and the
                        Cappadocians, by the Antiochene interpretation and method of John
                        Chrysostom, and by philological comments, even if they originated with their
                        doctrinal opponents. Some of the existing collections have assumed canonical
                        status themselves, and are fostered and studied to the present day.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Becker, <title rend="italic">Fear of God</title>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. P.  Brock, <title rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac
                                tradition</title> (Gorgias Handbooks 7; 2006).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Joosten, ‘The Old Testament in the New: The Syriac versions of the
                            New Testament as a witness to the text of the Old Testament Peshitta’,
                            in <title rend="italic">The Peshitta. Its use in literature and liturgy.
                                Papers read at the Third Peshitta Symposium</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. B.  ter
                            Haar Romeny (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 15; 2006), 99–106.</bibl>
                        <bibl>D.  Kruisheer, ‘Ephrem, Jacob of Edessa, and the Monk Severus. An
                            analysis of <abbr>Ms.</abbr> Vat. Syr. 103, ff. 1–72’, in <abbr>
                                <title rend="italic">SymSyr</title> VII</abbr>, 599–605.</bibl>
                        <bibl>C.  Leonhard, <title rend="italic">Ishodad of Merw’s exegesis of the
                                Psalms 119 and 139–147. A study of his interpretation in the light
                                of the Syriac translation of Theodore of Mopsuestia’s
                                Commentary</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 585, Subs. 107; 2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>C.  Leonhard</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Die Beschneidung Christi in der syrischen Schatzhöhle.
                            Beobachtungen zu Datierung und Überlieferung des Werks’, in <title rend="italic">Syriaca II. Beiträge zum 3. deutschen
                                Syrologen-Symposium</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> M. Tamcke (<abbr>SOK</abbr> 33; 2004),
                            11–28.</bibl>
                        <bibl>G. J.  Reinink, ‘Tradition and the formation of the “Nestorian”
                            identity in sixth- to seventh-century Iraq’, in <title rend="italic">Religious origins of nations? The Christian communities of the
                                Middle East</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. B. ter Haar Romeny (2010),
                            217–50.</bibl>
                        <bibl>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny, ‘Question-and-answer collections in Syriac
                            literature’, in <title rend="italic">Erotapokriseis: Early Christian
                                Question-and-Answer literature in context</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A.  Volgers
                            and C.  Zamagni (2004), 145–63.</bibl>
                        <bibl>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny, ‘The Greek vs. the Peshitta in a West Syrian
                            exegetical collection (BL Add. 12168)’, in <title rend="italic">The
                                Peshitta. Its use in literature and liturgy. Papers read at the
                                Third Peshitta Symposium</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. B. ter Haar Romeny (<abbr>MPIL</abbr>
                            15; 2006), 297–310.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Greek or Syriac? Chapters in the establishment of a Syrian
                            Orthodox exegetical tradition’, in <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>StPatr</abbr>
                            </title>,
                            vol. 41, <abbr>ed.</abbr> F. Young <abbr>et al.</abbr> (2006), 89–95.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Les Pères grecs dans les florilèges exégétiques syriaques’, in
                                <title rend="italic">Les Pères grecs dans la tradition
                                syriaque</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Schmidt and D. Gonnet, SJ (<abbr>ÉtSyr</abbr> 4; 2007),
                            63–76.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Ephrem and Jacob of Edessa in the Commentary of the Monk
                            Severus’, in <title rend="italic">Malphono w-Rabo d-Malphone</title>,
                            <abbr>ed.</abbr> Kiraz, 535–57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. D.  Ryan, <title rend="italic">Dionysius bar Salibi’s factual and
                                spiritual Commentary on Psalms 73–82</title> (Cahiers de la Revue
                            Biblique 57; 2004).</bibl>
                        <bibl>D. G. K.  Taylor, ‘The manuscript tradition of Daniel of Ṣalaḥ’s Psalm
                            Commentary’, in <abbr>
                                <title rend="italic">SymSyr</title> VII</abbr>, 61–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>D. G. K.  Taylor</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘The Psalm Commentary of Daniel of Salah and the formation of
                            sixth-century Syrian Orthodox identity’, in <title rend="italic">Religious origins of nations? The Christian communities of the
                                Middle East</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. B. ter Haar Romeny (2010), 65–92.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.  Van Rompay, ‘Išoʿ bar Nun and Išoʿdad of Merv. New data for the
                            study of the interdependence of their exegetical works’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OLP</abbr>
                            </title> 8 (1977), 229–49.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Van Rompay</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘La littérature exégètique syriaque et le rapprochement des
                            traditions syrienne-orientale et syrienne-occidentale’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ParOr</abbr>
                            </title> 20 (1995), 221–35.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Van Rompay</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘The Christian Syriac tradition of interpretation’, in <title rend="italic">Hebrew Bible / Old Testament: The history of its
                                interpretation</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> M. Sæbø <abbr>et al.</abbr>, I.1 (1996),
                            612–41.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Van Rompay</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Development of Biblical interpretation in the Syrian Churches
                            of the Middle Ages’, in <title rend="italic">Hebrew Bible / Old
                                Testament: The history of its interpretation</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> M. Sæbø et
                            al., I.2 (2000), 559–77.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Van Rompay</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Past and present perceptions of Syriac literary tradition’,
                                <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                            </title> 3.1 (2000).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Van Rompay</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Between the school and the monk’s cell: The Syriac Old
                            Testament commentary tradition’, in <title rend="italic">The Peshitta.
                                Its use in literature and liturgy. Papers read at the Third Peshitta
                                Symposium</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. B. ter Haar Romeny (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 15; 2006),
                            27–51.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Van Rompay</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘An ascetic reading of the Book of Job. Fragments from a Syriac
                            commentary attributed to John the Solitary (<abbr>Ms.</abbr> London, British Library,
                            Add. 18814, f. 91r–95r)’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>LM</abbr>
                            </title> 119 (2006),
                            1–24.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Bas</forename> 
                  <surname>ter Haar Romeny</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
