<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Gabriel, Monastery of Mor</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Andrew N.</forename> 
                  <surname>Palmer</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Gabriel, Monastery of Mor</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Gabriel-Monastery-of-Mor</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/223</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">214</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="167-169"/>
                    <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Monastery of Mor Gabriel</idno>
                    <idno type="althead">Monastery of Qarṭmin</idno>
                    <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/place/226</idno>
                    <note type="type">place</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Famous monastery in Tur Abdin, founded in the late fourth century.<note>not a summary</note>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <ab type="infobox">Monastery of Qarṭmin</ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Monastery of Qarṭmin began long before its official foundation date of
                        397. The founders were Shmuel (Samuel) of Eshtin and his disciple Shemʿun
                        (Simeon) of Qarṭmin. In the village of Qarṭmin (Yayvantepe) there is a
                        church of the martyred <abbr>bp.</abbr> Karpos, Shmuel’s spiritual father. Karpos was
                        killed, according to the Life of Shmuel, by Persian raiders on the southern
                        escarpment of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tur-Abdin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/221">Ṭur ʿAbdin</placeName>
                        </ref>, which
                        rises from the Plain of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/142">Nisibis</placeName>
                        </ref>. The most
                        likely context is 350, when Nisibis, then a Roman city, was besieged. Shmuel
                        fled north from the raiders, into the hills, and so came to the village of
                        Qarṭmin, where he acquired a disciple, Shemʿun. Together they lived in a
                        ruined temple now called ‘The Arches of Mor Gabriel’. Then the boy Shemʿun
                        had a dream in which he was commanded by an angel to build a Beth Ṣlutho
                        (open-air enclosure for prayer) further to the west. Perhaps Shemʿun was
                        still alive when, more than forty years later, the Roman Emperor established
                        the institution officially by his benefaction in 397.</p>
                    <p>The answer to the question of how the <choice>
                            <sic>Emperor</sic>
                            <corr>emperor</corr>
                        </choice> in Constantinople came to hear
                        of this remote monastery and to consider it worthy of his attention must be
                        connected with the Roman frontier-garrison in the Castle of Tur ʿAbdin built
                        after the Persian raid of 350. The Christian soldiers in the castle honoured
                        the holy men of Qarṭmin and attributed the security of the frontier partly
                        to their prayers. It may well be that the Emperor also believed in the
                        efficacy of the holy men’s prayers and that the first large benefactions to
                        Qarṭmin (gold to build buildings, valuable communion vessels, and vestments
                        for the liturgy) were intended not only to raise morale, but also to
                        propitiate the God of Victories. The gesture of Honorius and Arcadius was
                        repeated even more generously by the following administration, that of
                        Theodosius II.</p>
                    <p>Theodosius’s death nearly coincided with the Council of Chalcedon (451), for
                        which the new Emperor, Marcian, was personally responsible. Considering the
                        later reputation of Qarṭmin as a focus of opposition to Chalcedon, it seems
                        likely that, by disagreeing with that council, the monks forfeited a
                        benefaction from this emperor. For the rest of the century confusion
                        reigned. Some emperors, like Zeno and Anastasius, tried to compromise on the
                        apparently insoluble issue of Chalcedon. But in 512, Anastasius, changing
                        his policy, sided with the opponents of the Council. In the same year,
                        according to the record preserved at Qarṭmin, he caused a church with a
                        splendid prayer hall to be built there. This is still in use as the main
                        church of the monastery. It seems likely that he also built the so-called
                        ‘Dome of Theodora’, an octagon of identical height and building materials,
                        and that this was originally used as a baptistery. Later, when there were no
                        longer large numbers of adult converts to Christianity who came to the
                        monastery to be baptized after making a penitential pilgrimage, the dome was
                        used as a kitchen. The great slab in the main church was made in the 8th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> for the purpose of making bread dough; for many centuries it stood
                        under the dome.</p>
                    <p>After Anastasius, no emperor declared himself an opponent of Chalcedon, and
                        no emperor made a benefaction to Qarṭmin. There is a story that the Empress
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodora-Empress">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/779">Theodora</persName>
                        </ref>, consort of Justinian I, who was
                        undoubtedly a great friend of monks and especially of those opposed to the
                        Council of Chalcedon, visited Qarṭmin and gave it the dome which is named
                        after her. This report is unworthy of credence.</p>
                    <p>The monastery became the residence of a <abbr>bp.</abbr> when the Persian Conquest created
                        vacancies on four sees in the area; the abbot of Qarṭmin was asked to fill
                        them all until suitable men could be found for those outside Ṭur ʿAbdin. By
                        the time of the Arab Conquest, in 639/40, the abbot of Qarṭmin, now Gabriel
                        of Beth Qustan (Bequsyone), was managing two dioceses from his monastery:
                        that of Ṭur ʿAbdin and that of Dara. No doubt the success with which he
                        negotiated a treaty with the Arab conquerors, protecting the rights of the
                        Christians in his region, made him great in the eyes of later generations.
                        When his Life came to be written, little was remembered about him, which
                        shows that it took time for him to acquire the reputation of a saint. He had
                        certainly acquired it by the year 774, in which the plague raged in Ṭur
                        ʿAbdin, killing 94 monks at Qarṭmin and all the prominent people at <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Salib-Dayr">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/68">Dayr
                            al-Ṣalīb</placeName>
                        </ref>. After 30 Qarṭmin monks had died in a single night, the
                        corpse of Gabriel was exhumed and fixed upright in the church to pray for an
                        end to the plague. After this, the right arm was detached and taken to Ḥaḥ,
                        near Dayr al-Ṣalīb, to bring an end to the plague there also.</p>
                    <p>The loss of 94 monks did not bring to an end the prosperity of Qarṭmin, which
                        was now sometimes called Dayro d-ʿUmro (Arabic <hi rend="italic">Dayr
                            al-ʿUmr</hi>), though it did perhaps make people begin to call it ‘The
                        Monastery of Gabriel’. The miracle performed by Mor Gabriel may also have
                        created a need for a written history of the monastery including the Lives of
                        Shmuel and Shemʿun and a Life of Gabriel (‘The Qarṭmin Trilogy’).</p>
                    <p>Mor Shemʿun d-Zayte, ‘Simeon of the Olive-Trees’ (d. 734), a monk of Qarṭmin,
                        became <abbr>bp.</abbr> of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Harran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/216">Ḥarran</placeName>
                        </ref> and used his influence to build in and around Nisibis,
                        whose Christian community (existing alongside Zoroastrians) was largely Ch.
                        of E., profit-making installations, such as olive-presses, water-mills,
                        bath-houses, and inns, which would add to the income of the Monastery of
                        Qarṭmin. Qarṭmin remained buoyant into the late 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>; but after about
                        800 a decline set in. The 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> seems to have been a period of low ebb.
                        ‘Mor Gabriel’s Monastery’ settled down into a cosy relationship with the
                        neighbouring villages, particularly Beth Sbirino (Bsorino) to the east. It
                        was a man from that village, <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>bp.</sic>
                                <corr>Bp.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> Yuḥanon, who revived, in the 11th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        (after it had been extinct for a <abbr>cent.</abbr>), the ancient Edessene script for use
                        in making new parchment copies of the Gospels. He called it <hi rend="italic">sreṭ ewangeliyon</hi> ‘Gospel script’ (one of the possible
                        etymologies of the name esṭrangelo). One ms. written out and illustrated by
                        his nephews, Emmanuel and Niho, monks of Qarṭmin, is extant in Berlin. <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/239">Bar ʿEbroyo</persName>
                        </ref> speaks of a total of seventy such volumes
                        by these calligraphists in the library of Qarṭmin. This ‘renaissance’ was
                        ultimately the consequence of the Byzantine reconquest of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Melitene">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/136">Melitene</placeName>
                        </ref> in
                        934.</p>
                    <p>The Monastery of Mor Gabriel is today the residence of the <abbr>bp.</abbr> of Ṭur ʿAbdin
                        and gives the appearance of great prosperity, though the villages all around
                        are becoming depopulated.</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/52">Fig. 52</ref> and <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/53">53</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <p>(For further details and literature, see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tur-Abdin">Ṭur ʿAbdin</ref>)</p>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Aydin, <title rend="italic">Das Leben des heiligen Gabriel. The
                                Life of Saint Gabriel. Tašʿito d-qadišo Mor
                            Gabriʾel</title> (2009).</bibl>
                        <bibl>F.  Briquel-Chatonnet, ‘Note sur l’histoire du monastère de
                            Saint-Gabriel de Qartamin’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>LM</abbr>
                            </title> 98 (1985),
                            95–102.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. P.  Brock, ‘The Fenqitho of the Monastery of Mor Gabriel in Tur
                            ʿAbdin’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OKS</abbr>
                            </title> 28 (1979), 168–82.</bibl>
                        <bibl>P. Y.  Dolapönü, <title rend="italic">Maktab zabne d- ʿumro qadišo
                                d-Qarṭmin</title> (Mardin, 1959). (in Syriac; Turkish edition in
                                <title rend="italic">Mor Gabriel. Dayrul-umur tarihi</title>
                            [Istanbul, 1971])</bibl>
                        <bibl>Fiey, <title rend="italic">Pour un Oriens christianus novus</title>,
                            254–6.</bibl>
                        <bibl>E. J. W.  Hawkins and M. C.  Mundell, ‘The mosaics of the monastery of
                            Mar Samuel, Mar Simeon and Mar Gabriel near Kartmin’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>DOP</abbr>
                            </title> (1973), 279–96.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Leroy, ‘Deux baptistères paléochrétiens d’Orient méconnus’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>CahArch</abbr>
                            </title> 25 (1976), 1–6.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A. N. Palmer, <title rend="italic">Sources for the history of the
                                Abbey of Qartmin in Tur ʿAbdin</title> (Ph.D. Diss., Oxford;
                            1982).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>A. N. Palmer</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Tašʿyoto d-qadiše mor(y) šmuʾel w-mor(y)
                                šemʿun w-mor(y) gabriʾel d-Qarṭmin</title> [The Lives of Saint
                            Shmuel, Saint Shemʿun and Saint Gabriel of Qarṭmin] (Glane/Losser,
                            1983).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>A. N. Palmer</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Monk and mason on the Tigris frontier: the
                                early history of Ṭur ʿAbdin</title> (University of Cambridge
                            Oriental Publications 39; 1990).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>A. N. Palmer</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘The Life of Gabriel of Qartmīn’, in <title rend="italic">Christian-Muslim relations</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> Thomas and Roggema,
                            892–7.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Andrew N.</forename> 
                  <surname>Palmer</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
