<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Hakkari</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>James F.</forename> 
                  <surname>Coakley</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Hakkari</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Hakkari</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/254</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">245</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="186-187"/>
                    <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/place/90</idno>
                    <note type="type">place</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Region in the southeast corner of <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/648">Turkey</placeName>; until 1915 the homeland of the majority of Christians belonging to the Ch. of
                        E..<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The region in the southeast corner of Turkey dominated by the mountains Cilo
                        Dag (4170 m.) and Sat Dag (3810 m.), and the highlands around them, cut by
                        the gorges of the Great Zab River and its tributaries. The spelling <hi rend="italic">Hakkiari</hi> is also found in English sources. In modern
                        Turkey <hi rend="italic">Hakkâri</hi> is the name of a province and of its
                        capital town, the former Julamerk (Cölemerik). There is no Christian
                        population now (only more or less ruined churches), but until 1915 Hakkari
                        was the homeland of the majority of Christians belonging to the Ch. of
                        E.</p>
                    <p>Within what is now Hakkari the dioceses of Beth Dasen and Beth <choice>
                            <sic>Bgash</sic>
                            <corr>Begash</corr>
                        </choice> are
                        known from the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, and the evidence of local saints, such as Mar
                        Zayʿa whose cult was in Jilu, may take the church history of the region back
                        to the 4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> But there is a long period of silence until <abbr>ca.</abbr> 1400 when,
                        according to tradition, Hakkari was populated by Christians from ‘Assyria’,
                        that is, the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mosul">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/139">Mosul</placeName>
                        </ref> plain, fleeing the ravages of Timur. The earliest report of
                        a <abbr>patr.</abbr> of the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> in Hakkari (in the village of Khananis near
                        Kochanes) dates from 1617–19, although the official tradition of the church
                        credits the removal of the patriarchal see to Hakkari to a <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Denḥa
                        (numbered as Mar Shemʿon XIII or XV) who held office 1662–1700.</p>
                    <p>The majority population of Hakkari was always Kurdish, and until the mid-19th
                        century, Assyrian Christians were subject to the local Kurdish chiefs with
                        their fortresses at Julamerk and Bashkale. Well-documented massacres of
                        Christians in 1843–46 were partly the consequence of intra-Kurdish wars,
                        another consequence of which was the gradual imposition of Turkish rule on
                        the region. Officially, Hakkari was a <hi rend="italic">sanjak</hi> within
                        the <hi rend="italic">vilayet</hi> of Van (except 1880–88 when it was itself
                        a <hi rend="italic">vilayet</hi>) with the seat of the local governor (<hi rend="italic">mutessarif</hi>) at Bashkale. Even so, only the so-called
                            <hi rend="italic">rayat</hi> areas on the periphery of Hakkari were
                        subject to direct Turkish rule. In central Hakkari were the ‘<hi rend="italic">ashiret</hi>’ areas in which the central government
                        operated only through the <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Mar Shemʿon, from whom taxes were collected
                        and to whom a salary was paid (both irregularly). A reasonable estimate in
                        1886 put the population of Hakkari at 70,000 Kurds and 50,000 Assyrian
                        Christians (although higher numbers of Christians were often quoted).</p>
                    <p>The principal Assyrian <hi rend="italic">rayat</hi> areas were: Gawar,
                        Shamsdin (including the village of Marbishu), Berwar, and Bashkale. The <hi rend="italic">ashiret</hi> districts were: Upper Tiari, Lower Tiari
                        (including the <choice>
                            <sic>vilage</sic>
                            <corr>village</corr>
                        </choice> of Ashitha), Tkhuma, Baz, and Jilu. Each of the <hi rend="italic">ashiret</hi> populations, usually called tribes, was
                        autonomous under its <hi rend="italic">malek</hi> (chief). The <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr>’s
                        village of Kochanes and a few other groups of villages (Walto, Tal, Diz)
                        were also part of the <hi rend="italic">ashiret</hi> area, although not
                        always considered ‘tribal’. The <hi rend="italic">malek</hi>s owed a feudal
                        allegiance to the <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> but were often disaffected. Differences among the
                        dress, dialect, and even physiognomy of the tribes were generally commented
                        on by Western writers. Even today and even in the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diaspora">diaspora</ref> tribal identities are strong among Assyrians. The
                        membership of the Ancient Church of the East, for example, has a large
                        proportion of Lower Tiari families.</p>
                    <p>The want of good government in Hakkari is a theme in 19th-cent. reports on
                        the area. Christians and Kurds managed a tense coexistence, but it was
                        characterized by continual feuds, disputes over sheep-stealing, and robbery
                        of each other and of travellers. Christian grievances were directed more
                        often at the Turkish government than the Kurds. The government was, however,
                        by nature hostile to Christians as a disloyal non-Muslim element in the
                        population, and the fact that their grievances were often channeled through
                        western missionaries and consular officials increased this hostility.</p>
                    <p>Ethnic cleansing began in Oct. 1914 with an order for the deportation of
                        Christians from Hakkari. With the outbreak of war, this became during
                        1914–15 an organized destruction of <hi rend="italic">rayat</hi> villages by
                        Turkish troops with the assistance of Kurdish irregulars, in which many
                        Assyrian civilians were killed. Apparently after a decision by the Assyrians
                        in May 1915 to join the war on the Russian and British side, a full-scale
                        campaign against them was launched by Haydar Bey, the <hi rend="italic">vali</hi> of Mosul. Heavy fighting drove the Assyrian remnant to
                        retreat into the high mountains, and then to escape as best they could into
                        Persia. At the end of Sept. 1915 it was reported that 25,000 had reached
                        Salmas (north of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Urmia">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/206">Urmia</placeName>
                        </ref>), including Mar
                        Shimun. The men of Jilu had withdrawn to Persia earlier in the year, and in
                        all an estimated 40,000 Assyrians from Hakkari eventually found their way to
                        Urmia.</p>
                    <p>There were attempts to resettle the area by the Assyrian mountaineers in 1920
                        and 1922–24. The latter ended with the Turkish army driving the settlers
                        back over the Iraqi border. When in July 1925 this border was drawn by the
                        League of Nations and Hakkari finally awarded to Turkey, there was an end to
                        ideas of return to the old homeland.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Riley, ‘Christians and Kurds in Eastern Turkey’, <title rend="italic">Contemporary Review</title> 56 (1889), 452–68.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A. J.  Maclean and W. H. Browne, <title rend="italic">The Catholicos
                                of the East and his people</title> (1892), 11–46.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.-M.  Fiey, ‘Proto-histoire chrétienne du Hakkari turc’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OS</abbr>
                            </title> 9 (1964), 443–72.</bibl>
                        <bibl>C.  Dauphin, ‘The rediscovery of the Nestorian churches of the Hakkari
                            (South Eastern Turkey)’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECR</abbr>
                            </title> 8 (1976),
                            56–67.</bibl>
                        <bibl>N. Chevalier, <title rend="italic">Les montagnards chrétiens du
                                Hakkâri et du Kurdistan septentrional</title> (Publications du
                            Département de Géographie de l’Université de Paris-Sorbonne, 13;
                            1985).</bibl>
                        <bibl>D. Gaunt, <title rend="italic">Massacres, resistance, protectors:
                                Muslim-Christian relations in Eastern Anatolia during World War
                                I</title> (2006), 121–46.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>James F.</forename> 
                  <surname>Coakley</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
