<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Ḥarqlean Version</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Andreas</forename> 
                  <surname>Juckel</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Ḥarqlean Version</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Harqlean-Version</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/258</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">249</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="188-191"/>
                    <note type="type">work</note>
                    <note type="abstract">The last Syriac version of the <abbr>NT</abbr>, prepared by Tumo of
                        Ḥarqel (<abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>) 615/16 in the Enaton near <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/572">Alexandria</placeName>
                        (Egypt).<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The last Syriac version of the <abbr>NT</abbr>, prepared by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tumo-of-Harqel">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/87">Tumo of
                        Ḥarqel</persName>
                        </ref> (<abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>) 615/16 in the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/The-Enaton">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/473">Enaton</placeName>
                        </ref>
                        near Alexandria (Egypt). This version is a recension (<hi rend="italic">turroṣo</hi>) of the <abbr>NT</abbr>, with numerous Greek variant readings
                        (translated into Syriac) quoted in the margins or with asterisks in the main
                        text. The recensional method of the Ḥarqlean Version was inherited from
                        Origen’s Hexaplaric Septuagint recension (the Syriac translation of which is
                        the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syro-Hexapla">Syro-Hexapla</ref>). The Syro-Hexapla therefore can contribute to the
                        proper understanding of the Ḥarqlean version’s features and intention.
                        Historically, both versions are parts of the same translation project the
                        Syr. Miaphysites initiated in the second decade of the 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr> According
                        to the subscriptions of the Ḥarqlean Gospels (Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">CESG</hi>, vol. 4, 369), Acts, and the Pauline epistles, the
                        translation was executed ‘at the Enaton of (i.e., near) Alexandria, the
                        great city, in the holy Convent of the Antonines … in the year 927 of
                        Alexander, in the fourth indiction (i. e., 615/16)’. The Ḥarqlean Version is
                        mentioned by <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/239">Bar ʿEbroyo</persName>
                        </ref> in his ‘Storehouse of
                        Secrets’ (<hi rend="italic">Awṣar roze</hi>), proem, in his Ecclesiastical
                        History (I,50 = vol. 1, col. 267), and by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Michael-I-Rabo">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/217">Michael
                            Rabo</persName>
                        </ref>, Chronicle, X,25 = vol. IV 391.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Characteristic Features</label>
                    <p>The characteristic features of the Ḥarqlean version are the decisive turn
                        towards the Greek (‘mirror translation’) and the introduction of the
                        philological and thus ‘critical’ dimension into the history of the Syriac
                        <abbr>NT</abbr>. The method of recension sketched in the subscriptions remains ambiguous
                        (esp. the role of the Philoxenian); the result, however, is clear: Tumo
                        prepared a <abbr>NT</abbr> text that did not exist before; <choice>
                            <sic>i.e. </sic>
                            <corr>i.e., </corr>
                        </choice>he produced a recension
                        of the <abbr>NT</abbr>. This recension was based on a translation of an existing Greek
                        model and supplemented by textual material drawn from additional Greek <abbr>mss.</abbr>
                        In the same way, the Syro-Hexapla is based on an existing Greek model (the
                        Hexaplaric Septuagint recension) and supplemented by textual material drawn
                        from Aquila, Symmachus, and Theodotion (and others). The new philological
                        and ‘critical’ dimension is provided by the <hi rend="italic">distinctive</hi> presentation of the additional material. It is located
                        in the margins or in the main text (marked with asterisks) in order not to
                        mix the textual traditions put together in this recension. This <hi rend="italic">distinctive</hi> presentation allows the additional
                        material to be read in context as variants of the <hi rend="italic">Graeca
                            veritas</hi>. Additions to and omissions from Tumo’s Greek model could
                        be presented in the main text; exchanges of words or passages had to be
                        presented in the margin and connected to the corresponding word in the text
                        by a graphic sign. The <hi rend="italic">obelos</hi> is used for the sake of
                        translation technique to mark Syriac words which do not match the Greek <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> but are necessary for an intelligible
                        rendering of the Greek. By this way of quoting the additional material and
                        using ‘critical’ signs, Tumo is a pupil of Origen; from a modern point of
                        view, he attached a ‘critical’ apparatus to his version. Of course Tumo was
                        not a modern critic, but he was aware of the non-uniformity of the Greek
                        text. He knew about different textual traditions and that translating a
                        single Greek <abbr>ms.</abbr> (like <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Polykarpos">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/35">Polykarpos</persName>
                        </ref>, who
                        prepared the Philoxenian) would provide only an imperfect knowledge of the
                        Greek <abbr>NT</abbr> text.</p>
                    <p>Besides the recensional features, a revisional relation between the Ḥarqlean
                        Version and the Philoxenian is reported in the subscriptions of the Ḥarqlean
                        Version. Although this report is not detailed enough, Tumo could have used
                        the earlier version as the starting point of his own. An attractive feature
                        of the earlier version was its relation to Caesarea in Palestine and to the
                        famous library of Pamphilus, which is reported in the Ḥarqlean subscription
                        to the Pauline letters. A revisional relation to the Philoxenian would have
                        brought Tumo’s own version in line with the Caesarean origin of the
                        Syro-Hexapla and would have supplied the whole Miaphysite translation
                        project with one uniform authority.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Historical Setting</label>
                    <p>As J. Gwynn suggested (‘Paulus [48] Tellensis’, <hi rend="italic">
                            <abbr>DCB</abbr>
                        </hi> 4
                        [1887], 266–71, at 267), the instigative historical setting of the laborious
                        translation project could have been the reunion of the Syrian and Coptic
                        Miaphysites after decades of schisma dating from the time of the Syrian
                        <abbr>Patr.</abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Peter-of-Kallinikos">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/75"> Peter of
                            Kallinikos</persName>
                        </ref> (581–91) and the Coptic Patriarch Damian (578–606).
                        Although no proof can be given, Gwynn’s suggestion is supported by the
                        common date 616 for the reunion and the completion of the Ḥarqlean Version.
                        This suggestion, however, puts a special linguistic perspective on the
                        Ḥarqlean Version. The reunion had to be performed completely in Greek; and
                        both parties had to determine the authoritative Greek text of the Scriptures
                        for reunion. This text had to be of ‘ecumenical’, not of local currency. For
                        the <abbr>OT</abbr>, Origen’s Hexaplaric Septuagint recension (handed down by Pamphilus
                        and <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Eusebius-of-Caesarea">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/480">Eusebius</persName>
                        </ref>) could easily be accepted by both
                        parties; for the <abbr>NT</abbr>, no such work of Origen existed, and the text had to be
                        determined by the Miaphysites themselves. This text became the Greek model
                        of the Ḥarqlean Version. According to this perspective, the Ḥarqlean Version
                        came into being after the determination of the Greek model as the
                        translation and inner-Syriac promulgation of the approved Greek <abbr>NT</abbr> text. The
                        recensional as well as the revisional imprint on the Ḥarqlean version were
                        added during or after translation, when comparison with additional Greek
                        <abbr>mss.</abbr> (and with the Philoxenian) was made. Another possibility is that the
                        Ḥarqlean margin was already an integral part of the Greek text established
                        by the Syrian and Coptic Miaphysites in order to quote (<choice>
                            <sic>i.e. </sic>
                            <corr>i.e., </corr>
                        </choice>to include into
                        the reunion) different textual traditions of both parties.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The History of the Version Reflected by the
                        <abbr>Mss.</abbr>
                    </label>
                    <p>After the rise of Islam, the version’s ‘ecumenical’ frame of reference was
                        lost and the version itself was considered as the ‘Greek’ (Bar ʿEbroyo in
                        his Scholia to the <abbr>NT</abbr>). The ‘ecumenical’ perspective of the Ḥarqlean Version
                        was replaced by a scientific and philological attitude. Due to the
                        complicated lay-out of the version, not all scribes were capable of
                        transmitting the text properly; some of them omitted the marginal quotations
                        and the <hi rend="italic">asterisks/obeloi</hi> completely, thus mixing the
                        readings Tumo intended to keep separate. The philologists were not
                        interested in preserving the original text but in updating it according to
                        the current Greek text of the New Testament, which was the increasingly
                        dominant Byzantine text. This development created ‘corrected’ models
                        (hyparchetypes) and faded out the original non- and pre- Byzantine part of
                        the version.</p>
                    <p>Due to the large number of <abbr>mss.</abbr>, the revisional development can be traced
                        best in the Gospel <abbr>mss.</abbr> The total is <abbr>ca.</abbr> 100 from the 8th to the 19th <abbr>cent.</abbr>,
                        but only <abbr>ca.</abbr> 20 <abbr>mss.</abbr> are furnished with the marginal and asterisked
                        additions. <abbr>Ms.</abbr> Vat. Syr. 268 (8th/9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>) is singled out by an
                        undeveloped stage of text, which preserved a large number of non-Byzantine
                        readings. The majority of the witnesses reflect the version’s development
                        towards the Greek Byzantine text; unfortunately, the oldest dated <abbr>ms.</abbr> of the
                        Gospels (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Florence, Bibl. Laurenziana Plut. I.40; 757) is of this type.
                        This first revisional stage of the version is well represented in further
                        <abbr>mss.</abbr> of the first millennium, <choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>by Vat. Syr. 267 (8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), Harvard
                        Syr.  16 (8th/9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), Brit. Libr. Add. 7163 (9th/10th  cent.), Mingana
                        Syr. 124 (9th/10th <abbr>cent.</abbr>), and Chester Beatty Syr. 3 (1177, copied from a
                        model of 841).</p>
                    <p>In the 12th <abbr>cent.</abbr> the revisional development entered a new stage with the
                        activity of <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysios-bar-Salibi">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/212">Dionysios
                            bar Ṣalibi</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 1171). Again, Gospel <abbr>mss.</abbr> provide the information.
                        The subscriptions, which report his revision (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Oxford, New Coll. 334;
                        12th/13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> and London, Brit. Libr. Add. 17,124; 1233/34; see Wright,
                            <hi rend="italic">Catalogue … British Museum</hi>, vol. 1, 42) do not
                        mention Greek <abbr>mss.</abbr>; it probably relies on several ‘corrected’ models of the
                        version itself. Essential features are the further reduction of the marginal
                        readings and critical signs (though some completely new are added), the
                        inversion of many text/margin readings, and the introduction of the Pericope
                        on the Adulteress (Jn 7:53–8:11).</p>
                    <p>The extreme rarity of <abbr>mss.</abbr> for Acts and the Epistles prevents us from tracing
                        a revisional development in these parts of the <abbr>NT</abbr>. There are only two <abbr>mss.</abbr>
                        from the first millennium, <abbr>ms.</abbr> Jerusalem, St. Mark 37 (Pauline epistles) and
                        <abbr>ms.</abbr> London, Brit. Libr. Add. 14,474 (Catholic Epistles), which are of the
                        9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> Two later <abbr>mss.</abbr> cover the entire <abbr>NT</abbr> with the exception of
                        Revelation: <abbr>ms.</abbr> Cambridge, Add. 1700 (1069/70) and <abbr>ms.</abbr> Oxford, New Coll. 333
                        (12th/13th <abbr>cent.</abbr>). Fortunately, all except the Cambridge <abbr>ms.</abbr> are furnished
                        with marginal and asterisked variants. Revelation is represented by <abbr>ca.</abbr> ten
                        late <abbr>mss.</abbr>, among which Mardin Orth. 36/2 (13th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> by A. Vööbus as
                        no. 35/2) is furnished with a subscription and with the full range of
                        marginal and asterisked variants. Important steps in the version’s history
                        are: 1.  the creation of a ‘Passiontide Harmony’ composed of literal
                        segments of the single Gospels. It is from the 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> and attributed to
                        Daniel of Beth Baṭin (near <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Harran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/216">Ḥarran</placeName>
                        </ref>); 2. the <hi rend="italic">liturgical</hi> use of the version, which entered the
                        lectionaries. This gives color to the version’s appreciation among the
                        Syrians as the ‘correct’ and ‘ecumenical’ text of the <abbr>NT</abbr>; 3. the adoption of
                        the version by the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Masora">Masora</ref> (connected
                        with the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Qarqaphto-Monastery-of">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/229">Qarqaphto</placeName>
                        </ref> monastery near <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Reshayna">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/172">Reshʿayna</placeName>
                        </ref>) in the
                        8th/9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>; 4. the production of <hi rend="italic">bilingual</hi> codices
                        in Syriac/Arabic <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Garshuni">Garshuni</ref> (<choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g.,</corr>
                        </choice>
                        Vat. Syr. 271 and Paris, Bibl. Nat. Syr. 57); and 5. the attachment of
                        extensive exegetical scholia taken from patristic authorities (<choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>Mingana
                        Syr. 105 and 480; Manchester, J. Rylands Univ. Library, no. 10).</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The History of Research</label>
                    <p>The history of research started with the <hi rend="italic">Editio
                            princeps</hi> published by Joseph White 1778–1803; it was based mainly
                        on one single <abbr>ms.</abbr> (New Coll. 333, with variants of <abbr>mss.</abbr> New Coll. 334 and
                        Bodl. Or. 361). From the very beginning scholars were confronted with the
                        question of the version’s identity (Philoxenian or Ḥarqlean). According to
                        White’s interpretation of the subscriptions it was the Philoxenian version
                        he published, which <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tumo-of-Harqel">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/87">Tumo of
                            Ḥarqel</persName>
                        </ref> reissued by only attaching the marginal and asterisked
                        readings. G. H. Bernstein in 1837 considered White’s text to be a separate
                        version, though a thorough revision, of the Philoxenian. The question
                        remained open until the publication of Philoxenos’s late writings, which
                        provided genuine Philoxenian quotations of the <abbr>NT</abbr> (especially his commentary
                        on the prologue of St. John’s Gospel, <abbr>ed.</abbr> by A. de Halleux [<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 380,
                        1977]). Bernstein’s view turned out to be substantially correct; the <choice>
                            <sic>
                                <hi rend="bold">Philoxenian version</hi>
                            </sic>
                            <corr>
                            Philoxenian version
                        </corr>
                        </choice> itself is considered lost.</p>
                    <p>A new approach to the Greek background of the Ḥarqlean Version was launched
                        by B. Aland, who successfully reconstructed the Greek <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> of the Ḥarqlean major Catholic Epistles and the writings
                        of Paul. The version’s Greek model can be traced to a group of
                        10th–15th-cent. minuscule <abbr>mss.</abbr> (1611, 1505, 2138, 2495 according to Gregory
                        and Aland), the ancestry of which is not a descendent of the Greek model
                        itself but of a <abbr>ms.</abbr> akin to this model having a common 5th/6th-cent.
                        ancestry (B. Aland 1986, introduction). The knowledge of the Greek model
                        opened a new perspective on Tumo’s method of revison, with two principal
                        issues: 1. Tumo is a <hi rend="italic">translator</hi>, who faithfully
                        follows his Greek <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi>; the marginal and
                        asterisked annotations derive from different Greek <abbr>mss.</abbr>, which supply the
                        version with variant readings of the <hi rend="italic">Graeca veritas</hi>;
                        2. the revisional relation to the Philoxenian (reported in the
                        subscriptions) is rather on the Syriac than on the Greek level. There was a
                        shift from a fairly exact rendering to a ‘mirror translation’; the Greek
                        background of both versions largely remained the same. These results derive
                        from a text-critical study and from a reedition of the Ḥarqlean Version,
                        which is based on a new important <abbr>ms.</abbr> (Jerusalem, St. Mark 37; 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>).
                        G. Zuntz’s still dominant approach to the revisional relation between the
                        Philoxenian and Ḥarqlean versions is solely based on an interpretation of
                        the subscriptions and guided too much by the term ‘revision’ instead of
                        ‘translation’.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Editions</label>
                    <p>The complex structure of the Ḥarqlean Version, its liability to distortion,
                        the revisional development, and the scanty attestation of the Praxapostolos
                        confront editors with not a few problems. Not surprisingly, most of the
                        Ḥarqlean editions are one-<abbr>ms.</abbr>-publications. A comprehensive critical edition
                        of the Gospels, which sets out the revisional development of the version in
                        some detail, is much to be desired. Ḥarqlean texts published so far are: L.
                        de Dieu, <hi rend="italic">Apocalypsis Sancti Iohannis</hi> (Leiden, 1627)
                        (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Hebr. Scal. 18); J. White, <hi rend="italic">Sacrorum Evangeliorum
                            Versio Philoxeniana ...</hi>, vol. 1, 1–2 (Oxford, 1778) (Gospels); vol.
                        2, 1–2 (Oxford, 1799/1803) (Acts and Letters) (<abbr>ms.</abbr> New Coll. 333, with
                        variants of <abbr>mss.</abbr> New Coll. 334 and Bodl. Or. 361 [all Oxford]);
                        G. H.  Bernstein, <hi rend="italic">Das heilige Evangelium des Iohannes.
                            Syrisch in harklensischer Übersetzung  … </hi>(Leipzig, 1853) (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Vat.
                        Syr. 271); R. L. Bensly, <hi rend="italic">The Harklean version of the
                            Epistle to the Hebrews, chapter XI,28–XIII,25</hi> (Cambridge, 1889)
                        (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Cambridge, Add. 1700); M. A. Weigelt, <hi rend="italic">Diatessaric
                            Harmonies on the Passion Narrative in the Harclean Syriac Version</hi>
                        (Ph.D. Diss.; 1969) (based on <abbr>mss.</abbr> Vat. Syr. 268; London, Brit. Libr. Add.
                        18,714; Paris, Bibl. Nat. Syr. 31, 51 and 52; Cambridge, Add. 1700); A.
                        Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">The Apocalypse in the Harklean version</hi> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr>
                        400; 1978) (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Mardin Orth. 35/2 [<choice>
                            <sic>i.e. </sic>
                            <corr>i.e., </corr>
                        </choice>36/2]); B. Aland and A. Juckel, <hi rend="italic">Das Neue Testament in syrischer Überlieferung</hi> I
                        (1986) (James, 1 Peter, 1 John; according to <abbr>mss.</abbr> London, Brit. Libr. Add.
                        14,474; Oxford, New Coll. 333; Cambridge, Add. 1700); B. Aland and A.
                        Juckel, <hi rend="italic">Das Neue Testament in syrischer Überlieferung</hi>
                        II,1–3 (1991, 1995, 2002) (the corpus of Pauline epistles; according to <abbr>mss.</abbr>
                        Jerusalem, St. Mark Syr. 37; Oxford, New Coll. 333; Cambridge, Add. 1700);
                        G. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Edition of the Syriac Gospels</hi> (4
                        vols.; 1996) (<abbr>ms.</abbr> Vat. Syr. 268, supplemented by <abbr>ms.</abbr> Vat. Syr. 267 and
                        Florence, Bibl. Laurenziana Plut. I,40); P. A. L. Hill, <hi rend="italic">The Harklean Version of St. Luke 1–11: A Critical Introduction and
                            Edition</hi> (Ph.D. Diss., Melbourne; 2002) (based on 19 <abbr>mss.</abbr>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>I. R.  Beacham, <title rend="italic">The Harklean Syriac Version
                                of Revelation: Manuscripts, Text and Methodology of Translation from
                                Greek</title> (Ph.D. Diss., Birmingham; 1990).</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. P.  Brock, ‘The resolution of the Philoxenian/Harclean problem’, in
                                <title rend="italic">New Testament textual criticism. Its
                                significance for exegesis. Essays in honour of Bruce M.
                                Metzger</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> E. J. Epp and G. D. Fee (1981), 325–43.</bibl>
                        <bibl>W. H. P.  Hatch, ‘The subscription in the Chester Beatty manuscript of
                            the Harclean Gospels’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>HTR</abbr>
                            </title> 30 (1937),
                            141–155.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Juckel, ‘Die Bedeutung des Ms Vat. syr. 268 für die
                            Evangelienüberlieferung der Harklensis’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OC</abbr>
                            </title>
                            83 (1999), 22–45.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Juckel, ‘Towards an Analytical Concordance of the Harklean <abbr>NT</abbr>’, in
                                <title rend="italic">Foundations for Syriac Lexicography</title>,
                            vol. 2, <abbr>ed.</abbr> P. J.  Williams (2009), 99−154.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kiraz, <title rend="italic">CESG</title>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>B. M.  Metzger, <title rend="italic">The early versions of the New
                                Testament</title> (1977), 63–75, 83–98.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. D.  Thomas, ‘A List of Manuscripts Containing the Harclean Syriac
                            Version of the <abbr>NT</abbr>’, <title rend="italic">Theological Review (of the Near
                                East School of Theology)</title> 2 (1979), 26–32.</bibl>
                        <bibl>G.  Zuntz, <title rend="italic">The Ancestry of the Harklean New
                                Testament</title> (1945).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Andreas</forename> 
                  <surname>Juckel</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
