<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Islam, Syriac interactions with</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Sidney H.</forename> 
                  <surname>Griffith</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Islam, Syriac interactions with</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Islam-Syriac-contacts-with</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/302</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">293</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="219-224"/>
                    <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Syriac contacts with Islam</idno>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>Syriac-speaking Christians, along with Arabic-speaking Christians whose
                        patristic and liturgical heritage was largely Syriac, were among those
                        Christians most immediately present to Islam in its origins. Throughout
                        early Islamic history, especially in the period stretching from the earliest
                        Islamic conquests in the territories of the Oriental Patriarchates in the
                        first half of the 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, up to the Mongol destruction of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Baghdad">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/41">Baghdad</placeName>
                        </ref>
                        in 1258 and beyond, interactions between Syriac Christians and Muslims were
                        a regular feature of political, intellectual, and cultural life in the
                        caliphate. Thereafter, and up to the present day, Syriac-speaking
                        communities have continued to be a significant, cultural presence in the
                        Islamic milieu, especially in the modern states of Turkey, Syria, Lebanon,
                        Palestine, Iraq, and Iran, where so-called ‘Neo-Aramaic’ dialects (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aramaic">Aramaic</ref>; <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sureth">Sureth</ref>; <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Turoyo">Ṭuroyo</ref>),
                        with their roots in classical Syriac, are still spoken and the classical
                        literature is still prized.</p>
                    <p>By the middle of the 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, when Islamic rule was firmly established in
                        the Levant, the main Christian, confessional communities among the
                        Syriac-speaking peoples were already firmly established. In due course,
                        Syriac- and Arabic-speaking Christians and Muslims alike came to refer to
                        them as ‘Nestorians’, ‘Jacobites’, and ‘Melkites’, adopting the polemically
                        inspired denominational labels devised by each community’s theological and
                        Christological adversaries. Already in the 6th and early 7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, these
                        communities were well established in the peripheral regions of Arabia
                        (Hainthaler), with well-known congregations along the Persian Gulf, in
                        Ḥaḍramawt and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nagran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/464">Nagran</placeName>
                        </ref> in south Arabia (Trimingham; Tardy), among the Lakhmids
                        and Ghassanids on the north eastern and western fringes of the desert
                        (Shahid), and the tribal groups Christianized by the monks of Palestine and
                        the Sinai. From these peripheral locations among others, largely under
                        Syriac and Aramaic influence, knowledge of Christian doctrine and practice,
                        along with a considerable body of ecclesiastical lore, spread among the
                        tribally organized, Arabic-speaking peoples of central Arabia and the Ḥijāz.
                        By the time of the prophet Muḥammad (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 570–632), there was a significant
                        level of awareness of Christianity in its Aramaic and Syriac expression, in
                        the environs of Mecca and Yathrib/Medina, of its scriptures, traditions, and
                        confessional formulae. The principal evidence for this relatively high
                        quotient of awareness of Aramaic and Syriac Christianity in the
                        Arabic-speaking milieu of <choice>
                            <sic>7th </sic>
                            <corr>7th-</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> Arabia is the Arabic Qurʾān itself.
                        Scholars alternatively trace this awareness to the influence of a local
                        ‘Jewish Christianity’ (De Blois; Gnilka), or to the actual presence of
                        mainly ‘Jacobite’ and ‘Nestorian’ Christians in the Qurʾān’s audience, based
                        on the text’s reflection of common eschatological and scriptural themes and
                        its critiques of Christian doctrines and practices in their Syriac
                        expression, as a growing body of scholarship in recent times is increasingly
                        arguing (Andrae; Reynolds; Van der Velden; Griffith 2008).</p>
                    <p>Syriac interaction with Islam thus had its beginnings in the very origins of
                        Islam, manifesting itself principally in the Islamic scripture; according to
                        one estimate, Syriac loan words in the Arabic Qurʾān account for about
                        seventy percent of the foreign vocabulary in the text (Mingana). This state
                        of affairs, along with other considerations, has prompted some recent
                        scholars to propose a hitherto unsuspected level of influence of the Syriac
                        language even on the grammar and lexicography of Qurʾānic Arabic
                        (Luxenberg). Other scholars had already made use of other comparative data
                        (Wansbrough) to propose a later, early 8th-cent., Syrian origin for
                        Muḥammad, Islam, and the Qurʾān; some have gone so far as to postulate the
                        development of Islam at this late date from a supposed heretical,
                        pre-Nicene, Syriac Christianity, hitherto unrecognized by earlier Syriac
                        scholars (Ohlig). While these latter hypotheses have gained little or no
                        scholarly support for their specific conclusions, they nevertheless
                        highlight the continuing importance of Syriac and Syriac studies for the
                        scholarly investigation of Islamic origins in Late Antiquity.</p>
                    <p>Syriac writers were among the earliest, non-Muslim witnesses to the Islamic
                        conquest and to the appearance of Islam as a new religious tradition. The
                        so-far earliest known Christian reference to Muḥammad by name occurs in a
                        Syriac chronicle composed around the year 640; the text mentions ‘a battle
                        between the Romans and the Arabs of Muḥammad in Palestine twelve miles east
                        of Gaza’ in the year 634 (Hoyland, 120). The chroniclers continued to record
                        the interactions between Muslims and Christians well up into the Middle
                        Ages, including records of battles, raids, massacres, martyrdoms,
                        impositions of taxes, and other matters, including even accounts of the
                        reigns of the caliphs and other aspects of Islamic history. These accounts
                        have proven invaluable to historians of the early Islamic period, as
                        independent records of events that are only sparsely reported or not
                        reported at all in Islamic, Arabic sources of the time (Borrut). The great
                        medieval, Syriac chronicles, such as the Chronicle of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Michael-I-Rabo">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/217">Michael Rabo</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 1199) and the anonymous <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Chronicle-of-1234">Chronicle of
                            1234</ref>, incorporating the narratives of earlier chroniclers (<choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g.,</corr>
                        </choice>
                            <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysios-of-Tel-Mahre">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/155">Dionysios
                            of Tel Maḥre</persName>
                        </ref>), include biographies of Muḥammad and accounts of
                        Islamic religious thought, along with reports of the encounters between
                        Muslims and Christians. These encounters were often unfriendly and sometimes
                        resulted in mass conversions to Islam. For example, a chronicler from the
                        late 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr> says of the Syriac-speaking Christians in his era, in the
                        region of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tur-Abdin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/221">Ṭur ʿAbdin</placeName>
                        </ref>, that ‘the gates were opened to them to [enter] Islam<choice>
                            <sic>. . . . </sic>
                            <corr>….</corr>
                        </choice>Without blows or tortures they slipped towards apostasy in great
                        precipitancy; they formed groups of ten or twenty or thirty or a hundred or
                        two hundred or three hundred without any sort of compulsion<choice>
                            <sic>. . . .</sic>
                            <corr>…</corr>
                        </choice>, going
                        down to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Harran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/216">Ḥarran</placeName>
                        </ref> and becoming Muslims. A great crowd did so, from the
                        districts of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref> and of Ḥarran and of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Reshayna">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/172">Reshʿayna</placeName>
                        </ref>’
                        (Harrak, 324).</p>
                    <p>The earliest religious responses in Syriac to the challenge of Islam seem to
                        have been in the apocalyptic genre. The most notable of these is the ‘<ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Methodius-Apocalypse-of-Pseudo-">Apocalypse of Pseudo-Methodius</ref>’, in all likelihood
                        composed originally in Syriac by a <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> writer in <abbr>ca.</abbr> 691 (Reinink
                        1993). The author explains how the interlude of Arab domination in time to
                        come, all immediate evidence to the contrary notwithstanding, will not
                        really disrupt the unfolding sequence of the four kingdoms of the prophecies
                        in the book of Daniel, destined to end with the kingdom of the Greeks.
                        Rather, he says, the depredations of the Arabs are part of God’s plan for
                        the era of punishment for sin that is destined to usher in the final days of
                        world history (Reinink 1992). The Apocalypse was soon translated into Greek
                        and from that language was many times translated into other languages of the
                        Christian west (Alexander). A number of other apocalyptic texts in Syriac
                        from the same era elaborated on the same theme (Drijvers; Suermann). The
                        most important of them was the Syriac <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sargis-Bhira">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/718">Sargis Bḥira</persName>
                        </ref>
                        legend, soon revised into Arabic, which incorporated many of these
                        apocalyptic themes into the story of Muḥammad’s encounter, following Islamic
                        sources, with a Christian monk who recognized the sign of prophecy on the
                        youthful prophet’s body. The 9th-cent. Syriac author told of the monk’s
                        interactions with Muḥammad, including their dialogue about the major topics
                        of Christian/Muslim controversy (Roggema). This ingenious narrative, which
                        was destined to exert an enormous influence within the Syriac- and
                        Arabic-speaking Christian communities of the Near East for centuries to
                        come, incorporated an already popular genre in Christian/Muslim relations in
                        Syriac, a literary dialogue between a Christian, often a monk, and a Muslim
                        notable, in this instance Muḥammad himself.</p>
                    <p>The earliest of the Syriac, apologetic dialogue texts, like the apocalyptic
                        narratives, also come from the early 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr> The earliest of them is a
                        letter, written in the early 700s and preserved in a manuscript copied in
                        874, in which a now unknown writer tells of the occasion when the <abbr>Syr. Orth. </abbr>
                        <abbr>Patr. </abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yuhanon-of-the-Sedre">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/92">Yuḥanon of
                            the Sedre</persName>
                        </ref> (<abbr>r.</abbr> 631–648) was interrogated by a Muslim emir, ʿUmayr
                        <abbr>b.</abbr> Saʿd al-Anṣārī, on Sunday, 9 May 644 (Nau, Penn) — even though this date
                        has been questioned in recent research. They discuss the major doctrinal and
                        practical issues between Christians and Muslims in such a way that the
                        Christian dialogue partner successfully defends his faith, thereby offering
                        the Christian Syriac reader of the text the confidence that Christians do
                        have answers to the Islamic religious challenge and ways to show the truth
                        of Christianity on the one hand and Islam’s shortfall on the other hand. Of
                        the numerous compositions in this genre written in Syriac over the
                        centuries, one might mention the most well known among them, works such as
                        the account of the monk of Beth Ḥale with a Muslim emir (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 720) (Hoyland;
                        Griffith 2000), the dialogue between a master and his disciple in Chapter 10
                        of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoros-bar-Koni">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/783">Theodoros bar
                            Koni</persName>
                        </ref>’s (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 792) ‘Scholion’ (Griffith 1981), <abbr>Patr. </abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Timotheos-I">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/790">Timotheos
                            I</persName>
                        </ref>’s (d. 823) account of his dialogue with the caliph, al-Mahdī,
                        and Muslim scholars in the caliph’s <hi rend="italic">majlis</hi> (Mingana;
                        Putman; Heimgartner), <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nonos-of-Nisibis">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/156">Nonos of
                            Nisibis</persName>
                        </ref>’s (d. after 861) apologetic treatise in Syriac (Van Roey),
                        and <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysios-bar-Salibi">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/212">Dionysios
                            bar Ṣalibi</persName>
                        </ref>’s (d. 1171) long refutation of Islam in thirty
                        chapters, distributed in three general discourses (Amar). Many anonymous
                        texts of this sort are known in the <abbr>ms.</abbr> tradition, and a number of them,
                        like <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Timotheos’s account of his dialogue with the caliph and his
                        attendant scholars, were later translated into Arabic and enjoyed a wide
                        circulation in the Christian communities in the Islamic world. As a matter
                        of fact, many of the Christian Arabic writers of apologetic texts of this
                        sort from the 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> onward were Syriac-speaking Christians who had
                        learned Arabic. The most well-known among the earliest of them were the
                        ‘Melkite’ <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoros-Abu-Qurra">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/782">Theodoros Abū
                            Qurra</persName>
                        </ref> (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 755-ca. 830), the ‘Jacobite’ Ḥabīb <abbr>b.</abbr> Khidma Abū Rāʾiṭa
                        (d. <abbr>ca.</abbr> 851), and the ‘Nestorian’ ʿAmmār al-Baṣrī (<abbr>fl.</abbr>
                        <abbr> ca.</abbr> 850), whose
                        apologetic texts in Arabic had a long and wide circulation among Middle
                        Eastern Christians (Griffith 2008).</p>
                    <p>An interesting feature of these Christian apologetic texts in both Syriac and
                        Arabic is that in them their authors developed an apologetic strategy for
                        commending the reasonable credibility of the controversial Christian
                        doctrines that took advantage of the modes of reasoning deployed by the
                        contemporary Muslim theologians in the early development of an Islamic,
                        systematic theology. In fact, it seems to have been the case that the
                        Arabic-speaking, Muslim theologians developed their characteristic modes of
                        reasoning in religious matters, the <hi rend="italic">ʿilm al-kalām</hi>,
                        very much in the course of their interactions with Syriac-speaking,
                        Christian theologians in such intellectual centers as Baṣra and Baghdad in
                        the late 8th and early 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> (Cook). One catches a glimpse of the
                        process in the Syriac letters of <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Timotheos I, who moved his residence
                        from <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Seleucia-Ctesiphon">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/182">Seleucia-Ctesiphon</placeName>
                        </ref> to Baghdad, where he not only participated in
                        a well-known debate at the caliph’s court, but where he also engaged in
                        conversations with Muslim scholars. He tells about his experiences and
                        recounts his conversations in several of his Syriac letters, addressed to a
                        number of Christian correspondents (Hurst). In these letters he tells not
                        only of his own experiences in conversation with Muslims but in three
                        letters addressed to Christians in the environs of Baṣra he offers advice
                        about how to discuss Christology in a Muslim dominated milieu (Griffith
                        2007). In these letters one acquires a glimpse into the circumstances of the
                        origins not only of Muslim controversial theology, but of a Christian <hi rend="italic">kalām</hi> as well, such as that displayed in the
                        generation after <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Timotheos, in the Arabic works of ʿAmmār al-Baṣrī, in
                        his interactions with the thought of his fellow Baṣrian, the Muʿtazilī,
                        Muslim <hi rend="italic">mutakallim</hi>, Abū Hudhayl al-ʿAllāf (d. <abbr>ca.</abbr>
                        840).</p>
                    <p>In Baghdad from the late 8th to the mid-11th <abbr>cent.</abbr> at least, Syriac-speaking,
                        Christian intellectuals played a determining role in the multi-faceted
                        intellectual undertaking known as the Graeco-Arabic translation movement in
                        early Abbasid times (Gutas). Building on the earlier, intellectually
                        important task of translating logical, philosophical, and other texts from
                        Greek into Syriac in the context of the Christological controversies,
                        especially by scholars in the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> community (Hugonnard-Roche), in the
                        9th and 10th <abbr>cent.</abbr> scholars who were mostly alumni of the several important
                        schools of the <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr>, were engaged by mostly Muslim patrons to translate
                        a whole range of texts from Greek into Arabic, embracing not only logical
                        and philosophical texts from the Platonic and Aristotelian traditions, but
                        medical, mathematical, and other scientific disciplines as well. Important
                        participants in this undertaking were members of the Bokhtishoʿ family, with
                        their connections with Gondeshapur (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Beth-Lapat">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/35">Beth Lapaṭ</placeName>
                        </ref>), the
                        famous <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Hunayn-b-Ishaq">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/542">Ḥunayn <abbr>b.</abbr>
                            Isḥāq</persName>
                        </ref> (808–73), with his family and associates from <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Hirta">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/219">Ḥirta</placeName>
                        </ref>,
                        and Abū Bishr Mattā <abbr>b.</abbr> Yūnus (d. 940) from the monastery of Dayr Qunnā, the
                        community from which many Christian officials at the caliphal court in the
                        9th  cent. came originally (Massignon). It is important to see that these
                        Syr. Christian intellectuals were not only translators for hire, but
                        important scholars in their own right, who participated fully in the
                        scholarly life of Baghdad in their time. Abū Bishr Mattā <abbr>b.</abbr> Yūnus is a case
                        in point; not only was he one of the two Christian teachers of the Muslim
                        philosopher Abū Naṣr al-Fārābī (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 870–950), the other one being Yuḥannā <abbr>b.</abbr>
                        Ḥaylān (d. 910), Abū Bishr was also the champion of ‘Greek logic’ among the
                        Christian and Muslim intellectuals of Baghdad. He defended the cause in a
                        famous, if for him <choice>
                            <sic>ill fated</sic>
                            <corr>ill-fated</corr>
                        </choice>, debate between himself and the champion of the
                        Muslim <hi rend="italic">mutakallimūn</hi>, Abū Saʾīd al-Sīrāfī, who
                        disdained ‘Greek logic’ in favor of the claims of theoretical Arabic grammar
                        as a sufficient measure of the soundness of statements made in Arabic
                        (Endress).</p>
                    <p>The most prominent philosopher in the third quarter of the 10th <abbr>cent.</abbr> in
                        Baghdad was the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Christian <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yahya-b-Adi">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/180">Yaḥyā <abbr>b.</abbr> ʿAdī</persName>
                        </ref>
                        (893–974), the student of al-Fārābī, and in turn the master of a circle of
                        both Muslim and Christian disciples who became the mainstays of the Baghdad
                        Aristotelians well into the 11th <abbr>cent.</abbr> Prominent among them was Yaḥyā’s Syr.
                        Orth. disciple ʿĪsā <abbr>b.</abbr> Zurʿa (943–1008), who was a notable presence in the
                        learned salons of the social elite of Baghdad in his time (Kraemer).</p>
                    <p>An interesting feature of the interaction between Syr. Christian and Muslim
                        scholars in the 10th and 11th  cent. is the response made by Christian
                        writers to positions taken by prominent Muslims in popular books written in
                        Arabic that enjoyed a wide circulation in their time. For example, the
                        Muslim philosopher Yaʿqūb <abbr>b.</abbr> Isḥāq al-Kindī (<abbr>ca.</abbr> 800 – <abbr>ca.</abbr> 867), who had
                        been a patron of Ḥunayn <abbr>b.</abbr> Isḥāq, wrote a widely read essay called ‘The Art
                        of Dispelling Sorrows’ that offered consolation on solely philosophical
                        grounds. At least three Christian writers wrote responses to this text in
                        Arabic (Griffith 1996), prominent among them being the Ch.  of E. prelate
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Eliya-of-Nisibis">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/472">Eliya of Nisibis</persName>
                        </ref> (975–1046), who became famous for his
                        discussions about religion with the Muslim vizier Abū al-Qāsim al-Ḥusayn <abbr>b.</abbr>
                        ʿAlī al-Maghribī (981–1027) (Samir). Similarly, the famous Muslim writer,
                        Abū ʿUthmān ʿAmr <abbr>b.</abbr> Bahr al-Jāḥiẓ (777–868) had argued in his famous <hi rend="italic">Kitāb al-ḥayawān</hi> that lifelong sexual continence is
                        impossible for humans. Both Yaḥyā <abbr>b.</abbr> ‘Adī and Eliya of Nisibis wrote
                        treatises on sexual continence expressly to refute al-Jāḥiẓ’s claims and to
                        commend the practice of sexual abstinence as an important virtue for one
                        seeking moral perfection (Griffith 2006).</p>
                    <p>These and many other instances of the interactions between Syr. Christians
                        and Muslims in the heyday of the Abbasid caliphs show clearly that
                        Christians of the Syriac-speaking communities played a major role in the
                        growth and development of classical Islamic culture in its origins. Their
                        interactions continued into much later times. A major case in point is
                        evident in the life and work of the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> polymath <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/239">Bar
                            ʿEbroyo</persName>
                        </ref> (1225–86). He composed important works in both Syriac and
                        Arabic, and in his time he was well known not only among his
                        co-religionists, but among Muslim intellectuals as well; he mentions the
                        names and takes account of the positions of Muslim writers such as Fakhr
                        al-Dīn al-Rāzī, al-Jāḥiẓ, and al-Ghazzālī in his own works. In Syriac, Bar
                        ʿEbroyo often wrote in the style current among Arabic-speaking writers of
                        his day. As a matter of course, he takes Islamic points of view seriously in
                        his work and in many ways he came the closest of all Syriac writers to
                        something like a real dialogue with Islam; in his work there is a concern
                        for scholarly objectivity, shown in his quotations from Islamic texts, that
                        sets him apart from the earlier writers of dispute texts (Takahashi).</p>
                    <p>An important, but controversial area of interaction between Syriac
                        Christianity and Islam is religious mysticism. Specifically, the question
                        arises about the influence of Christian asceticism and mysticism in its Syr.
                        expression, and especially in its E.-Syr. or <abbr>Ch. of E.</abbr> tradition, on Sufism
                        in its early, especially Persian stages. Scholars have been divided in their
                        opinions, with some pointing to the early development of Sufism in the very
                        territories of the Syriac-speaking Christians and citing numerous parallels
                        (<choice>
                            <sic>e.g.</sic>
                            <corr>e.g., </corr>
                        </choice>Tor Andrae; Blum); others have emphasized the natural origins of
                        Islamic mysticism in the Qurʾān and early Islamic tradition (Massignon).
                        This is very much an area of Syriac interaction with Islam in which
                        detailed, comparative study of texts has yet to be undertaken. Most scholars
                        of Sufism simply ignore the Syr. ambience in which many of the early Sufi
                        writers lived.</p>
                    <p>Not long after the ‘Syriac <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Renaissance-Syriac">Renaissance</ref>’ of the 12th and 13th centuries, when local languages
                        gradually came to dominate both the intellectual and even the ecclesiastical
                        and liturgical life of Syriac Christianity, at the expense of classical
                        Syriac, interactions between Islam and Syriac Christianity nevertheless
                        continued to be an important feature of life for the Christians living in
                        Islamic polities. Syriac-speaking communities readily became fluent in the
                        newly dominant languages of their homelands, be they Arabic, Turkish,
                        Kurdish, or Persian, and in these and other languages, such as those of
                        Central Asia, their interactions with Muslims have been continuous and their
                        participation in public life in the Islamic milieu, especially in the
                        Arabic-speaking world, has been significant especially in the cultural and
                        political spheres. A notable instance of this interaction in modern times
                        was the prominent place of Christian intellectuals in the promotion of Arab
                        nationalism in the early to middle 20th cent (Hourani).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Primary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>J. P.  Amar, <title rend="italic">Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī: A response
                                    to the Arabs</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 614–5; 2005).</bibl>
                            <bibl>O.  Braun, <title rend="italic">Timothei Patriarchae I
                                    epistulae</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 74–5; 1914–5).</bibl>
                            <bibl>I.-B.  Chabot, <title rend="italic">Chronique de Denys de
                                    Tell-Mahré, quatrième partie</title> (1895).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>I.-B.  Chabot</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Chronique de Michel le Syrien,
                                    patriarche jacobite d’Antioche (1166–99)</title> (4 vols.;
                                1899–1910).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>I.-B.  Chabot</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Anonymi Auctoris Chronicon ad annum
                                    Christi 1234 pertinens</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 81–2, 109, 354; 1916–20,
                                1937, 1974).</bibl>
                            <bibl>I.-B.  Chabot and R.  Hespel, <title rend="italic">Incerti
                                    auctoris chronicon anonymum pseudo-Dionysianum vulgo dictum
                                    II</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 104, 507; 1933, 1989).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Harrak, <title rend="italic">The chronicle of Zuqnīn: Parts
                                    III and IV; A.D. 488–775</title> (1999).</bibl>
                            <bibl>R.  Hespel, <title rend="italic">Théodore bar Koni. Livre des
                                    scolies (recension d’Urmiah)</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 447–448;
                                1983).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Mingana, ‘The apology of Timothy the Patriarch before the
                                Caliph Mahdi’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>BJRL</abbr>
                                </title> 12 (1928), 137–298.
                                (new <abbr>ed.</abbr> in preparation by M. Heimgartner).</bibl>
                            <bibl>F.  Nau, ‘Un colloque du patriarche Jean avec l’émir des Agaréens
                                et faits divers des années 712 à 716’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JA</abbr>
                                </title> 11.5 (1915), 225–79.</bibl>
                            <bibl>M. Penn, ‘John and the Emir. A new introduction, edition, and
                                translation’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>LM</abbr>
                                </title> 121 (2008),
                                65–91.</bibl>
                            <bibl>H.  Putman, <title rend="italic">L’Eglise et l’Islam sous Timothée
                                    I (780–823)</title> (1975).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. J.  Reinink, <title rend="italic">Die syrische Apokalypse des
                                    Pseudo-Methodius</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 540–1; 1993).</bibl>
                            <bibl>B.  Roggema, <title rend="italic">The legend of Sergius Baḥīrā:
                                    Eastern <choice>
                                        <sic>christian</sic>
                                        <corr>Christian</corr>
                                    </choice> apologetics and apocalyptic in response to
                                    Islam</title> (2009).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Scher, <title rend="italic">Theodorus Bar Kōnī. Liber
                                    scholiorum</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 69; 1912).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Van Roey, <title rend="italic">Nonnus de Nisibe. Traité
                                    apologétique</title> (1948).</bibl>
                            <bibl>W.  Witakowski, <title rend="italic">Pseudo-Dionysius of
                                    Tel-Mahre: Chronicle (known also as the Chronicle of Zuqnin):
                                    Part III</title> (1996).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>P. J.  Alexander, <title rend="italic">The Byzantine Apocalyptic
                                    Tradition</title> (1985).</bibl>
                            <bibl>T.  Andrae (trans. J. Roche), <title rend="italic">Les origines de
                                    l’islam et le christianisme</title> (1955).</bibl>
                            <bibl>T.  Andrae, <title rend="italic">In the garden of the myrtles:
                                    Studies in Early Islamic Mysticism</title> (1987).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. G.  Blum, <title rend="italic">Die Geschichte der Begegnung
                                    christlich-orientalischer Mystik mit der Mystik des
                                    Islams</title> (2009).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Borrut, ‘Entre tradition et histoire: genèse et diffusion de
                                l’image de ‘Umar II’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>MUSJ</abbr>
                                </title> 58 (2005),
                                329–78.</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Cook, ‘The Origins of Kalam’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>BSOAS</abbr>
                                </title> 43 (1980), 32–43.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>M.  Cook</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Early Muslim dogma</title>
                                (1981).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. Crone and M. Cook, <title rend="italic">Hagarism: The making of
                                    the Islamic world</title> (1977).</bibl>
                            <bibl>F. De Blois, ‘Naṣrānī (<choice>
                                    <sic>Ναζωραιος</sic>
                                    <corr>Ναζωραῖος</corr>
                                </choice>) and ḥanīf (<choice>
                                    <sic>εθνικος</sic>
                                    <corr>ἐθνικός</corr>
                                </choice>): Studies on
                                the religious vocabulary of Christianity and Islam’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>BSOAS</abbr>
                                </title> 65 (2002), 1–30.</bibl>
                            <bibl>H. J. W. Drijvers, ‘The Gospel of the Twelve Apostles: A Syriac
                                Apocalypse from the early Islamic period’, in <title rend="italic">Byzantine and Early Islamic Near East</title>, vol.1<title rend="italic">. Problems in the literary source
                                material</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Cameron and L. Conrad (1992),
                                189–213.</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Endress, ‘Grammatik und Logik: Arabische Philologie und
                                griechische Philosophie im Widerstreit’, in <title rend="italic">Sprachphilosophie in Antike und Mittelalter</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr>
                                B. Mojsisch (1986), 163–299.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. J.  van Ginkel <abbr>et al.</abbr> (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Redefining
                                    Christian identity. Cultural interaction in the Middle East
                                    since the rise of Islam</title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 134; 2005).</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  Gnilka, <title rend="italic">Die Nazarener und der Koran: Eine
                                    Spurensuche</title> (2007).</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. H.  Griffith, ‘Chapter Ten of the Scholion: Theodore Bar Kônî’s
                                apology for Christianity’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OCP</abbr>
                                </title> 47
                                (1981), 158–188.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>  ‘Disputes with Muslims in Syriac Christian texts: From
                                Patriarch John (d. 648) to Bar Hebraeus (d. 1286)’, in <title rend="italic">Religionsgespräche im Mittelalter</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr>
                                B.  Lewis and F.  Niewöhner (1992), 251–73.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘The Muslim philosopher al-Kindī and his Christian readers:
                                Three Arab Christian texts on “The Dissipation of Sorrows”’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>BJRL</abbr>
                                </title> 78 (1996), 111–27.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Disputing with Islam in Syriac. The case of the Monk of Bêt
                                Ḥālê and a Muslim emir’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                                </title> 3
                                (2000).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Yaḥyā ibn ʿAdī’s Colloquy on Sexual Abstinence and the
                                Philosophical Life’, in <title rend="italic">Arabic theology, Arabic
                                    philosophy: From the many to the one</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr>
                                J. E.  Montgomery (2006), 299–333.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘The Syriac letters of Patriarch Timothy I and the birth of
                                Christian kalām in the Mu‛tazilite milieu of Baghdad and Baṣrah in
                                Early Islamic times’, in <title rend="italic">Syriac polemics.
                                    Studies in honour of G. J. Reinink</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> W. J. van Bekkum
                                <abbr>et al.</abbr> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 170; 2007), 103–32.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">The Church in the shadow of the Mosque.
                                    Christians and Muslims in the world of Islam</title>
                                (2008).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. H.  Griffith</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Christian Lore and the Arabic Qurʾān: the “Companions of
                                the Cave” in <title rend="italic">Sūrat al-Kahf</title> and in
                                Syriac Christian Tradition’, in Reynolds 2008, 109–138.</bibl>
                            <bibl>D.  Gutas, <title rend="italic">Greek thought, Arabic culture: The
                                    Graeco-Arabic translation movement in Baghdad and early ʿAbbasid
                                    society</title> (1998).</bibl>
                            <bibl>Th.  Hainthaler, <title rend="italic">Christliche Araber vor dem
                                    Islam: Verbreitung und konfessionelle Zugehörigkeit; eine
                                    Hinführung</title> (2007).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Hourani, <title rend="italic">Arabic thought in the Liberal
                                    Age, 1798–1939</title> (1983).</bibl>
                            <bibl>R. G.  Hoyland, <title rend="italic">
                                    <choice>
                                        <sic>Seeing Islam as others saw
                                    it: A survey and evaluation of Christian, Jewish and Zoroastrian
                                    writings on Early Islam (1997)</sic>
                                        <corr>Seeing Islam</corr>
                                    </choice>
                                </title>.</bibl>
                            <bibl>H.  Hugonnard-Roche, <title rend="italic">La logique d’Aristote du
                                    grec au syriaque</title> (2004).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Jefferey, <title rend="italic">The foreign vocabulary of the
                                    Qurʾān</title> (1938).</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. L.  Kraemer, <title rend="italic">Humanism in the Renaissance
                                    of Islam: The cultural revival during the Buyid age</title>
                                (1986).</bibl>
                            <bibl>B.  Landron, <title rend="italic">Chrétiens et musulmans en Irak:
                                    Attitudes nestoriennes vis-à-vis de l’islam</title>
                                (1994).</bibl>
                            <bibl>C. Luxenberg, <title rend="italic">Die syro-aramäische Lesart des
                                    Koran: Ein Beitrag zur Entschlüsselung der Koransprache</title>
                                (2000; 2nd rev. <abbr>ed.</abbr> 2004). (<abbr>ET</abbr> by T. Müke as <title rend="italic">The Syro-Aramaic reading of the Koran: A contribution to the
                                    decoding of the language of the Koran</title> [2007])</bibl>
                            <bibl>L.  Massignon, ‘La politique islamo-chrétienne des scribes
                                nestoriens de Deir Qunna à la cour de Bagdad au IXe siècle de notre
                                ère’, <title rend="italic">Vivre et Penser</title> 2 (1942),
                                7–14.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>L.  Massignon</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Essai sur les <choice>
                                        <sic>origins</sic>
                                        <corr>origines</corr>
                                    </choice> du lexique
                                    technique de la mystique musulmane</title> (rev. <abbr>ed.</abbr> 1968). (<abbr>ET</abbr>
                                by B. Clark as <title rend="italic">Essay on the origins of the
                                    technical language of Islamic mysticism</title> [1997])</bibl>
                            <bibl>M. Metselaar, <title rend="italic">Die Nestorianer und der frühe
                                    Islam</title> (2009).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Mingana, ‘Syriac Influence on the Style of the Ḳurʾān’,
                                    <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>BJRL</abbr>
                                </title> 11 (1927), 77–98.</bibl>
                            <bibl>K. H.  Ohlig, ‘Das syrische und arabische Christentum und der
                                Koran’, in <title rend="italic">Die dunklen Anfänge: Neue
                                    Forschungen zur Entstehung und frühen Geschichte des
                                    Islam</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> K. H. Ohlig and G. R. Puin (2007),
                                366–404.</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Penn, ‘Syriac sources for the study of early Christian-Muslim
                                relations’, <title rend="italic">Islamochristiana</title> 29 (2003),
                                59–78.</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. J.  Reinink, ‘Ps.-Methodius: A concept of history in response
                                to the rise of Islam’, in <title rend="italic">The Byzantine and
                                    Early Islamic Near East</title>, vol. 1, <title rend="italic">Problems in the Literary Source Material</title>, ed<title rend="italic">.</title> A. Cameron and L. I. Conrad (1992),
                                149–87.</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Reynolds (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">The Qur’ān in its
                                    historical context</title> (2008).</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Salama-Carr, <title rend="italic">La traduction à l’époque
                                    abbaside: l’école de Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq et son importance pour la
                                    traduction</title> (1990).</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. Kh.  Samir, <title rend="italic">Foi et culture en Irak au XIe
                                    siècle: Elie de Nisibe et l’islam</title> (1996).</bibl>
                            <bibl>I.  Shahid, <title rend="italic">Byzantium and the Arabs in the
                                    fifth century</title> (1989).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>I.  Shahid</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Byzantium and the Arabs in the sixth
                                    century</title> (1995).</bibl>
                            <bibl>H.  Suermann, <title rend="italic">Die geschichtstheologische
                                    Reaktion auf die einfallenden Muslime in der edessenischen
                                    Apokalyptik des 7. Jahrhunderts</title> (1985).</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Tamcke (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Christians and Muslims in
                                    dialogue in the Islamic Orient of the
                                <choice>
                                        <sic>Middle-Ages</sic>
                                        <corr>Middle Ages</corr>
                                    </choice>
                                </title> (2007).</bibl>
                            <bibl>R.  Tardy, <title rend="italic">Najrān: Chrétiens d’Arabie avant
                                    l’islam</title> (1999).</bibl>
                            <bibl>H.  Takahashi, <title rend="italic">Bar Hebraeus: A
                                    bio-bibliography</title> (2005).</bibl>
                            <bibl>D.  Thomas (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Syrian Christians under
                                    Isalm. The first thousand years</title> (2001).</bibl>
                            <bibl>Thomas and Roggema (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Christian-Muslim
                                    relations</title>.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. Spencer Trimingham, <title rend="italic">Christianity among the
                                    Arabs in pre-Islamic times</title> (1979).</bibl>
                            <bibl>F.  van der Velden, ‘Konvergenztexte syrischer und arabischer
                                Christologie: Stufen der Textentwicklung von Sure 3, 33–64’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OC</abbr>
                                </title> 91 (2007), 164–203.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>F.  van der Velden</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Kontexte in Konvergenzstrang — die Bedeutung textkritischer
                                Varianten und christlicher Bezugstexte für die Redaktion von Sure 61
                                und Sure 5, 110–119’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OC</abbr>
                                </title> 92 (2008),
                                181–224.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  Wansbrough, <title rend="italic">The sectarian milieu: Content
                                    and composition of Islamic salvation history</title>
                                (1978).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Sidney H.</forename> 
                  <surname>Griffith</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
