<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Judaism, Syriac contacts with</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename> 
                  <surname>Van Rompay</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Judaism, Syriac contacts with</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Judaism-Syriac-contacts-with</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/318</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">309</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="232-236"/>
                    <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Syriac contacts with Judaism</idno>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">
                        <note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>Syriac Christianity originated and developed in areas in which communities of
                        Diaspora Judaism existed. Throughout their history Syr. Christians lived in
                        proximity to Jews, both in the cities of Syria and in North and Central
                        Mesopotamia, and they shared with Jews their language and much of their
                        religious worldview. The interactions between Syr. Christians and Jews can
                        be studied on three different levels: 1. the common religious and cultural
                        heritage, and the influx of ideas from Judaism into Syr. Christianity, in
                        particular in the early period; 2. the literary representations of Judaism
                        within Syr. Christian literature, which are often of a polemical nature; 3.
                        the more occasional and incidental comments on contacts and exchanges
                        between Syr. Christians and Jews in daily life. While Jews and Judaism are
                        frequently mentioned and discussed in Syr. sources, explicit references to
                        Syr. Christians are almost completely lacking from Jewish sources. Whether
                        and to what extent certain passages in Rabbinic literature were written in
                        response to arguments brought forward by Syr. Christians remains a question
                        of scholarly debate. Evidence of Jewish interest in Syr. Christianity is
                        occasionally found in the Middle Ages, e.g., when R. Hai Gaon (939–1038)
                        expresses interest in knowing the E.-<abbr>Syr. Cath.</abbr>’s view on an obscure phrase
                        in Psalms, or when a Jewish redactor rewrites the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Peshitta">Peshitta</ref> of
                        Proverbs into a Targum (Sokoloff, 404–5; Weitzman, 109–11). A more
                        considered interest was found in the period of Humanism and Enlightenment,
                        e.g., with <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/De-Rossi-Azariah-Buonaiuto">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/443">A. de’
                            Rossi</persName>
                        </ref> and, more sporadically, with B. de Spinoza (d. 1677).</p>
                    <p>The eastward spread of Christianity from Palestine must have affected the
                        Jewish communities and the Semitic, largely Aramaic speaking, populations of
                        Syria and Mesopotamia. Some of the earliest Christian preaching must have
                        been done in Aramaic, even though there is very little evidence. At the same
                        time, by the beginning of the Christian era, Hellenism and Greco-Roman
                        culture had a strong presence throughout the Near East, and Greek soon
                        became the primary language of Christianity. Not surprisingly, therefore,
                        there has been an ongoing discussion among scholars as to whether the Jewish
                        stream of ideas or the Greco-Roman one was more decisive in the birth and
                        early development of Syr. Christianity. There is reason, however, to assume
                        that Judaism was a determining factor in the origin and early development of
                        Syr. Christianity, based on the fact (1) that Syr. Christians, probably in
                        the late 2nd <abbr>cent.</abbr>, received the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta from Judaism (regardless of
                        whether the translation from Hebrew was made prior to its being adopted as
                        the Syr. Christian Bible, or was made by Syr. Christians with a Jewish
                        background); (2) that early Syr. literature occasionally reflects
                        non-biblical phraseology of the Jewish Targumim (e.g., Brock 1995); (3) and
                        that early Syr. liturgy exhibits features of Jewish origin (Rouwhorst).</p>
                    <p>Somewhat related to this is the question of Syr. Christianity’s relationship
                        to so-called Jewish Christianity, i.e., forms of Christianity represented by
                        people who, mostly of Jewish origin themselves, continued to identify as
                        Jews and remained faithful to Jewish customs and rituals (such as
                        circumcision and food laws). As evidence for the existence of Jewish
                        Christians in Syria, one may point to the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Didascalia-Apostolorum">Didascalia
                            Apostolorum</ref> (3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr>), which most likely was written in Syria
                        and which in some sections clearly reflects a Christian community that was
                        composed of both Gentiles and Jews (who had to be discouraged from
                        identifying too closely with non-Christian Judaism). This text, however, was
                        written in Greek and may not be representative of the situation in the
                        heartlands of Syr. Christianity; on the other hand, the text’s reception and
                        popularity in Syriac, most likely from the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> onwards, indicates that
                        its content was seen as relevant to Syr. Christianity. The Pseudo-Clementine
                        writings (see <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Clement-of-Rome-and-Pseudo-Clementine-literature">Clement of Rome</ref>) also reflect Jewish
                        understandings of Christianity (see most recently Reed). Written in Greek,
                        probably in the 3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr>, these texts were translated into Syriac and parts
                        were included in the earliest dated Syr. <abbr>ms.</abbr> (Brit. Libr. Add. 12,150, dated
                        411).</p>
                    <p>Recent scholarship has pointed out that in the early Christian period the
                        boundaries between Jewish and Christian communities were far from watertight
                        and allowed for a rather fluid pattern of religious identification. This
                        situation of porous borders may have lasted longer in Aramaic-speaking areas
                        than in the Greco-Roman world; it also may have had a longer history in the
                        Sasanian Empire, where the 4th-cent. Christianization of the Roman Empire
                        had little immediate effect (Becker 2003). In such a situation the
                        interrelationship between Jews and Christians may have been more complex
                        than it was in the Christianized Roman Empire.</p>
                    <p>Regardless of how strong a presence Jewish Christianity had in the early
                        period, Syr. Christianity from the 4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> onwards saw itself as breaking
                        away from Judaism. The two main 4th-cent. authors, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aphrahat">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/10">Aphrahaṭ</persName>
                        </ref> and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ephrem">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/13">Ephrem</persName>
                        </ref>,
                        convey mixed messages. On the one hand, a number of themes and ideas of
                        Jewish origin are found in their works and suppose an audience that, at
                        least in part, was well acquainted with Judaism. On the other hand, this
                        common ground with Judaism did not prevent these authors from expressing
                        distance from and rejection of Judaism, including contemporary Judaism. Just
                        as in Greek Christian literature, Judaism was defined increasingly as the
                        opposite of Christianity. The writings of Aphrahaṭ and Ephrem may be read
                        perhaps as reflecting a situation which was still characterized by ongoing
                        communality between Jews and Christians, but in which these very authors
                        were intent on drawing clearer boundaries and creating separation.
                        Anti-Jewish sentiment, which had been largely absent from early Syr.
                        literature, became a factor in the process of Christian self-identification.
                        It may also be telling that it is mainly Aphrahaṭ’s second series of
                        Demonstrations (nos.  11–22), dated to 344, that contains anti-Jewish
                        polemic, while the earlier series (Dem. 1–10, dated to 337) is relatively
                        free from it. In 344, well into the Roman-Persian war and the predicament of
                        persecution, Christians may have needed a more powerful warning that they
                        should not choose the easy solution of retreating to the relative safety of
                        Judaism.</p>
                    <p>Aphrahaṭ and Ephrem, writing in the Persian-Sasanian Empire and in the Roman
                        Empire respectively, share a number of themes and arguments in their
                        dealings with Judaism, but their tone is very different. To account for
                        Ephrem’s harsh language about Jews (which may have targeted Judaizing
                        Christians rather than Jews themselves), scholars have pointed to Ephrem’s
                        and his community’s own profound Jewishness (Cassingena: ‘«judéité»
                        fondatrice’), which would have contributed to Ephrem’s particular
                        sensitivity. But the general profile of Aphrahaṭ’s community cannot have
                        been much different, and yet his approach is so much milder. Should we
                        ascribe the difference between Aphrahaṭ and Ephrem to ‘personal temperament
                        and inclination’ (Hayman 1985, 427)? Or should the social and political
                        context be taken into consideration? In the Persian-Sasanian Empire, in
                        which Aphrahaṭ wrote, both Judaism and Christianity were minorities in the
                        Zoroastrian society. In the Roman Empire, however, Syr. Christianity soon
                        became part of the emerging imperial orthodoxy, which in Ephrem’s day was in
                        the process of asserting itself, although it still was fragile (as the short
                        reign of Emperor Julian showed) and weakened by internal division. Might
                        this difference have contributed to setting a different tone for Aphrahaṭ,
                        on the one hand, and for Ephrem, on the other? But even within the corpus of
                        Ephrem’s writings the degree of anti-Jewish polemic differs widely: the
                        Commentary on Genesis (a work with many ‘Jewish’ features) and the Prose
                        Refutations (dealing with different ‘heretical’ doctrines) have very little
                        anti-Jewish polemic; the anti-Judaism of the Commentary on the Diatessaron
                        reflects the language of theological debate (Morrison); and some of the
                        Hymns are passionately anti-Jewish.</p>
                    <p>Anti-Jewish literature continued in Syr. Christianity, without ever becoming
                        as prominent as it was in Greek or Latin Christianity. And again, marked
                        differences are found, such as between <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Serugh">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Yaʿqub of
                            Serugh</persName>
                        </ref>’s harshness and his contemporary <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Narsai">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/650">Narsai</persName>
                        </ref>’s mildness
                        (Frishman). Here again, one author is writing within the Roman Empire and
                        the other as a member of a minority group in the Persian-Sasanian Empire. In
                        addition, these authors belong to different theological traditions, which
                        may have had a different impact on their approach to Judaism. As dyophysite
                        Christology and Antiochene biblical interpretation were often portrayed by
                        opponents as being (nearly) identical to Judaism, the use of anti-Jewish
                        argument may have become, for those of the Antiochene tradition, less
                        attractive.</p>
                    <p>From the mid-8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, when both Jews and Syr. Christians had become
                        minority groups under the dominance of Islam, a report is preserved of a
                        disputation that was held in the region of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Hims">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/215">Ḥimṣ</placeName>
                        </ref> between <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sargis-the-Stylite">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/81">Sargis the Stylite</persName>
                        </ref> (it is unclear whether he was a Miaphysite or
                        a Chalcedonian) and a Jew (<abbr>ed.</abbr> Hayman). While the text contains a number of
                        stock arguments of anti-Jewish polemic, there also is a remarkable passage
                        in which the Jewish interlocutor mentions those Christians ‘who associate
                        with us in the synagogue, and who bring offerings and alms and oil, and at
                        the time of the Passover send unleavened bread …’ (22.1, <abbr>ed.</abbr> Hayman, 72;
                        transl. 73–74). Sargis is unable to challenge this description, but portrays
                        these people as ‘sick and weak’, not able to walk on the king’s highway.
                        Once again we seem to be confronted with porous borders, which allow for
                        multiple religious identifications.</p>
                    <p>In addition to occasionally targeting the Jews in their theological polemic,
                        Syr. Christians also had a genuine interest in Judaism. Their main source
                        for post-biblical Jewish history was <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Josephus">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/577">Josephus</persName>
                        </ref>’s ‘Jewish
                        War’. While a Syr. translation is preserved only of the Sixth Book,
                        quotations from other books in Sargis the Stylite’s ‘Disputation’ and
                        elsewhere (in a Miaphysite florilegium, possibly of the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, preserved
                        in <abbr>ms.</abbr> Dayr al-Suryān 28, and in <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysios-bar-Salibi">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/212">Dionysios
                            bar Ṣalibi</persName>
                        </ref>’s Treatise against the Jews) suggest that a full
                        translation once existed. This work was used for purposes well beyond that
                        of polemic. <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Edessa">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/113">Yaʿqub of
                            Edessa</persName>
                        </ref> had a keen interest in Jewish writings, such as the ‘Book
                        of Enoch’ and ‘Jewish Histories’ (<hi rend="italic">tašʿyātā yudāyātā</hi>,
                        a work related to ‘Jubilees’), whose authenticity and usefulness he
                        defended, even against more negative views in the earlier tradition (Adler).
                        He was also familiar with certain Jewish traditions, such as the
                        pronunciation and writing of the Tetragrammaton, and he was aware of the
                        importance of the Hebrew language, of which he had some, albeit rather
                        limited knowledge (see Salvesen). <abbr>Cath. </abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Timotheos-I">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/790">Timotheos I</persName>
                        </ref> as
                        well relied on Jews, who in some cases were converts, for information about
                        the Bible. A common practice in biblical commentaries is the quotation of
                        alternative readings from the ‘Hebrew (Bible)’ (along with those from the
                        Septuagint), which either agree with the Masoretic text or, more often,
                        reflect later Jewish interpretations (see, e.g., Ter Haar Romeny 2001).
                        Interest in Jewish sects is found in several Syr. authors, the latest of
                        whom is Dionysios bar Ṣalibi (Brock 1977). In his ‘Treatise against the
                        Jews’, probably the last such work to be written in Syriac, he included an
                        overview of Jewish sects, largely based on <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Epiphanius-of-Salamis">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/477">Epiphanius
                            of Salamis</persName>
                        </ref>’s <hi rend="italic">Anakephalaiosis</hi>, expanded with
                        information taken from Josephus’ ‘Jewish War’ (Book II,160–6). <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/239">Bar ʿEbroyo</persName>
                        </ref>’s attitude towards Judaism is largely
                        irenic. While until recently it was assumed that he was of Jewish descent
                        (‘Son of the Hebrew’, his father being the physician Ahrun), most scholars
                        have now abandoned this view, linking his name instead to the village of
                        ʿEbro, on the Euphrates. There is very little evidence of conversion from
                        Judaism to Syr. Christianity in the Islamic period and, more generally,
                        contacts between Jews and Christians are very poorly documented. Canonical
                        collections include rules urging Christians to work on the Jewish Sabbath,
                        prohibiting bishops and clergy from celebrating Jewish festivals, and
                        warning Christians not to accept unleavened bread from Jews (Kawerau 94).
                        Here again we may be dealing with attempts by the church leadership to
                        create a separation that did not always exist in daily life.</p>
                    <p>For the later period, we have an interesting example of the co-existence of
                        Jews and E.-Syr. Christians in Iraqi Kurdistan. From the early 17th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        onwards, benefitting from improved living conditions, both Jews and
                        Christians started writing down their vernacular Neo-Aramaic languages,
                        which were closely related and mutually understandable. Borrowing the script
                        from their respective authoritative traditions (Hebrew and Jewish Aramaic
                        for the Jews and Syriac for the Christians), they proceeded in very similar
                        ways, turning in the first place to liturgical or para-liturgical texts.
                        This ‘areal phenomenon’, involving both Jewish and Christian communities (A.
                        Mengozzi, <hi rend="italic">Israel of Alqosh and Joseph of Telkepe</hi>
                        [<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 590; 2002], 16), seems to presuppose a rather unproblematic
                        relationship between the two religious communities. As a matter of fact,
                        Aramaic-speaking Jews and Christians lived together peacefully in Iraqi
                        Kurdistan until around 1950, and in Iran even later. Among the villages and
                        towns in which Jews and Christians lived in close proximity to each other,
                        the following deserve to be singled out: <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Alqosh">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/19">Alqosh</placeName>
                        </ref>, where Jews
                        and Christians went on pilgrimage to the tomb of the prophet Nahum (Fiey,
                            <hi rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne</hi>, vol. 2, 396–400); Zakho (see
                        most recently A. Sabar, <hi rend="italic">My father’s paradise</hi> [2009]);
                        and Shosh (ancient Bashosh; see Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Assyrie
                            chrétienne</hi>, vol. 1, 259). An E.-Syr. <abbr>ms.</abbr>, Brit. Libr. Add. 25,875,
                        dated 1709/10 (Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol. 3, 1064–69)
                        contains a Hebrew alphabet and some additional writing in Hebrew, including
                        a part of Ps. 22 in Hebrew script, even though the text is Syriac. In the
                        20th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, however, the political situation in the Middle East added a new
                        layer of tension to the relationship between Jews and Syr. Christians.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Primary Sources (selection)</head>
                            <bibl>M.  Albert, <title rend="italic">Jacques de Saroug. Homélies
                                    contre les Juifs</title> (<abbr>PO</abbr> 38.1; 1976).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A. H.  Becker, ‘The Discourse on the Priesthood (BL Add. 18295,
                                ff. 137b–140b): An anti-Jewish text on the abrogation of the
                                Israelite priesthood’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JSS</abbr>
                                </title> 51 (2006),
                                85–115. (with an important ‘Note’ on this text by G. Herman, in
                                    <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JSS</abbr>
                                </title> 54 [2009], 389–91)</bibl>
                            <bibl>A. P.  Hayman, <title rend="italic">The disputation of Sergius the
                                    Stylite against a Jew</title> (<abbr>CSCO</abbr> 338–339; 1973).</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  de Zwaan, <title rend="italic">The treatise of Dionysius bar
                                    Ṣalibhi against the Jews</title> (1906).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>W. Adler, ‘Jewish Pseudepigrapha in Jacob of Edessa’s Letters and
                                historical writings’, in <title rend="italic">Jacob of Edessa and
                                    the Syriac culture of his day</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> B. ter Haar Romeny
                                (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 18; 2008), 49–65.</bibl>
                            <bibl>A. H.  Becker, ‘Anti-Judaism and care for the poor in Aphrahat’s
                                    <title rend="italic">Demonstration</title> 20’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JECS</abbr>
                                </title> 10 (2002), 305–27.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>A. H.  Becker</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Beyond the spatial and temporal <title rend="italic">Limes</title>: Questioning the “Parting of the ways” outside
                                the Roman Empire’, in <title rend="italic">The ways that never
                                    parted. Jews and Christians in Late Antiquity and the Middle
                                    Ages</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. H. Becker and A. Y. Reed (2003; <abbr>repr.</abbr>
                                2007), 373–92.</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. P. Brock, ‘Some Syriac accounts of the Jewish sects’, in <title rend="italic">A Tribute to Arthur Vööbus</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. H.
                                Fischer, 265–76.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. P.  Brock</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Jewish traditions in Syriac sources’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JJS</abbr>
                                </title> 30 (1979), 212–232.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. P.  Brock</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘A Palestinian Targum feature in Syriac’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JJS</abbr>
                                </title> 46 (1995), 271–82.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>S. P.  Brock</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘The Peshitta Old Testament. Between Judaism and
                                Christianity’, <title rend="italic">Cristianesimo nella
                                    Storia</title> 19 (1998), 483–502.</bibl>
                            <bibl>F.  Cassingena-Trévedy, ‘Éphrem le Syrien et le judaïsme:
                                renversement d’une problématique’, in <title rend="italic">Études
                                    bibliques et Proche-Orient ancien. Mélanges offerts au Père P.
                                    Féghali</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Chehwan and A. Kassis (2002), 343–52.
                                (also in <title rend="italic">Lettre de Ligugé</title> 295 [2001],
                                112–17)</bibl>
                            <bibl>H. J. W. Drijvers, ‘Edessa und das jüdische Christentum’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>VC</abbr>
                                </title> 24 (1970), 3–33.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>H. J. W. Drijvers</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Jews and Christians at Edessa’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JJS</abbr>
                                </title> 36 (1985), 88–102.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>H. J. W. Drijvers</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Syrian Christianity and Judaism’, in <title rend="italic">The Jews among pagans and Christians in the Roman
                                    Empire</title>, ed J. Lieu <abbr>et al.</abbr> (1992), 124–46.</bibl>
                            <bibl>C. Fonrobert, ‘The Didascalia apostolorum: a Mishnah for the
                                disciples of Jesus’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JECS</abbr>
                                </title> 9 (2001),
                                483–509.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. Frishman, ‘Narsai’s homily for the Palm Festival — Against the
                                Jews: For the Palm Festival or Against the Jews?’<choice>
                                    <sic/>
                                    <corr/>
                                </choice> in <abbr>
                                    <title rend="italic">SymSyr</title> IV</abbr>, 217–29.</bibl>
                            <bibl>eadem, ‘And Abraham had faith: But in what? Ephrem and the Rabbis
                                on Abraham and God’s Blessings’, in <title rend="italic">The
                                    Exegetical Encounter between Jews and Christians in Late
                                    Antiquity. The Book of Genesis</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> H.  Spurling and
                                E.  Grypeou (Jewish and Christian Perspectives Series 18; 2009),
                                163–79.</bibl>
                            <bibl>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny, ‘The Hebrew and the Greek as
                                alternatives to the Syriac version in Išoʿdad’s Commentary on the
                                Psalms’, in <title rend="italic">Biblical Hebrew, Biblical texts.
                                    Essays in memory of Michael P. Weitzman</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr>
                                A.  Rapoport-Albert and G. Greenberg (<abbr>JSOT</abbr> Supplement Series 333;
                                2001), 431–56.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>  ‘Hypotheses on the development of Judaism and Christianity
                                in Syria in the period after 70 c.e.’, in <title rend="italic">Matthew and the Didache: Two Documents from the Same
                                    Jewish-Christian Milieu?</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> H. van de Sandt (2005),
                                13–33.</bibl>
                            <bibl>A. P. Hayman, ‘The image of the Jew in the Syriac anti-Jewish
                                polemical literature,’ in <title rend="italic">“To see ourselves as
                                    others see us”. Christians, Jews, “Others” in Late
                                    Antiquity</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> J. Neusner and E. S. Frerichs (1985),
                                423–41.</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. Hidal, ‘Evidence for Jewish believers in the Syriac Fathers’,
                                in <title rend="italic">Jewish believers in Jesus</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> O.
                                Skarsaune and R. Hvalvik (2007), 568–80.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. Joosten, ‘La tradition syriaque des évangiles et la question du
                                «substrat araméen»’, <title rend="italic">Revue d’histoire et de
                                    philosophie religieuses</title> 77 (1997), 257–72.</bibl>
                            <bibl>P.  Kawerau, <title rend="italic">Die jakobitische Kirche im
                                    Zeitalter der syrischen Renaissance</title> (1955).</bibl>
                            <bibl>S.  Kazan, ‘Isaac of Antioch’s Homily against the Jews’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>OC</abbr>
                                </title> 45 (1961), 30–53; 46 (1962), 87–98; 47
                                (1963), 88–97; 49 (1965), 57–78.</bibl>
                            <bibl>N. Koltun-Fromm, ‘A Jewish-Christian conversation in
                                fourth-century Persian Mesopotamia’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JJS</abbr>
                                </title> 47 (1996), 45–63.</bibl>
                            <bibl>eadem, ‘Aphrahat and the Rabbis on Noah’s righteousness in light
                                of the Jewish-Christian polemic’, in <title rend="italic">The book
                                    of Genesis in Jewish and Oriental Christian interpretation. A
                                    collection of essays</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> J. Frishman and L. Van Rompay
                                (<abbr>TEG</abbr> 5; 1997), 57–71.</bibl>
                            <bibl>eadem, ‘Zipporah’s complaint. Moses is not conscientious in the
                                deed! Exegetical traditions of Moses’ celibacy’, in <title rend="italic">The ways that never parted. Jews and Christians in
                                    Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. H. Becker and
                                A. Y. Reed (2003; <abbr>repr.</abbr> 2007), 283–306.</bibl>
                            <bibl>eadem, <title rend="italic">Hermeneutics of Holiness. Ancient
                                    Jewish and Christian Notions of Sexuality and Religious
                                    Community</title> (2010).</bibl>
                            <bibl>T.  Kronholm, <title rend="italic">Motifs from Genesis 1–11 in the
                                    genuine hymns of Ephrem the Syrian, with particular reference to
                                    the influence of Jewish exegetical tradition</title>
                                (Coniectanea Biblica. Old Testament Series 11; 1978).</bibl>
                            <bibl>K. McVey, ‘The anti-Judaic polemic of Ephrem Syrus’ Hymns on the
                                Nativity’, in <title rend="italic">Of scribes and <choice>
                                        <sic>scholars</sic>
                                        <corr>scrolls</corr>
                                    </choice>: Studies
                                    on the Hebrew Bible, intertestamental Judaism, and Christian
                                    origins presented to J. Strugnell</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> H. W. Attridge et
                                al. (1990), 229–40.</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. C.  Mimouni, ‘Le judéo-christianisme syriaque: mythe littéraire
                                ou réalité historique?’<choice>
                                    <sic>,</sic>
                                    <corr/>
                                </choice> in <abbr>
                                    <title rend="italic">SymSyr</title> VI</abbr>,
                                269–79.</bibl>
                            <bibl>C. E.  Morrison, ‘The Jews in Ephrem’s Commentary on the
                                Diatessaron’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JCSSS</abbr>
                                </title> 8 (2008),
                                23–43.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  Neusner, <title rend="italic">Aphrahat and Judaism. The
                                    Christian-Jewish argument in fourth-century Iran</title> (Studia
                                Post-Biblica 19; 1971; <abbr>repr.</abbr> 1999).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A. Y.  Reed, ‘ “Jewish Christianity” as counter-history? The
                                apostolic past in Eusebius’ <title rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                                    History</title> and the Pseudo-Clementine Homilies’, in <title rend="italic">Antiquity in Antiquity. Jewish and Christian pasts
                                    in the Greco-Roman world</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> G.  Gardner and
                                K. L.  Osterloh (Texts and Studies in Ancient Judaism 123; 2008),
                                173–216.</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Rouwhorst, ‘Jewish liturgical traditions in early Syriac
                                Christianity’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>VC</abbr>
                                </title> 51 (1997),
                                72–93.</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Salvesen, ‘Did Jacob of Edessa know Hebrew?’<choice>
                                    <sic>,</sic>
                                    <corr/>
                                </choice> in <title rend="italic">Biblical Hebrew, Biblical texts. Essays in memory
                                    of Michael P. Weitzman</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A. Rapoport-Albert and G.
                                Greenberg (<abbr>JSOT</abbr> Supplement Series 333; 2001), 457–67.</bibl>
                            <bibl>C.  Shepardson, <title rend="italic">Anti-Judaism and Christian
                                    orthodoxy. Ephrem’s Hymns in fourth-century Syria</title> (North
                                American Patristics Society. Monograph Series 20; 2008).</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Sokoloff, ‘Jewish Babylonian Aramaic and Syriac: Mutual
                                elucidation’, in <abbr>
                                    <title rend="italic">SymSyr</title> VI</abbr>,
                                401–8.</bibl>
                            <bibl>M. P.  Weitzman, <title rend="italic">The Syriac Version of the
                                    Old Testament: An Introduction</title> (University of Cambridge
                                Oriental Publications 56; 1999).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename> 
                  <surname>Van Rompay</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
