<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Baby</forename> 
                  <surname>Varghese</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Malankara-Orthodox-Syrian-Church</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/348</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">339</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="256-258"/>
                    <note type="type">org</note>
                    <note type="abstract">The Malankara Orthodox Church claims to have
                        been founded by St. Thomas, one of the twelve apostles of Christ.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Malankara Orthodox Church (MOC) proudly claims to have been founded by
                        St. Thomas, one of the twelve apostles of Christ. From the early centuries
                        of the Common Era, the St. Thomas Christians of Kerala had intermittent
                        relationship with the Syriac communities in the ancient Persian Empire.
                        Regular contacts were rather difficult, because of the Arab-Muslim control
                        of the trade route in the Arabian Sea.</p>
                    <p>In the 15th <abbr>cent.</abbr> the relationship with the E.-Syr. Church was apparently
                        strong, but this was abruptly broken by the Portuguese presence in the
                        Indian subcontinent. In the so-called <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diamper-Synod-of">Synod of
                            Diamper</ref> (1599), Dom. Alexis Menezis, Archbishop of Goa, with the
                        support of the king of Cochin, was able to bring the St. Thomas Christians
                        under the authority of Rome. In 1653 the great majority rejected the forced
                        union with Rome at the famous Coonan Cross. As they wanted to retain Syriac
                        language and liturgy, and above all the ecclesiastical independence, they
                        wrote letters to various Eastern patriarchates requesting to send them a <abbr>bp.</abbr>
                        Thus in 1665, in a Dutch vessel Mar Gregorios, the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        <abbr> bp.</abbr> of
                        ‘Jerusalem’ reached Kerala and consecrated Mar Thoma I, as the <abbr>bp.</abbr> of the
                        St. Thomas Christians. In 1685, Mar Baselios Yaldo and Mar Ivanios
                        Ḥidayatallah, two more Antiochian prelates, arrived. However, the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        liturgy and the Serṭo script were widely used only much later. E.-Syr.
                        influence is evident from the fact <choice>
                            <sic/>
                            <corr>that </corr>
                        </choice>the six bishops who headed the community
                        between 1665 and 1765 took the title Mar Thoma I to VI.</p>
                    <p>In 1751, the arrival of a <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> delegation consisting of Baselios
                        Shakrallah, Mar Gregorios, Ramban Yoḥannan, and a few deacons, marks the
                        beginning of the introduction of the Serṭo script and the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> liturgy
                        in the Malankara Orthodox Church. Mar Thoma VI (consecrated by his
                        predecessor in 1765), the head of the Syrians, after much hesitation,
                        consented to be re-consecrated by the Antiochian bishops under the name Mar
                        Dionysios I (in 1770).</p>
                    <p>Meanwhile in 1772, the Antiochian <abbr>bp.</abbr> Mar Gregorios consecrated a native <abbr>bp.</abbr>
                        named Mar Koorilose. Mar Dionysios I (alias Mar Toma VI) used his political
                        influence to expel the rival <abbr>bp.</abbr> to Thozhiyur, in the kingdom of Cochin.
                        This marks the origin of the so-called <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Malabar-Independent-Syrian-Church">Malabar Independent Syrian Church</ref> (or ‘Thozhiyur Church’).</p>
                    <p>In 1815 Pulikottil Joseph Mar Dionysios (consecrated by Mar Philoxenos, the
                        second <abbr>bp.</abbr> of Thozhiyur) founded the Old Seminary (the present Orthodox
                        Theological Seminary) with the generous support of the British Resident Col.
                        Munro. Following the death of Mar Dionysios (in 1816), the English
                        missionaries assumed the direction of the Old Seminary and modern education
                        started in Kerala for the first time. The missionaries had the dream to
                        train native clergy and to reform the liturgical practices of the Malankara
                        Orthodox Church. The native clergy were opposed to it, and in 1836 the
                        missionaries left the Seminary. However, they did convert a few Syrian
                        Christians to the Anglican Church.</p>
                    <p>Meanwhile, some of the Syrians favourable to the reforms, sent a deacon to
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mardin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/130">Mardin</placeName>
                        </ref> and in 1843, <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Mar Eliya II consecrated him under the
                        name Mathews Mar Athanasios. He was the first Indian <abbr>bp.</abbr> consecrated by a
                        <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        <abbr> 
                     <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> On his return to India, he led the efforts for reforms with
                        some success thanks to the support of the English missionaries and the local
                        rulers. Cheppattu Mar Dionysios, the head of the Malankara Orthodox Church<choice>
                            <sic> was</sic>
                            <corr/>
                        </choice> unwilling to fight against the reformers, abdicated in favour of a
                        visiting Antiochian prelate named Yoyakim Mar Koorilose. Though he could not
                        provide effective leadership for the community against the reformers, during
                        his 20 years stay in Kerala, Mar Koorilose visited parishes and completed
                        the introduction of Antiochian liturgical practices. In 1864, the Patriarch
                        Yaʿqub II consecrated a native prelate named Joseph Mar Dionysios (<choice>
                            <sic>d.1909</sic>
                            <corr>d. 1909</corr>
                        </choice>).
                        Being unable to contain the progress of the reformers, he appealed to the
                        <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> to visit India. Thus <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Peṭros III visited Malabar and during his
                        <choice>
                            <sic>two year</sic>
                            <corr>two-year</corr>
                        </choice> stay (1875–77), he brought the Malankara Orthodox Church under the
                        <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Patriarchate of Antioch. In 1876, the <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> convened a synod in
                        Mulanthuruthy (near Cochin) and established an administrative structure. The
                        parishes over which the ‘Malankara Metropolitan’ had little or no control<choice>
                            <sic>,</sic>
                            <corr/>
                        </choice>
                        were organized under six dioceses, and six bishops were consecrated. Thus
                        the system of a single metropolitan for the entire Church came to an
                        end.</p>
                    <p>A few years later, the royal court of Travancore made a verdict in favour of
                        Mar Joseph Dionysios and the Malankara Orthodox Church. The reformed group
                        established themselves as an independent church, known as ‘the Mar Thoma
                        Syrian Church’.</p>
                    <p>In the first decade of the 20th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, the relationship between the <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Mar <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abdullah-II-Sattuf">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/313">ʿAbdullāh II</persName>
                        </ref> and Mar Geevarghese Mar Dionysios became
                        tense on the question of authority over properties of the Malankara Orthodox
                        Church. This led to the excommunication of Mar Dionysios and the division of
                        the Malankara Orthodox Church into two groups, one accepting the supreme
                        authority of the patriarch and the other rejecting it. The group led by Mar
                        Dionysios invited <abbr>Patr. </abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abdulmasih-II">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/314">ʿAbdulmasīḥ II</persName>
                        </ref>, who was
                        
                        deposed by the Turkish authorities. In 1912, he consecrated Baselios Pawlos
                        I (d. 1914), the first <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Cath.</sic>
                                <corr>cath.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> of the Malankara Orthodox Church. Thus began
                        the major division and a series of litigations which lasted for four
                        decades. In 1934, the General Assembly of the Malankara Orthodox Church
                        adopted a Constitution and endorsed the claims of autocephaly. In 1958, the
                        Supreme Court of India made a verdict in favour of the <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Cath.</sic>
                                <corr>cath.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> Thanks to the
                        initiatives of the Patriarch <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ignatius-Yaqub-III">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/545">Ignatius
                            Yaʿqub III</persName>
                        </ref> and the Catholicos Geevarghese II (1929–64), the two
                        groups were united. In 1964, Patriarch Yaʿqub III presided over the
                        consecration of the Catholicos Augen I (d. 1975).</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately the unity did not last for more than 12 years. The <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr>
                        consecrated bishops and finally in 1975, a <abbr>Cath.</abbr> (‘<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Maphrian">Maphrian</ref>’) for the
                        group which accepted his authority. Now the Malankara Orthodox Church
                        remains divided under two Catholicoi and two synods.</p>
                    <p>The Malankara Orthodox Church has a membership of about 1 million, 1100
                        parishes, 1200 priests, and 18 bishops. There are several schools, Colleges,
                        Engineering and Medical Faculties, hospitals and orphanages under its
                        administration. The Malankara Orthodox Church follows the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Liturgy
                        (Mosul tradition). But the liturgical language is Malayalam. Hindi and
                        English are, however, also used in North India or outside India.</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/66">Fig. 66</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>C. Chaillot, <title rend="italic">The Malankara Orthodox
                                Church</title> (1996).</bibl>
                        <bibl>D. Daniel, <title rend="italic">The Orthodox Church of India. A
                                History</title> (1972).</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. K. Kuriakose (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Orthodox Identity in
                                India. Essays in Honour of V. C. Samuel</title> (1988).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Baby</forename> 
                  <surname>Varghese</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
