<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Mar Thoma Syrian Church (Malankara)</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>John R. K.</forename> 
                  <surname>Fenwick</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Mar Thoma Syrian Church (Malankara)</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mar-Thoma-Syrian-Church-Malankara</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/356</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">347</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="265-266"/>
                    <note type="type">org</note>
                    <note type="abstract">The Mar Thoma Church is that section of the non-Roman Saint
                        Thomas Christians which has undertaken a degree of liturgical and doctrinal
                        reform under the influence of Church of England missionaries in the 19th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> 
                  <note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Mar Thoma Church is that section of the non-Roman St. <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Thomas-Christians">Thomas
                            Christians</ref> which has undertaken a degree of liturgical and
                        doctrinal reform under the influence of Church of England missionaries in
                        the 19th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                    </p>
                    <p>The arrival of British administrators and <choice>
                            <sic>Churchmen</sic>
                            <corr>churchmen</corr>
                        </choice> in early 19th-cent.
                        Kerala coincided with a desire for improved training for clergy. With the
                        encouragement of the British Resident, Colonel Munro, a College was founded
                        at Kottayam under Indian auspices, though it was soon dominated by
                        missionaries of the Anglican Church Missionary Society who arrived in 1816.
                        Under their influence Palakunnathu Abraham, a <hi rend="italic">Malpan</hi>
                        from Maramon, agitated for the removal of some liturgical and cultural
                        practices. Abraham was simultaneously genuinely committed to W.-Syr.
                        identity, including the use of Serṭo script, which rapidly replaced E.-Syr.
                        while he was teaching at the College.</p>
                    <p>Various factions in the community appealed to the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        <abbr> Patr.</abbr> at <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Zafaran-Dayr">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/69">Dayr
                            al-Zaʿfarān</placeName>
                        </ref>, who, in 1842, consecrated a nephew of Abraham Malpan
                        as Mathews Mar Athanasios. His pursuit of reform was inconsistent. He
                        continued as Malankara Metropolitan until his death in 1877, though in the
                        preceding year <abbr>Patr.</abbr> Peṭros III had divided Kerala into seven Dioceses for
                        those who wished to live under his jurisdiction. After a decade of
                        litigation, a Court ruling in 1889 declared that Toma Mar Athanasios
                        (successor to Mathews Mar Athanasios) was not Malankara Metropolitan as he
                        had not been consecrated by a <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Antioch">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>
                        </ref>. The
                        ‘Reformers’ were required to leave the ancient Churches and erect new
                        buildings. They took the name ‘Mar Thoma Syrian Church’.</p>
                    <p>There was a crisis in 1893 when Toma Mar Athanasios died without having
                        consecrated a successor. Recourse was had to the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Malabar-Independent-Syrian-Church">Malabar Independent Syrian Church</ref>, whose bishops travelled to
                        Kottayam in the face of many threats and consecrated a son of Abraham Malpan
                        with the title Titus Mar Thoma. Since then, Thozhiyur bishops have actively
                        participated at every Mar Thoma consecration, thus enabling that Church to
                        remain sacramentally connected to its Oriental Orthodox heritage. On five
                        occasions in the 20th <abbr>cent.</abbr> Mar Thoma Metropolitans have consecrated bishops
                        for Thozhiyur.</p>
                    <p>The ‘agenda’ of the reform was very much determined by the issues which had
                        dominated the English Reformation in the 16th <abbr>cent.</abbr>: prayer and the
                        departed, the invocation of saints, eucharistic Presence. The first two were
                        deleted from liturgical practice. With regard to the third, the Mar Thoma
                        anaphoral epiclesis still prays that the Holy Spirit will ‘sanctify this
                        Bread that it may be the Body of our Lord Jesus Christ’ (with a parallel
                        petition over the Cup), though prayer addressed to the Sacramental Christ is
                        omitted. Phrases which Anglican influence suggested were capable of a
                        ‘monophysite’ interpretation were also amended. Only the Councils of Nicaea,
                        Constantinople, and Ephesus are commemorated in the Qurbānā.</p>
                    <p>The form of the Church’s worship remains unmistakably <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> The
                        vestments, church furnishings, chanting, use of incense, and the general
                        dynamics of worship mark it as a Church in the Oriental Orthodox tradition.
                        Its bishops are celibates, distinguished by the monastic <hi rend="italic">schema</hi>. They are buried seated in their robes. Beards are optional
                        for priests, but are worn by many (all bishops have them). The white cassock
                        is universal. Most worship is now in Malayalam, though some Syriac formulae
                        remain in use. English and other languages are increasingly used outside
                        India.</p>
                    <p>The Church has always had a strong commitment to fostering the spiritual life
                        of its members. In the 1880s it inaugurated the world-famous Maramon
                        Convention. Domestic prayer and Bible reading are encouraged. Ashrams and,
                        more recently, a celibate order of priests have been instituted. The Church
                        has several evangelistic missions throughout India, but has not yet applied
                        its evangelistic zeal to any great extent in the Diaspora. There is a long
                        tradition of close relations with the Church of South India and the Church
                        of North India, though the Mar Thoma Church has said that it does not wish
                        to abandon its eastern heritage by uniting with the two western-derived
                        Churches. The Church is actively involved in the World Council of Churches
                        and other ecumenical bodies.</p>
                    <p>Theological training remains Western in form. Whereas the <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Malabar-Catholic-Church">Malabar
                            Catholic Church</ref> has engaged in an active debate about freeing
                        itself from colonially-imposed theological method and rediscovering its
                        Eastern roots, the Mar Thoma Church has not yet ventured upon that
                        process.</p>
                    <p>The Church today has approximately 1 million members worldwide, under the
                        oversight of ten bishops. The bishops constitute the episcopal synod,
                        presided over by the most senior, who is Metropolitan. The supreme governing
                        body is the <hi rend="italic">Sabha Mandalam</hi>, which has over a thousand
                        clergy and lay representatives from all the congregations worldwide, and
                        meets annually.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>K. T.  Joy, <title rend="italic">The Mar Thoma Church: A Study
                                of its Growth and Contribution</title> (published by the author;
                            Kottayam, 1986).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Mar Thoma, <title rend="italic">Christianity in India and a Brief
                                History of the Mar Thoma Syrian Church</title> (1968).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Mar Thoma, <title rend="italic">The Mar Thoma Church: Heritage and
                                Mission</title> (2nd <abbr>ed.</abbr> 1986).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>John R. K.</forename> 
                  <surname>Fenwick</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
