<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Martyrs and persecutions</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Sebastian P.</forename> 
                  <surname>Brock</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Martyrs and persecutions</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Martyrs-and-persecutions</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/366</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">357</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="271-273"/>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Times of persecution and of martyrdom fall into four main
                        periods: 1. early 4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> (and again under Julian, 361-3), within the
                        Roman Empire (<choice>
                            <sic>i.e. </sic>
                            <corr>i.e., </corr>
                        </choice>approximately <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/648">Turkey</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/486">Syria</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/487">Lebanon</placeName>, and Palestine);
                        2. mid-4th to mid-7th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, in the Persian (Sasanian) Empire (approximately
                        modern <placeName>Iraq</placeName> and Iran); 3. under
                        Arab rule; and 4. under Ottoman rule and in modern times.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>Times of persecution and of martyrdom fall into four main periods: 1. early
                        4th <abbr>cent.</abbr> (and again under Julian, 361–3), within the Roman Empire (<choice>
                            <sic>i.e.</sic>
                            <corr>i.e.,</corr>
                        </choice>
                        approximately Turkey, Syria, Lebanon, and Palestine); 2. mid-4th to mid-7th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr>, in the Persian (Sasanian) Empire (approximately modern Iraq and
                        Iran); 3. under Arab rule; and 4. under Ottoman rule and in modern times. It
                        is only from the first two periods that sizeable collections of ‘Martyr
                        Acts’ in Syriac are available. From both a literary and a historical point
                        of view these works can vary enormously in character: a few are brief
                        factual reports made more or less at the time; many more are later literary
                        reworkings which, even though they may sometimes be based on reliable
                        sources, have introduced imaginary dialogues between persecutor and
                        persecuted whose aim is to edify and give encouragement to those who read or
                        hear them; miraculous elements also tend to appear. In other martyr acts the
                        miraculous takes over on a large scale and they take on an epic
                        character.</p>
                    <p>Two groups of Syriac Martyr Acts from the Roman Empire are of especial
                        importance: <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Eusebius-of-Caesarea">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/480">Eusebius</persName>
                        </ref>’s Palestinian Martyrs, whose
                        complete form survives only in Syriac translation, and the various
                        martyrdoms associated with <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref>.</p>
                    <p>The Edessene martyrdoms fall into two distinct categories, historical and
                        legendary. The former concern the deacon Ḥabib and the laymen Shmona and
                        Gurya, who were martyred probably in 309 and 310; all three came from
                        villages around Edessa, but met their death in Edessa. Although the accounts
                        have been embellished with dialogues and miraculous elements, it is likely
                        that the basic information given is reasonably reliable. This cannot be said
                        concerning two other Edessan martyrdoms, the Acts of Sharbel and those of
                        Barsamya, which purport to be contemporary accounts of events that took
                        place under Trajan in 105: both can be shown to be fictional accounts put
                        out in the first half of the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> by circles in Edessa which also
                        produced the <choice>
                            <sic>
                                <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Addai-Teaching-of">Teaching of
                            Adda</ref>i</sic>
                            <corr>
                                <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Addai-Teaching-of">Teaching of
                                Addai</ref>
                            </corr>
                        </choice> and the legend of the city’s conversion.</p>
                    <p>Outside the Roman Empire it appears that there was no persecution of
                        Christians under the Parthian dynasty, which came to an end in 226. Under
                        the Sasanians (224–651) serious persecution first arose only after
                        Constantine and his successors had adopted Christianity; it is significant
                        that most of the outbreaks in the 4th and 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> were at times of war
                        with the Roman Empire. The persecution of the 340s under Shapur II was the
                        most widespread, and produced a large number of martyr acts, of varying
                        historical reliability. <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemon-bar-Sabbae">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/9">Shemʿon bar
                            Ṣabbaʿe</persName>
                        </ref>, <abbr>bp.</abbr> of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Seleucia-Ctesiphon">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/182">Seleucia-Ctesiphon</placeName>
                        </ref> (which was beginning to emerge as the
                        patriarchal see) was one of the first to be put to death (probably in 344).
                        The persecution extended to villages as well as to towns and included lay
                        people as well as clergy. Knowledge of these Persian martyrdoms reached the
                        Roman Empire by means of Greek translations and Sozomen’s account in his
                        Ecclesiastical History (II.9–14), as well as by word of mouth. A list of
                        these martyrs was given at the end of a <abbr>ms.</abbr> written in Edessa in November
                        411 (ms. Brit. Libr. Add. 12,150).</p>
                    <p>Subsequent persecutions again occurred in <abbr>ca.</abbr> 420 (at the end of the reign of
                        Yazdgard I and beginning of that of Bahram V), and <abbr>ca.</abbr> 445 (under Yazdgard
                        II), but on a much smaller scale; both were at times of hostilities with the
                        Roman Empire. Several accounts of the martyrdoms during these persecutions
                        survive, especially for the former (some of these are by a certain <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abgarids-of-Edessa">Abgar</ref>; there is also an account in <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoret-of-Cyrrhus">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/781">Theodoret</persName>
                        </ref>’s Ecclesiastical History, V, 39). Martyrdoms continue
                        to occur down to the end of the Sasanian Empire, but after the middle of the
                        5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> they are almost all confined to isolated cases of converts from
                        Zoroastrianism of noble birth. Several long accounts of these, often of
                        great historical interest, survive in both Syriac and Greek; these include
                        the Acts of Grigor (who managed to become a general after his conversion,
                        but was eventually martyred in 542), the learned <abbr>Cath. </abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aba">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/308">Aba</persName>
                        </ref> (540–552), two
                        women martyrs, Shirin (558/9) and Golindush/Mary (591), Giwargis (George)
                        and his sister Mary (613), Ishoʿsabran (620), and Mogundat/Anastasius (628)
                        whose martyr acts enjoyed great popularity in Greek and Latin.</p>
                    <p>The earliest and most detailed information about persecution and martyrdoms
                        in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nagran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/464">Nagran</placeName>
                        </ref>, in the South Arabian kingdom of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Himyar">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/474">Ḥimyar</placeName>
                        </ref>, comes from
                        three related Syriac texts, one of which is a Letter by <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemun-of-Beth-Arsham">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/53">Shemʿun of
                            Beth Arsham</persName>
                        </ref> written in 524, while subsequent Martyr Acts are in
                        Greek, Ethiopic, and other languages. The date of the persecution is not
                        certain: 518, 522, and 523 are the possibilities.</p>
                    <p>Several Martyr Acts survive from the early centuries of Arab rule, though
                        only a very few are written in Syriac, and these are incorporated into
                        Chronicles. Under the Umayyads there were only isolated martyrdoms and the
                        majority of martyrdoms took place under the early Abbasids, in particular
                        during the caliphates of al-Manṣūr (754–75) and al-Mahdī (775–85). Those
                        martyred fall into a number of different categories. Christian Arabs in
                        particular were under considerable pressure to convert to Islam, and a
                        number of those who resisted were put to death. Muslim converts to
                        Christianity, and Christians who had converted to Islam and then returned to
                        Christianity were in especial danger of martyrdom, and among the latter
                        category there are cases of Christians who had been captured as children and
                        then been brought up as Muslims, but who subsequently decided to return to
                        their original faith. Prisoners of war were sometimes forced to apostasize,
                        and those who refused were put to death (in some cases this was a matter of
                        reprisals). Non-Arab Christians living under Arab rule were (at least in the
                        earlier period) in less danger of suffering persecution and martyrdom unless
                        they openly provoked the authorities. In the following centuries persecution
                        tended to be intermittent and local, though none the less dire; this was
                        especially the case under the Mongol ruler Timur Lang (Timurlane) in the
                        14th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although later centuries (both under Ottoman rule and more recently, in the
                        20th and 21st <abbr>cent.</abbr>) have witnessed periods of persecution with many
                        martyrdoms in the Syriac and other Churches of the Middle East, the genre of
                        Martyr Acts seems to have largely died out in languages other than in Greek
                        (for which the <hi rend="italic">Neon Martyrologion</hi> provides many
                        examples from the Ottoman period). A notable martyr of this period was <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemun-II-Basileios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/291">Shemʿun II,</persName>
                        </ref> Mafryono of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tur-Abdin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/221">Ṭur ʿAbdin</placeName>
                        </ref>
                        (1740). Records, if they exist, of massacres and martyrdoms are primarily to
                        be found in the course of historical accounts and in poetry; this applies in
                        particular to the appalling massacres of 1895/6 and 1915 (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sayfo">Sayfo</ref>, the year of
                        the ‘Sword’), when all the Syriac communities suffered immense losses, as
                        well as the Armenians. Many of the victims were killed specifically because
                        they refused to deny their faith.</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/70">Fig. 70</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Primary Sources</head>
                            <listBibl>
                                <head>First Period</head>
                                <bibl>F. C.  Burkitt, <title rend="italic">Euphemia and the
                                        Goth</title> (1913). (Shmona, Gurya, Ḥabib)</bibl>
                                <bibl>W.  Cureton, <title rend="italic">History of the Martyrs of
                                        Palestine</title> (1861).</bibl>
                                <bibl>
                           <choice>
                              <reg>W.  Cureton</reg>
                              <orig>idem</orig>
                           </choice>, <title rend="italic">Ancient Syriac Documents</title>
                                    (1864). (Barsamya, Sharbel)</bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <listBibl>
                                <head>Second Period</head>
                                <bibl>Most of the Persian Martyr Acts were published by P. Bedjan in
                                    his <title rend="italic">Acta Martyrum et Sanctorum</title> (II
                                    and IV), and his <title rend="italic">Histoire de Mar Jab-Alaha,
                                        de trois autres Patriarches...</title> (1895; <abbr>repr.</abbr> 2007).
                                    Selected translations in O. Braun, <title rend="italic">Ausgewählte Akten persischer Märtyrer</title> (1915), and
                                    selected summaries in G.  Hoffmann, <title rend="italic">Auszüge
                                        aus syrischen Akten persischer Märtyrer</title> (1880). A
                                    guide to the 64 different texts, and to translations (where
                                    available) and further bibliography is given in the Appendix to
                                    S. P. Brock, <title rend="italic">The history of Mar Maʿin, with
                                        a guide to the Persian Martyr Acts</title> (2008).</bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <listBibl>
                                <head>Third Period</head>
                                <bibl>Accounts of persecutions and martyrdoms are to be found here
                                    and there in the various chronicles, notably the Zuqnin
                                    Chronicle (late 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>; see Harrak, under Secondary Sources)
                                    and that of Michael Rabo.</bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                            <listBibl>
                                <head>Fourth Period</head>
                                <bibl>Mor Julius Çiçek, <title rend="italic">Mimre d-ʿal
                                        Sayfe</title> (1981). (covering 1714–1914)</bibl>
                                <bibl>Shlemun Henno, <title rend="italic">Gunḥe d-Suryoye d-Ṭur
                                        ʿAbdin</title> (1987).</bibl>
                                <bibl>ʿAbdmshiḥo Naʿman d-Qarahbash, <title rend="italic">Dmo
                                        zliḥo</title> (1987, 1989; <abbr>GT</abbr> 2002).</bibl>
                                <bibl>Naʿman Aydin, <title rend="italic">Gedše w-šabṭe d-Ṭur
                                        ʿAbdin</title> (1997).</bibl>
                                <bibl>Asmar al-Khoury, <title rend="italic">Ṣulfoto qašyoto d-ʿal
                                        Suryoye</title> (1998).</bibl>
                            </listBibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>J. Bet-Şawoce, <title rend="italic">Sayfo b-Ţurʿabdin
                                    1914–1915</title> (2006).</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. P. Brock, ‘Christians in the Sasanid Empire: a case of divided
                                loyalties’, in <title rend="italic">Syriac Perspectives on Late
                                    Antiquity</title> (1984), ch. 6.</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. Devos, ‘Les martyrs persans à travers <choice>
                                    <sic>leur</sic>
                                    <corr>leurs</corr>
                                </choice> actes syriaques’, in
                                    <title rend="italic">La Persia e il mondo Greco-Romano</title>
                                (1966), 213–25.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.-M.  Fiey, ‘Martyrs sous les Ottomans’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>LM</abbr>
                                </title> 101 (1983), 387–406.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>J.-M.  Fiey</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Saints syriaques</title>.</bibl>
                            <bibl>D. Gaunt, <title rend="italic">Massacres, resistance, protectors.
                                    Muslim-Christian relations in Eastern Anatolia during World War
                                    I</title> (2006). (with further bibliography)</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Harrak, ‘Piecing together the fragmentary account of the
                                martyrdom of Cyrus of Harran’ [in the Zuqnin Chronicle], <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>AB</abbr>
                                </title> 121 (2003), 297–328.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. Walker, <title rend="italic">The Legend of Mar Qardagh</title>
                                (2006).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Wiessner, <title rend="italic">Zur Märtyrerüberlieferung aus
                                    der Christenverfolgung Schapurs II</title> (1967).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Yonan, <title rend="italic">Ein vergessener Holocaust. Die
                                    Vernichtung der christlichen Assyrer in der Turkei</title>
                                (1989).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Sebastian P.</forename> 
                  <surname>Brock</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
