<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Michael I Rabo</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Dorothea</forename> 
                  <surname>Weltecke</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Michael I Rabo</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Michael-I-Rabo</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/382</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">373</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="287-290"/>
                    <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/person/217</idno>
                    <note type="type">person</note>
                    <note type="abstract">
                        <abbr>Patr.</abbr> and historian, most notably of a World Chronicle.
                        <note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <ab type="infobox">(d. 1199) [<abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>]</ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>
                        <abbr>Patr.</abbr> and historian, most notably author of a World Chronicle. Michael I Rabo
                        (1126–99) was a distinguished <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> and a dominant figure in the
                        intellectual history of the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Church during the 12th <abbr>cent.</abbr> He was
                        renowned for his intrepid diplomacy, his rigorous legislation, and sanctions
                        in order to reform the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> ecclesiastical administration as a means
                        to enhance Christian autonomy. Michael was born in 1126 in a still largely
                        Christian <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Melitene">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/136">Melitene</placeName>
                        </ref>, where Greeks as well as <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> and Armenians lived
                        side by side with Muslims. Being a member of a clerical family, Michael was
                        sent to the nearby <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Barsawmo-Dayro-d-Mor">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/224">Dayro d-Mor
                            Barṣawmo</placeName>
                        </ref> for education. He stayed on as a monk and prior. In the
                        year 1166 Michael was elected <abbr>patr.</abbr> of the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> Church under the
                        pressure of a reform party among the bishops. In order to ensure his and his
                        flock’s interests and freedom of action Michael balanced out his relations
                        with the warring parties in the area of his jurisdiction. Especially in the
                        first half of his patriarchate his authority was felt and sought within the
                        entire group of non-Chalcedonian churches, Copts and Armenians included.
                        Michael was accepted as a frequent visitor in Latin <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Antioch">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/10">Antioch</placeName>
                        </ref> with the
                        consent of the Byzantine emperor Manuel Komnenos (1143–80) in spite of the
                        opposition of the Greek-orthodox community. In Antioch he was the first Syr.
                        Orth. <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>Patr.</sic>
                                <corr>patr.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> after the expulsion of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Severus-of-Antioch">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of
                            Antioch</persName>
                        </ref> (in 518) to act as <abbr>patr.</abbr> there and to consecrate a number
                        of bishops. He also visited <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Jerusalem">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>
                        </ref> several
                        times. Michael was invited to take part in the third Lateran Council in
                        1179, but declined.</p>
                    <p>The second half of his patriarchate was overshadowed by the election of an
                        anti-patriarch, named <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoros-bar-Wahbun">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/216">Theodoros
                            bar Wahbun</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 1193) in 1180, who was supported by the Latins in
                        the Crusader States as well as by the Armenian <abbr>Cath.</abbr> Gregory IV (1173–93).
                        Apart from a rapprochement between Michael and the Seljuk Sultan Qilij
                        Arslan II (1155–92), this led to some temporary diplomatic isolation until
                        1193, when Michael was fully recognized again by his church as well as by
                        his Christian neighbors. Michael was buried in his newly-built church in Mor
                        Barṣawmo.</p>
                    <p>Michael’s writing was largely concentrated on the reform project. Parallel to
                        his numerous obligations as a <abbr>patr.</abbr>, he collected <abbr>mss.</abbr> of theological and
                        historical content and restored and compiled hagiographical and liturgical
                        works. His canonistic work is partly conserved in later collections, but the
                        greater part is lost, as is his treatise on dualist heresies composed for
                        the Lateran Council. He also composed some liturgical and hagiographical
                        works and collected ancient theological and historical sources.</p>
                    <p>These he used for his monumental world chronicle from the origin of the world
                        to 1195. Michael’s chronicle has been studied intensively since its edition
                        and translation by J.-B Chabot. Inspired by the works of <abbr>
                            <choice>
                                <sic>bp.</sic>
                                <corr>Bp.</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </abbr> 
                  <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Edessa">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/113">Yaʿqub of Edessa</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 708) and <abbr>Patr. </abbr>
                        <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysios-of-Tel-Mahre">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/155">Dionysios
                            of Tel Maḥre</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 845), Michael’s chronicle blended both Eusebian
                        genres, the chronological tables and the narrative ecclesiastical history.
                        Michael used chronographies and ecclesiastical histories as sources and
                        added further material. Only part of these he had directly before his eyes;
                        others he used through intermediaries, as he reveals himself. Michael
                        related his own time from a well informed and independent point of view. In
                        view of source-critical methods and the universality of the chronological
                        scope the highest standard in <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> chronography was reached with this
                        chronicle. Michael intended his work for learned clerical readers with
                        access to a well-stocked library.</p>
                    <p>The text is not preserved in its entirety, and the layout of Michael’s
                        chronicle was distorted through the process of copying. Chabot’s edition is
                        a facsimile of a documentary copy written for him in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref> (Urfa) from
                        1897 to 1899. While the scribes tried to imitate the layout, a number of
                        mistakes were introduced. Its <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi>, the only
                        extant <abbr>ms.</abbr>, was written in 1598 by a very competent scribe. It is kept by
                        the community of the Edessenians in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aleppo">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/18">Aleppo</placeName>
                        </ref>. In view of
                        the loss of the original, this beautiful manuscript is the best witness for
                        the layout of the chronicle. Fortunately it will soon be made available in
                        print. This <abbr>ms.</abbr> was probably the <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> for an
                        Arabic translation, which also sought to preserve some of the visual
                        features, while changing others. The Arabic translation has much the same
                        lacunae as the Syriac text. By comparing his version with the Arabic
                        translation preserved in <abbr>ms.</abbr> London, Brit. Libr. Or. 4402 (which is one of
                        several Arabic copies), Chabot detected some details lost in the Syriac
                        text. No further research has been done so far on this problem.</p>
                    <p>The historical material was originally organized in four columns, the first
                        being designated as the ‘succession of the patriarchs’, the second as
                        ‘succession of the kings’, the chronological canon as ‘computation of the
                        years’. No title of the additional column, which contains mixed material, is
                        now known. Chapters with excursus were inserted, which interrupted the
                        system of columns. After an open and abrupt end, six appendices follow. The
                        first appendix is a monumental synopsis of all the kings and patriarchs
                        mentioned. It was supposed to function as a directory. The second appendix
                        is a treatise on the historical identity of the Syrians, who are connected
                        to the Ancient Oriental Empires, the Assyrians, the Babylonians, and the
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Arameans">Arameans</ref>. When the chronicle was translated into Armenian, in two
                        different translations, in 1246 and 1247, it was transformed according to
                        Armenian interests.</p>
                    <p>Michael’s chronicle was motivated by a strong cognitive interest in
                        historical and chronological knowledge. It also examines the historical role
                        of the <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr> as a cultural-ethnic group as well as a church on the one
                        hand with respect to God’s plan of salvation and on the other the universal
                        reality of historical change and contingency.</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/75">Fig. 75</ref> and <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/76c">76c</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Primary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>Chabot, <title rend="italic">Chronique de Michel le
                                Syrien</title>, I–V. (Syr. with <abbr>FT</abbr>)</bibl>
                            <bibl>G.  Kiraz (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Texts and translations of
                                    the Chronicle of Michael the Syrian</title> (2009–). (a
                                multi-volume series that includes a <abbr>repr.</abbr> of Chabot’s edition and
                                translation, and a facsimile edition of the Aleppo <abbr>ms.</abbr>)</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>R. Abramowski, <title rend="italic">Dionysius von Tellmahre.
                                    Jakobitischer Patriarch von 818–845. Zur Geschichte der Kirche
                                    unter dem Islam</title> (1940).</bibl>
                            <bibl>L. P.  Bernhard, ‘Die Universalgeschichtsschreibung des
                                christlichen Orients’, in <title rend="italic">Mensch und
                                    Weltgeschichte. Zur Geschichte der
                                    Universalgeschichtsschreibung</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A.  Randa (1969),
                                111–141.</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. P.  Brock, ‘Syriac historical writing: A survey of the main
                                sources’, <title rend="italic">Journal of the Iraqi Academy. Syriac
                                    Corporation</title> 5 (1978–80), 1–30. (<abbr>repr.</abbr> in <title rend="italic">Studies in Syriac Christianity</title> [1992], ch.
                                I)</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  van Ginkel, ‘Michael the Syrian and his sources’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>JCSSS</abbr>
                                </title> 6 (2006), 53–60.</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Schmidt, ‘Die zweifache armenische Rezension der syrischen
                                Chronik Michaels des Großen’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>LM</abbr>
                                </title> 109
                                (1996), 299–319.</bibl>
                            <bibl>Weltecke, <title rend="italic">Die «Beschreibung der
                                    Zeiten»</title>.</bibl>
                            <bibl>W.  Witakowski, <title rend="italic">The Syriac Chronicle of
                                    Pseudo-Dionysius of Tel-Maḥrē. A Study in the History of
                                    <choice>
                                        <sic>Histiography</sic>
                                        <corr>Historiography</corr>
                                    </choice>
                                </title> (1987).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>W.  Witakowski</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘The Chronicle of Eusebius: Its Type and Continuation in
                                Syriac Historiography’, <title rend="italic">ARAM</title> 11–12
                                (1999–2000), 419–37.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Dorothea</forename> 
                  <surname>Weltecke</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
