<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Mūsā al-Ḥabashī, Dayr Mār</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Erica Cruikshank</forename> 
                  <surname>Dodd</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Mūsā al-Ḥabashī, Dayr Mār</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Musa-al-Habashi-Dayr-Mar</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/392</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">383</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="296-300"/>
                    <idno type="althead" subtype="altorder">Dayr Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashī</idno>
                    <idno type="subject">http://syriaca.org/place/228</idno>
                    <note type="type">place</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Monastery of Moses the Ethiopian, perched on top of
                        a steep, rocky promontory south of Nabk.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <ab type="infobox">[formerly <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>, now Syr. Catholic]</ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The Monastery of Moses the Ethiopian is perched on top of a steep, rocky
                        promontory that juts out of a deep gully between two cliffs in the high
                        region south of Nabk. The earliest historical reference to the monastery is
                        in a hand-written note beside a text of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/John-Chrysostom">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/573">John
                            Chrysostom</persName>
                        </ref> on the Gospel of Matthew, in a 6th-cent. <abbr>ms.</abbr> preserved
                        in the British Library. A second note in the same <abbr>ms.</abbr> states that this
                        volume was ‘the property of the convent of Mushe, on the hill called “the
                        Great Head,” east of Natpha, in the province of Damascus’. The subsequent
                        history of the monastery is closely documented by numerous inscriptions
                        within the church, and by <abbr>mss.</abbr> that once belonged to its flourishing
                        scriptorium. Until the end of the 14th <abbr>cent.</abbr> it was the seat of a bishopric
                        that later fell under the jurisdiction of Ḥama and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mardin">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/130">Mardin</placeName>
                        </ref>, and then
                        under the bishopric of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Jerusalem">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>
                        </ref> and
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Damascus">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/66">Damascus</placeName>
                        </ref> (Kaufhold).</p>
                    <p>The monastery prospered well into the 18th <abbr>cent.</abbr> and was recorded by both
                        Burton and Moritz late in the 19th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, but some time thereafter was
                        totally abandoned and fell into ruin. The fortress-like building was
                        approached through a small door on the top floor, from where it was built
                        four stories down; but when discovered again in 1981, the lower floors had
                        all caved in and the upper terrace had only one room that sheltered sheep.
                        At that time the chapel was still preserved, its walls decorated with
                        falling, painted stucco but the roof and the ciborium were gone, burned for
                        firewood. A young Jesuit, Father Paolo dall’Oglio, an Orientalist by
                        training, visited the site and decided to restore the monastery to its
                        former state. With great care to reproduce its original plan and
                        accoutrements, and with the help of local teams of Christian volunteers from
                        Syria and Iraq, with experts in the Department of Antiquities in Damascus,
                        and the Istituto del Restauro in Rome, Father Paolo cleared the lower rooms
                        and rebuilt the upper stories and the chapel. In subsequent years he dug a
                        well, added outlying buildings, and established a new order for the
                        monastery. He now presides over a small group of monks, nuns, and novitiates
                        in a religious center dedicated to serving the surrounding community of
                        Christians and Muslims and to promoting a dialogue between them. The
                        monastery receives daily a great number of visitors, both Christian and
                        Muslim.</p>
                    <p>For as long as the inhabitants of Nabk can remember, the monastery has been
                        known as Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashī (St. Moses the Ethiopian), but, according to
                        the inscriptions and to the <abbr>mss.</abbr>, it was originally dedicated to Mār Mūsā
                        the Prophet (St. Moses the Prophet). The earliest reference to Moses the
                        Ethiopian comes from the 17th <abbr>cent.</abbr> It is possible that this saint became
                        associated with the monastery on the arrival of a number of Abyssinian monks
                        in the 15th <abbr>cent.</abbr> (Cruikshank Dodd). These monks from Mar Girgios al-Ḥabash,
                        in Ehden, and Mar Yaʿqub al-Ḥabash in Bsharre, were evicted from the Qadisha
                        valley by the Maronites in 1488. In this case the change of name from Mār
                        Mūsā, to Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabash (of the Ethiopians), to Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashi (the
                        Ethiopian) might have come about naturally in the process of time. A hand
                        encased in a silver casket purporting to be the hand of Mar Moses the
                        Ethiopian is inscribed as a donation to the monastery by <abbr>Bp.</abbr> Eliya in 1817
                        and is now preserved in the Church of the Virgin, in Nabk. The <abbr>Syr. Orth.</abbr>
                        Christians of Nabk celebrate the feast of Moses the Ethiopian on 28 Aug. In
                        the Greek Church his feast day is 18 June.</p>
                    <p>The various stages in the monastery’s long history are recorded in
                        inscriptions. Those carved in the building stones indicate that the church
                        was rebuilt and renovated in A.H. 504 (= AD 1058/1059). Subsequently, it was
                        enlarged and turned into a fortress in the 15th <abbr>cent.</abbr> and restored again in
                        the 16th. Inscriptions painted on the wall paintings identify the figures
                        and scenes. Earlier layers of painting are inscribed in Greek, whereas the
                        top layer for the most part uses Syriac. There are also dedications and
                        memorials written on the paintings themselves by various visitors to the
                        monastery, in Syriac and in Arabic, that contribute to the history of the
                        monastery (Tweir, Haddad, Muwazzin, ter Haar Romeny et <choice>
                            <sic>al</sic>
                            <corr>al.</corr>
                        </choice>).</p>
                    <p>With this long and fascinating history, the chapel in Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashī
                        also preserves until today the most extensive series of paintings to have
                        come down to us from the whole of the Levant (Cruikshank Dodd, Dall’Oglio,
                        Westphalen, Immerzeel). The chapel is unique in that it shows a
                        well-documented, coherent series of paintings from more than one period,
                        paintings that are indispensable for the study of medieval Christian
                        art.</p>
                    <p>There are three (or three and a half) principal layers of painting, applied
                        at three different periods (Westphalen). The first, or earliest layer of
                        paintings (layer 1), can be dated to the 11th <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        <abbr> ca.</abbr> 1060, soon after the
                        first renovations to the church, to which more wall paintings were added a
                        few years later (1a), at some time before 1095. Another layer (2) is dated
                        by an inscription on the Baptismal scene to 1095. The latest series (3) is
                        the most extensive and best preserved. The date of the third layer is
                        recorded in an inscription over a painting of the Evangelist Matthew, and it
                        may be read as either 1192 (assuming that the Seleucid calendar is
                        followed), or 1208/9 (if it is taken as a Hijra year), a distinction which
                        is, unfortunately, not clear in the original.</p>
                    <p>The interior of the chapel was elaborately painted when it was first restored
                        in 1058/9. Beneath the more recent remains of the third layer, there is a
                        bust of Christ on the triumphal arch with what appear to be archangels at
                        either side. Above these figures there may have been painted the Forty
                        Martyrs of Sebaste (Immerzeel). An Annunciation was placed on either side of
                        the window. The riding saints, Theodore and George, appear opposite each
                        other on the spandrels of the arches in the nave, where also the remains of
                        a second pair may be traced from this early date. Still in the nave, on the
                        southern spandrel nearest to the apse is the Ascension of Elijah in his
                        Chariot. In the southern aisle, west end, an early representation of the
                        Presentation in the Temple (?) is balanced by a group of apostles, probably
                        the Pentecost, at the west end of the northern aisle. In the southern aisle,
                        an image of Samson and the Lion is painted high above the western arch. At
                        the east end, there may have been an early Baptism in the northern aisle and
                        an early Myrophores (Three Women at the Tomb) in the southern aisle. The
                        columns and the soffits of the arches are decorated with standing saints and
                        martyrs, both male and female most of whom were added shortly after this
                        first layer (period 1a).</p>
                    <p>Layer 2 (1095) comprises a large Baptism, painted over the earlier Baptism at
                        the eastern end of the northern aisle, and a renewed Myrophores painted over
                        the earlier one in the southern aisle. A stylite Saint (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Shemun-the-Stylite">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/744">Shemʿun the
                            Stylite</persName>
                        </ref>?) stands beside the Baptism. At the western end of the
                        southern aisle is a renewed Presentation in the Temple.</p>
                    <p>Most of the extant paintings belong to layer three, the last layer of paint,
                        1192 or 1208/9. They present the most coherent series of paintings to have
                        come down to us in the Syriac churches. The triumphal arch, high up under
                        the eaves, is decorated with Christ Emmanuel and an Annunciation, below
                        which is the Christ Pantocrator between the figures of twelve standing
                        apostles that spill into the nave. In the apse was a Deesis (now largely
                        destroyed) with the Christ on a throne surrounded by the four beasts of the
                        Apocalypse. Below them, in the bema, the standing Virgin Blachernitissa
                        between standing Church Fathers: <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Cyril-of-Alexandria">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/430">Cyril of
                            Alexandria</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Basil-of-Caesarea">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/376">Basil</persName>
                        </ref>, <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Athanasius-of-Alexandria">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/354">Athanasius</persName>
                        </ref>, and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/John-Chrysostom">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/573">John
                            Chrysostom</persName>
                        </ref>, on her right<choice>
                            <sic>.</sic>
                            <corr/>
                        </choice>; and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ignatius-of-Antioch">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/544">Ignatius</persName>
                        </ref>,
                        James, and two others (destroyed) on her left. On the iconastasis there are
                        painted the five wise and five foolish virgins. Four large riding horsemen,
                        George and Theodore, Bacchos and Sergios charge down the nave, above the
                        arches, towards the apse. The remains of two other riding saints are visible
                        nearer the apse, making six in all. Four evangelists writing their gospels
                        fill the spandrels. On the western wall is a great Last Judgment above which
                        is the <hi rend="italic">Traditio clavium</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Traditio Legis</hi>, of which only the lower part of Peter and Paul
                        remain. Below them the remaining ten Apostles are seated on either side of a
                        Hetoimasia between Adam and Eve. On the one side, below the apostles, are
                        the three patriarchs, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, together with Mary, holding
                        bunches of souls in their laps. Beneath them are the saints, martyrs and
                        holy men ascending from their tombs to heaven at the blast of trumpeting
                        angels. On the other side of the Hetoimasia stand heretical bishops and
                        various groups of enemies of the orthodox churches, along with Satan seated
                        among souls drowning in the waters of the Styx, a devil holding down the
                        scales, and below them are naked women symbolizing the seven sins. The Last
                        Judgment spills over onto the walls of the nave.</p>
                    <p>Among these impressive scenes, the walls and the piers in Mār Mūsā are
                        painted with numerous figures of standing saints and martyrs, including John
                        the Baptist and Saba, Euthymios and Anthony (?). The soffits of the arches
                        are reserved for female saints, among them: Anastasia, Catherine, Barbara,
                        Elizabeth, and Julia (Juliana).</p>
                    <p>These paintings are evidence of a continuing tradition of Christian painting
                        in lands dominated by Muslim rulers. In their iconography, they kept alive
                        the painterly tradition of the Early Christian Church and also followed
                        closely Byzantine innovations from Constantinople. In the 12th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, some
                        iconographic elements were imported from Crusader <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Jerusalem">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/104">Jerusalem</placeName>
                        </ref>. In
                        their style, each of the layers of paint demonstrate a stylistic tradition
                        in East Christian art that was aware of and sensitive to regional
                        developments in Lebanon, Cyprus, Egypt, Iraq and Cappadocia. The painters
                        were local Syrians who were also influenced by contemporary Islamic art in
                        the region. On the whole, the paintings of Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashī remain the
                        richest illustration of East Christian art preserved until today.</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/85c">Fig. 85c</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/86">86</ref>, <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/87">87</ref>, and <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/88c">88c</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>A.  Badwi, ‘The wall paintings of Mount Lebanon’, in <title rend="italic">Documentation and Conservation of Art in Syria. Papers
                                of the Workshop held at Damascus University, 16–19 September,
                                1996</title> (2000), 61–8.</bibl>
                        <bibl>E.  Cruikshank  Dodd, <title rend="italic">The frescoes of Mar Musa
                                al-Habashi. A study in medieval painting in Syria</title> (Studies
                            and Texts 139; 2001).</bibl>
                        <bibl>eadem, <title rend="italic">Medieval Painting in the Lebanon</title>
                            (2004).</bibl>
                        <bibl>P.  Dall’Oglio <abbr>et al.</abbr>, <title rend="italic">Il restauro del monastero
                                di San Mosè l’Abassino, Nebek, Siria</title> (1998).</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Folda, <title rend="italic">The art of the crusaders in the Holy
                                Land, 1098–1187</title> (1995).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J.  Folda</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Crusader Art in the Holy Land. From the
                                Third Crusade to the Fall of Acre</title> (2005).</bibl>
                        <bibl>B. ter Haar Romeny <abbr>et al.</abbr>, ‘The wall paintings and inscriptions of
                            Deir Mar Musa al-Habashi’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 4 (2007),
                            95–188.</bibl>
                        <bibl>N. Hélou, ‘L’icône bilaterale de la Vierge de Kaftoun au Liban: Une
                            œuvre d’art syro-byzantin à l’époque des Croisés’, <title rend="italic">Chronos. Revue d’Histoire de l’<choice>
                                    <sic>Univerité</sic>
                                    <corr>Université</corr>
                                </choice> de Balamand</title> 7
                            (2003), 101–30.</bibl>
                        <bibl>eadem, ‘À propos d’une école syro-libanaise d’icônes au XIII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title>
                            3 (2006), 53–72.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.-A. Hunt, ‘Christian art in Greater Syria and Egypt: A triptych of
                            the Ascension with Military Saints reattributed’, <title rend="italic">Al-Masāq</title> 12 (2000), 1–36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>eadem,   ‘A Woman’s Prayer to St. Sergios in Latin Syria. Interpreting
                            a thirteenth-century icon at Mount Sinai’, <title rend="italic">Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies</title> 15 (1991) 96–145. (<abbr>repr.</abbr>
                            in <title rend="italic">Byzantium, Eastern Christendom and Islam. Art at
                                the crossroads of the medieval Mediterranean</title>, vol. 2 [2000],
                            78–126)</bibl>
                        <bibl>M.  Immerzeel, ‘Le saint cavalier de Deir Saydet Hamatour’, <title rend="italic">Tempora. Annales d’histoire et d’archéologie</title>
                            14–15 (2003–2004), 175–85.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>M.  Immerzeel</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>   ‘Medieval wall paintings in Lebanon: Donors and artists’,
                                <title rend="italic">Chronos. Revue d’Histoire de l’Université de
                                Balamand</title> 10 (2004), 7–47.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>M.  Immerzeel</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘The wall paintings in the Church of Mar Elian at Homs: A
                            ‘restoration project’ of a nineteenth-century Palestinian master’,
                                <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 2 (2005), 149–65.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>M.  Immerzeel</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Monasteries and Churches of the Qalamun (Syria): Art and
                            pilgrimage in the Middle Ages’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JCSSS</abbr>
                            </title> 7
                            (2007), 74–98.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>M.  Immerzeel</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘The Monastery of Our Lady of Saydnaya and its icon’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 4 (2007), 13–26.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>M.  Immerzeel</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Identity Puzzles. Medieval Christian art in
                                Syria and Lebanon</title> (<abbr>OLA</abbr> 184; 2009).</bibl>
                        <bibl>K.  Innemée and M.  Immerzeel, ‘The Chapel of the Prophet Elijah near
                            Maʿarrat Saydnaya (Syria) and its mural paintings,’ <title rend="italic">Al-Masāq</title> 12 (2000), 69–97.</bibl>
                        <bibl>H.  Kaufhold, ‘Notizen über das Moseskloster bei Nabk und das
                            Julianskloster bei Qaryatain in Syrien’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>OC</abbr>
                            </title> 79 (1995), 48–119.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Lassus, <title rend="italic">Sanctuaires chrétiens de
                            Syrie</title> (1947), 299–301, fig. 109.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Leroy, <title rend="italic">Les manuscrits syriaques à peintures
                                conservés dans les bibliothèques d’Europe et d’Orient. Contribution
                                à l’étude de l’iconographie des églises de langue syriaque</title>
                            (Institut français d’archéologie de Beyrouth. Bibliothèque archéologique
                            et historique 77; 1964).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J.  Leroy</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>  ‘La renaissance de l’église syriaque au XII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>–XIII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
                            siècles’, in <title rend="italic">Cahiers de civilisation
                                médiévale</title> 14 (1971), 131–48, 239–255.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J.  Leroy</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Découvertes de peintures chrétiennes en Syrie’, <title rend="italic">Annales archéologiques arabes syriennes</title> 25
                            (1975), 95–113.</bibl>
                        <bibl>M.  Mundell, ‘Monophysite Church decoration’, in <title rend="italic">Iconoclasm. Papers given at the ninth Spring Symposium of Byzantine
                                Studies</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> A.  Bryer and J. Herrin (1977), 59–74.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Nasrallah, ‘Le couvent de Saint Moîse l’Ethiopien dans le Djebel
                            Kalamoun (Syrie)’, in <title rend="italic">Étape. Revue de la France
                                Libre</title> (1941).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J.  Nasrallah</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘La peinture monumentale des patriarchats Melkites’, in <title rend="italic">
                                <choice>
                                    <sic>Ikones</sic>
                                    <corr>Icônes</corr>
                                </choice> Melkites, Exposition organisée par le Musée
                            Nicolas Sursock, 16 mai <choice>
                                    <sic>-</sic>
                                    <corr>–</corr>
                                </choice> 15 <choice>
                                    <sic>Juin</sic>
                                    <corr>juin</corr>
                                </choice>, 1969</title> (1969), 67–98.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.  Nordiguian, ‘Une chapelle peinte à Kfar Chlaïmane dans le
                            haut-pays de Batroun’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>MUSJ</abbr>
                            </title> 54 (1995–6),
                            97–116.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Nordiguian</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘La chapelle peinte de Saydet Hamatour dans le Koura’, <title rend="italic">Chronos. Revue d’Histoire de l’Université de
                                Balamand</title> 1 (1998), 67–89.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Nordiguian</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Note sur deux fragments de peinture à Saydet Kharayeb de Kfar
                            Helda’, <title rend="italic">Tempora. Annales d’histoire et
                                d’archéologie</title> 14–15 (2003–2004), 187–92.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>L.  Nordiguian</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Une vision de Saint Eustathe au Liban’, <title rend="italic">Tempora. Annales d’histoire et d’archéologie</title> 16–17
                            (2005–6), 163–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>L.  Nordiguian and J.-C.  Voisin, <title rend="italic">Châteaux et
                                églises du moyen âge au Liban</title> (1999).</bibl>
                        <bibl>Y.  Sader, <title rend="italic">Peintures murales dans les églises
                                médiévales du Liban</title> (1987).</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>Y.  Sader</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Painted churches and rock-cut chapels of
                                Lebanon</title> (1997).</bibl>
                        <bibl>A. Schmidt and S. Westphalen (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Christliche
                                Wandmalereien in Syrien. Qara und das Kloster Mar Yakub</title>
                            (<abbr>SKCO</abbr> 14; 2005).</bibl>
                        <bibl>B. Snelders, ‘A newly discovered wall painting in the Church of Mar
                            Giworgis in Qaraqosh, Iraq’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ECA</abbr>
                            </title> 4 (2007),
                            27–48.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. Westphalen, ‘Wandmalereien in syrischen und libanesischen Kirchen.
                            Aspekte christlicher Kunst im Orient vom 11.–13. <choice>
                                <sic>Jahhundert</sic>
                                <corr>Jahrhundert</corr>
                            </choice>’, <title rend="italic">Antike Welt</title> 31.5 (2000), 487–502.</bibl>
                        <bibl>M. Zibawi, <title rend="italic">Orients chrétiens</title>
                            (1996).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Erica Cruikshank</forename> 
                  <surname>Dodd</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
