<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Old Syriac documents</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Aaron M.</forename> 
                  <surname>Butts</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.0">Electronic Edition Draft Version 1.0</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Old Syriac documents</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Old-Syriac-documents</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/416</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">407</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="314-317"/>
                    <note type="type">subject</note>
                    <note type="abstract">Several parchments from the third century were found in Dura Europos.
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syriac-Language"> Syriac language</ref> is best known from the large
                        corpus of Christian literature that began to be produced by the <choice>
                            <sic>2nd-cent.</sic>
                            <corr>2nd cent.</corr>
                        </choice>
                        and continues to be composed until the present day. Syriac is, however, also
                        attested in a much smaller corpus of non-Christian documentary texts that
                        date from the 1st to the 3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr> These texts are traditionally termed ‘Old
                        Syriac’. The largest group of Old Syriac texts are <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Inscriptions">inscriptions</ref>, which number over 100 (<abbr>ed.</abbr> Drijvers and Healey). In
                        addition to the Old Syriac inscriptions, there are also the Old Syriac
                        documents, which include three Syriac parchments as well as several Syriac
                        texts found on (primarily) Greek documents from the Middle Euphrates
                        region.</p>
                    <p>The first of the Old Syriac parchments was discovered in 1933 during
                        excavations of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dura-Europos">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/77">Dura-Europos</placeName>
                        </ref>,
                        an important military outpost for the Parthian Empire and then the Roman
                        Empire on the Euphrates. This document, which is now known as P. Dura 28, is
                        a bill of sale for a female slave dated 9 May 243 (the most accessible
                        version of the text is in Drijvers and Healey, 232–6 [s.v. P1]; but see also
                        Bellinger and Welles; Goldstein; Healey 2009, 264–75 [with plate 9]; Torrey;
                        Welles, Fink, and Gilliam, 142–9 [with pl. LXIX, LXXI]; plates are also
                        found in Moller, 185–6). In addition to this Syriac parchment, more than 150
                        other documents were found at Dura-Europos, most of which are in Greek or
                        Latin though there are also a few in Iranian or Aramaic (<abbr>ed.</abbr> Welles, Fink,
                        and Gilliam). For more than fifty years, P. Dura 28 was without parallel,
                        but in 1988 two similar Old Syriac parchments, now known as P.  Euphrates 19
                        and 20, came to light. Though not found in controlled excavations, it is
                        likely that both of these documents originate from Appadana (Neapolis), just
                        north of Dura-Europos on the Euphrates. P. Euphrates 19 is a transfer of
                        debt dated 28 Dec. 240 (the most accessible version of the text is in
                        Drijvers and Healey, 237–42 [s.v. P2], but see also Teixidor 1989, 220;
                        1990, 144–54 [includes two plates]; Brock; Aggoula; Healey 2008; 2009,
                        252–64 [with plate 8]). P. Euphrates  20 is a property lease dated 1 Sept.
                        242 (the most accessible version of the text is in Drijvers and Healey,
                        243–8 [s.v. P3]; see also Teixidor 1989; 1990, 154–57; 1991–1992 [includes
                        two plates]; Brock; Aggoula). These two Syriac parchments belong to a cache
                        of texts that also includes 19 Greek papyri and parchments (<abbr>ed.</abbr> Feissel and
                        Gascou [and Teixidor]). On several of these Greek texts, there is additional
                        writing in Syriac. P. Euphrates 6 (with its duplicate P. Euphrates 7), for
                        instance, contains a bill of sale for a slave in Greek, which is followed by
                        seven lines of Syriac summarizing the sale as well as a list of witnesses
                        and guarantors (verso), both in Syriac. In addition, a Syriac subscription
                        occurs on two of the Greek papyri, viz. P. Euphrates 3 and its duplicate P.
                        Euphrates 4. This subscription is the earliest witness to the use of Syriac
                        on papyrus (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Papyri-Syriac">Papyri,
                            Syriac</ref>).</p>
                    <p>Since their discovery, the Old Syriac documents have proven important on a
                        number of fronts. In both their content and form they have added to the
                        growing body of data for the Aramaic legal tradition. The three Old Syriac
                        parchments are of the <hi rend="italic">Doppelurkunde-</hi>type, in which
                        the main text is presented on the lower portion of the parchment and an
                        abbreviated summary occurs on the top. This top section would have
                        originally been rolled up and sealed in order to prevent tampering. This
                        practice is well attested both in Greek and Aramaic papyrology, and it may
                        have antecedents in the cuneiform tradition where tablets were enclosed in
                        clay envelopes. The legal terminology in the Old Syriac parchments also
                        points to continuity with other Aramaic legal texts, such as the Elephantine
                        papyri, the Samaria Papyri, the Nabataean papyri, and the Jewish legal texts
                        from the Judaean desert and the ‘Cave of Letters’ in Naḥal Ḥever (see Healey
                        2005). In P. Dura 28, for instance, it is stated: ‘From today until forever,
                        you, Tiro, the buyer, and your heirs will have authority (<hi rend="italic">šlyṭ</hi>) over this female slave whom I have sold to you, to possess
                        or to sell or to do with her whatever you wish (<hi rend="italic">kl
                            d-tṣbʾ</hi>)’ (ln. 11–12). This type of statement — commonly called a
                            <hi rend="italic">Kyrieia</hi>-clause  — is found throughout the Aramaic
                        legal tradition, as well as in Greek papyri.</p>
                    <p>The dating formulae in the Old Syriac documents <choice>
                            <sic>has</sic>
                            <corr>have</corr>
                        </choice> provided valuable
                        information for the chronology of the last kings of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref> (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abgarids-of-Edessa">Abgarids</ref>). P. Dura 28 shows that the Abgarid dynasty
                        must have come to an end in 212/213 when the city became a Roman <hi rend="italic">colonia</hi>. On the basis of P. Euphrates 19, which
                        states that 28 Dec. 240 is the 2nd year of king Abgar, it can be established
                        that the dynasty was restored in 239 (or late 238) under Abgar X, son of
                        Maʿnu. Finally, it seems that Edessa must have reverted to a <hi rend="italic">colonia</hi> by 242 on the basis of P. Euphrates 20, which
                        gives 1 Sept. 242 as year 30 of the <hi rend="italic">colonia</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Old Syriac documents are also an important witness to an early stage of
                        the Syriac language. The <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Script-Syriac">script</ref> of the Old Syriac
                        documents is not the monumental Esṭrangela that is found in most of the Old
                        Syriac inscriptions and the oldest Syriac literary <abbr>mss.</abbr>, but rather it is of
                        a more cursive type (especially in P. Euphrates 20) that also occurs in some
                        mosaic inscriptions. These documents, thus, corroborate the existence of a
                        cursive script, which was used alongside Esṭrangela already in the earliest
                        period of Syriac and which would later develop into Serṭo (see Healey 2000).
                        In orthography, the Old Syriac documents have features in common with the
                        Old Syriac inscriptions, but different from Classical Syriac, e.g. the
                        defective writing of historical short *<hi rend="italic">u</hi> (e.g. <hi rend="italic">ḥšbn</hi> ‘reckoning’) versus the plene writing with a <hi rend="italic">mater lectionis</hi> in Classical Syriac (e.g. <hi rend="italic">ḥwšbn</hi>) and the representation of the etymological
                        lateral *<hi rend="italic">ɬ</hi> (= traditional <hi rend="italic">ś</hi>)
                        with <hi rend="italic">š</hi> (e.g. <hi rend="italic">ʿšryn</hi> ‘twenty’)
                        versus <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in Classical Syriac (e.g. <hi rend="italic">ʿsryn</hi>). In one important diagnostic feature, however, the Old
                        Syriac documents differ from most of the Old Syriac inscriptions in
                        agreement with Classical Syriac: the prefix marker of the 3rd-person
                        masculine prefix-conjugation is <hi rend="italic">y</hi> in most of the Old
                        Syriac inscriptions, but <hi rend="italic">n</hi> in both the Old Syriac
                        documents and Classical Syriac. This shows that there was already linguistic
                        variation in Old Syriac (see recently Healey 2008). Finally, the Old Syriac
                        documents provide evidence for Syriac-Greek language contact already in the
                        middle of the 3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr> as there are a relatively large number of Greek
                        lexical borrowings (20 types that occur more than 50 times) in the
                        documents, several of which show a significant degree of incorporation into
                        the Syriac language, e.g. <hi rend="italic">ʾsṭrṭgwtʾ </hi>‘strategos-ship’
                        (&lt; Greek <hi rend="italic">stratēgós</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">ʾrkwnwtʾ</hi> ‘archon-ship’ (&lt; Greek <hi rend="italic">árchōn</hi>).</p>
                    <p>See <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/1">Fig. 1</ref> and <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/94">94</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>B.  Aggoula, ‘Studia Aramaica III’, <title rend="italic">Syria</title> 59 (1992), 391–422, esp. 391–9.</bibl>
                        <bibl>A. R.  Bellinger and C. B.  Welles, ‘A third-century contract of sale
                            from Edessa in Osrhoene’, <title rend="italic">Yale Classical
                                Studies</title> 5 (1935), 95–154 with plates I–III.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. P.  Brock, ‘Some new Syriac documents from the third century AD’,
                                <title rend="italic">ARAM</title> 3 (1991), 259–67.</bibl>
                        <bibl>H. M.  Cotton, W. E. H.  Cockle, and F. G. B.  Millar, ‘The papyrology
                            of the Roman near East: A survey’, <title rend="italic">The Journal of
                                Roman Studies</title> 85 (1995), 214–35. (provides a useful checklist
                            of texts)</bibl>
                        <bibl>Drijvers and Healey, <title rend="italic">The Old Syriac
                                inscriptions</title>.</bibl>
                        <bibl>D.  Feissel and J.  Gascou, ‘Documents d’archives romains inédits du
                            Moyen-Euphrate (III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle après J.-C.)’,
                                <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>CRAIBL</abbr>
                            </title> 1989, 535–61.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>D.  Feissel and J.  Gascou</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Documents d’archives romains inédits du Moyen Euphrate (III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> s. après J.-C.). I. Les pétitions (P.
                            Euphr. 1 à 5)’, <title rend="italic">Journal des Savants</title> 1995,
                            65–119.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>D.  Feissel and J.  Gascou</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Documents d’archives romains inédits du Moyen Euphrate (III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> s. après J.-C.). III. Actes diverses et
                            lettres (P. Euphr. 11 à 17)’, <title rend="italic">Journal des
                                Savants</title> 2000, 157–208.</bibl>
                        <bibl>D.  Feissel, J.  Gascou, and J.  Teixidor, ‘Documents d’archives
                            romains inédits du Moyen Euphrate (III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> s.
                            après J.-C.). II. Les actes de vente-achat (P. Euphr. 6 à 10)’, <title rend="italic">Journal des Savants</title> 1997, 3–57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J.  Gascou, ‘The papyrology of the Near East’, in <title rend="italic">The Oxford handbook of papyrology</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. S. Bagnall
                            (2009), 473–94. (ch. 20)</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. A.  Goldstein, ‘The Syriac Deed of Sale from Dura-Europos’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JNES</abbr>
                            </title> 25 (1966), 1–16.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. F.  Healey, ‘The early history of the Syriac Script: A
                            reassessment’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>JSS</abbr>
                            </title> 45 (2000), 55–67.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J. F.  Healey</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘New evidence for the Aramaic legal tradition: From Elephantine
                            to Edessa’, in <title rend="italic">Studia semitica. The Journal of
                                Semitic Studies jubilee volume</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> P. S. Alexander et
                            al. (<abbr>JSS</abbr> Supplement 16; 2005), 115–27.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J. F.  Healey</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Some lexical and legal notes on a Syriac loan transfer of 240
                            CE’, in <title rend="italic">Malphono w-Rabo d-Malphone</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr>
                            G. A. Kiraz, 211–26.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. F.  Healey, ‘Variety in early Syriac: The context in contemporary
                            Aramaic’, in <title rend="italic">Aramaic in its historical and
                                linguistic setting</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> H. Gzella and M. L. Folmer (Akademie
                            der Wissenschaften und der Literatur, Mainz. Veröffentlichungen der
                            Orientalischen Kommission 50; 2008), 221–29.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J. F.  Healey</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, <title rend="italic">Aramaic Inscriptions and Documents of the
                                Roman Period</title> (Textbook of Syrian Semitic Inscriptions 4;
                            2009), esp.  252–75.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Millar, <title rend="italic">Roman Near East</title>, 478–81.</bibl>
                        <bibl>G. I. Moller, ‘Towards a new typology of the Syriac manuscript
                            alphabet’, <title rend="italic">JNSL</title> 14 (1988), 153–97.</bibl>
                        <bibl>S. K. Ross, ‘The last king of Edessa: New evidence from the Middle
                            Euphrates’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ZPE</abbr>
                            </title> 97 (1993), 187–206.</bibl>
                        <bibl>J. Teixidor, ‘Les derniers rois d’Édesse d’après deux nouveaux
                            documents syriaques’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>ZPE</abbr>
                            </title> 76 (1989),
                            219–22.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J. Teixidor</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Deux documents syriaques du III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
                            siècle après J.-C., provenant du Moyen Euphrate’, <title rend="italic">
                                <abbr>CRAIBL</abbr>
                            </title> (1990), 144–166.</bibl>
                        <bibl>
                     <choice>
                        <reg>J. Teixidor</reg>
                        <orig>idem</orig>
                     </choice>, ‘Un document syriaque de fermage de 242 après J.-C.’, <title rend="italic">Semitica</title> 41–42 (1991–1992), 195–208.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ch. C.  Torrey, ‘A Syriac parchment from Edessa of the year 243 A.D.’,
                                <title rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Semitistik und verwandte
                                Gebiete</title> 10 (1935), 32–45.</bibl>
                        <bibl>C. B.  Welles, R. O.  Fink and J. F.  Gilliam, <title rend="italic">The excavations at Dura-Europus by Yale University and the French
                                Academy of Inscriptions and Letters</title>, Final Report V, Part 1.
                                <title rend="italic">The parchments and papyri</title>
                            (1959).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Aaron M.</forename> 
                  <surname>Butts</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
