<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:syriaca="http://syriaca.org"
     xmlns:saxon="http://saxon.sf.net/"
     xmlns:functx="http://www.functx.com">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a">Peshitta</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Bas</forename> 
                  <surname>ter Haar Romeny</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Craig E.</forename> 
                  <surname>Morrison</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</sponsor>
            <funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
               <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1.5">Electronic Edition Version 1.5</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Published by Gorgias Press LLC, 954 River Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA www.gorgiaspress.com for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</authority>
            <authority>Published with the collaboration of Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
            <authority>Published and hosted with the collaboration of the Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
                  <p>Distributed under an Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0) License.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-09-22-16:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</title>
            <editor role="general"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#sbrock">Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#abutts">Aaron M. Butts</editor>
            <editor role="print-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#lvanrompay">Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute Possekel</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <editor role="electronic-edition"
                    ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, and TEI editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#upossekel">Ute S. Posssekel</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning and initial valid TEI encoding by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David Michelson</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt> 
                    <resp>XSLT transformations by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky">Winona Salesky</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Data cleaning, editorial proofreading, TEI schema, and TEI encoding and editing by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
                </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversion to semantic XML by</resp>
                    <name ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#gkiraz">George A. Kiraz</name>
                </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                  <editor>Sebastian P. Brock</editor>
                  <editor>Aaron M. Butts</editor>
                  <editor>George A. Kiraz</editor>
                  <editor>Lucas Van Rompay</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Piscataway, N.J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Gorgias Press for Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2011</date>
                     <note>Copyright ©2011 by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</note>
                     <note>ISBN: 978-1-59333-714-8</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrected-draft">
         <change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#wsalesky"
                 n="1.0"
                 when="2020-05-18-04:00">Article record broken out form original electronic edition</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
                <head>Peshitta</head>
                <ab type="idnos">
                    <idno type="URI">https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Peshitta</idno>
                    <idno type="syriaca-bibl">http://syriaca.org/bibl/434</idno>
                    <idno type="entry">425</idno>
                    <milestone unit="pages" n="326-331"/>
                    <note type="type">work</note>
                    <note type="abstract">The name ‘Peshitta’ is used both for the translation of
                        the <abbr>OT</abbr>, made in the 2nd <abbr>cent.</abbr> on the basis of the Hebrew text, and for a
                        revision of the Old Syriac Version of the <abbr>NT</abbr>, which became the standard
                        version around 400.<note/>
                    </note>
                </ab>
                <div type="body">
                    <p>The name ‘Peshitta’ is used both for the translation of the <abbr>OT</abbr>, made in the
                        2nd <abbr>cent.</abbr> on the basis of the Hebrew text, and for a revision of the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Old-Syriac-Version">Old Syriac Version</ref> of the <abbr>NT</abbr>, which became the standard version
                        around 400.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Name ‘Peshitta’</label>
                    <p>It is only in the 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr> that we find the first attestation of the name
                        ‘Peshitta’. <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mushe-bar-Kipho">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/173">Mushe bar
                            Kipho</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 903) uses the name in his Commentary on the Hexaemeron
                        (unedited; <abbr>GT</abbr> in L. Schlimme [<abbr>GOF</abbr> I. Syriaca 14.1; 1977], 167– 173) and his
                        Introduction to the Psalter (<abbr>ed.</abbr> with <abbr>GT</abbr> in G. Diettrich, <hi rend="italic">Eine jakobitische Einleitung</hi> [Beihefte zur <abbr>ZAW</abbr> 5; 1901], 106–16).
                        He explains that he knew of two translations in Syriac: the Peshitta, based
                        on the Hebrew text, and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Pawlos-of-Tella">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/82">Pawlos of
                            Tella</persName>
                        </ref>’s translation from the Greek text of the Septuagint (see
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syro-Hexapla">Syro-Hexapla</ref>). Earlier references, in Syriac as well as in Greek
                        sources, simply refer to ‘the Syrian’.</p>
                    <p>The Syriac word <hi rend="italic">pšiṭtā</hi> is the feminine passive
                        participle of the verb <hi rend="italic">pšaṭ</hi> ‘to stretch out, to
                        extend’. It presupposes the word <hi rend="italic">mappaqtā</hi>
                        ‘translation’. The precise sense of this participle is no longer clear. In
                        other contexts, it often means ‘simple’. As the use in <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/239">Bar
                            ʿEbroyo</persName>
                        </ref> suggests, this is most probably also the sense when the
                        word is applied to the Syriac Bible. Some modern scholars, however, have
                        suggested other options. First, on the basis of the sense of the verb, the
                        participle has been interpreted as ‘widespread’, in the sense of ‘in common
                        use’, just like the Latin word <hi rend="italic">vulgata</hi>. The Syriac
                        Bible based on the Hebrew was indeed in common use, in contrast to the
                        versions made on the basis of the Greek Septuagint. Second, the usual sense
                        of the participle, ‘simple’, could be interpreted as ‘single’ rather than as
                        ‘abstaining from eloquent language’. This also assumes that the name was
                        intended to contrast the version with the Syro-Hexapla, the word <hi rend="italic">Hexapla</hi> meaning ‘six-fold’.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Origin and Dating of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta</label>
                    <p>Already in the 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr> one had to guess where the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta came from.
                        The Greek-speaking exegete <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodore-of-Mopsuestia">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/780">Theodore
                            of Mopsuestia</persName>
                        </ref> (d. 428) says that the Syriac Bible was composed by
                        some unknown man who often made mistakes and even made up stories. Syriac
                        authors in the following centuries mentioned various theories: it would have
                        been commissioned by Hiram, king of Tyre and an ally of David; alternatively
                        it would have been translated by a priest called Asya, who was sent to
                        Samaria by the king of Assyria (cf. 2 Kings 17:27–8), by the Apostles, by
                        Mark the Evangelist, or in the time of Abgar.</p>
                    <p>Modern scholars would agree with Theodore of Mopsuestia that the name of the
                        translator (or translators) is unknown. Still, one can try to find out
                        where, when, and in which community the Peshitta was translated. Over the
                        past two centuries, some scholars have defended Jewish authorship, others
                        Christian, whereas the famous linguist Theodor Nöldeke came up with the
                        compromise that Jewish Christians were behind the work.</p>
                    <p>The most thorough and innovative discussion of the origin of the Peshitta is
                        that of the late Michael Weitzman. In his <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi> to this Syriac version, he first explains that the
                        categories of ‘Judaism’ and ‘Christianity’ as they were used in the debate
                        do not take account of the diversity within both religions which research of
                        the last decades has revealed (see <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Judaism-Syriac-contacts-with">Judaism, Syriac contacts with</ref>). It would be better, he argues,
                        first to establish the ‘theological profile’ of the translation. Only then
                        can we compare the version with what we know of the Jewish and Christian
                        communities of the time. Weitzman’s own position is that the Peshitta was
                        translated in <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Edessa">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/78">Edessa</placeName>
                        </ref> from 150 onwards by a non-rabbinic Jewish group that
                        clearly identified themselves with Judaism, but neglected some elements of
                        ritual in favour of a more personal belief, in which prayer played an
                        important role. They emphasized faith and hope rather than observance. As
                        they shared these values with Christians, they might have adopted
                        Christianity. This would then explain how a Jewish translation came to be
                        transmitted by the Eastern Churches, and why it was not received among
                        rabbinic Jews.</p>
                    <p>The evidence for the presence of Jews in Edessa may lead to a modification
                        (Romeny 2005). As far as we can tell on the basis of the funerary
                        inscriptions found close to Edessa, it appears that Edessan Jews did use
                        more or less the same dialect of Aramaic, but did not use the same script as
                        the local pagans. They chose the square Jewish Aramaic script that was also
                        used for Hebrew. On the other hand, Classical Syriac as we know it from the
                        earliest Christian sources suggests that Edessan Christians adopted the Old
                        Syriac dialect and script that were used by the pagans, rather than the
                        Jewish script. This confronts us with the paradox of a translation that
                        supposes a knowledge of Hebrew found only among very learned Jews but that
                        was not written in the Jewish script. Was the Peshitta a gentile project,
                        after all, or should we assume that, perhaps together with an update of the
                        language, the translation was recast in Syriac script? The alternative is
                        that the translators were Jewish Christians (in the sense of: Jews who had
                        come to believe that Jesus Christ brought salvation) from the start.</p>
                    <p>It is certain that either some of the Jews of Edessa or one of its Christian
                        groups felt the need for a version in the dialect of the town. What Weitzman
                        calls the ‘theological profile’ of the translators is compatible with either
                        possibility, as long as we do not think in terms of the ideal types of
                        rabbinic Judaism and later Christianity. The use of the Syriac script,
                        however, points solely in the direction of Christians. Whatever the case may
                        be, it should be granted that the actual translation work was done by Jews,
                        be they converted to Christianity before (Romeny) or after (Weitzman) the
                        production of the Peshitta: we cannot assume that pagans who converted to
                        Christianity commanded sufficient knowledge of Hebrew.</p>
                    <p>Weitzman connects the Peshitta with the city of Edessa. The Peshitta
                        introduces references to Mabbug, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Harran">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/216">Ḥarran</placeName>
                        </ref>, and <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis">
                            <placeName ref="http://syriaca.org/place/142">Nisibis</placeName>
                        </ref>
                        as additions to the text or substitutions for other names. These names
                        suggest an origin in Osrhoene, the province around Edessa. The dialect and
                        script of the Peshitta also accord well with that of the inscriptions found
                        in this province.</p>
                    <p>Weitzman’s main argument for dating the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta is formed by quotations
                        of the Peshitta in other texts. On the basis of such quotations, a latest
                        possible date can be established. If the Peshitta was indeed the basis for
                        the <abbr>OT</abbr> quotations in the <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Diatessaron">Diatessaron</ref>, at
                        least the books actually cited, that is, the Pentateuch, the Latter
                        Prophets, and the Psalms, already existed and had attained some status by
                        around 170. On the other hand, the fact that <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bardaisan">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/3">Bardaiṣan</persName>
                        </ref>, born
                        in 154, quotes Gen. 9:6 in a form that stands closer to the Jewish Targum
                        Onqelos could still indicate some reserve towards the Peshitta. This is a
                        warning against adopting a much earlier date, and makes Weitzman propose the
                        date of <abbr>ca.</abbr> 150. Chronicles, and perhaps also Ezra and Nehemiah, may have
                        been translated about fifty years later.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Origin and Dating of the <abbr>NT</abbr> Peshitta</label>
                    <p>The history of the translation of the Greek <abbr>NT</abbr> into Syriac begins with <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Tatian">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/771">Tatian</persName>
                        </ref>’s
                        Diatessaron, a <choice>
                            <sic>2nd </sic>
                            <corr>2nd-</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr> Gospel harmony. The Old Syriac Version (3rd <abbr>cent.</abbr>)
                        is the oldest translation of the four separate Gospels and the Peshitta
                        (early 5th <abbr>cent.</abbr>) is a revision that brought the Old Syriac closer to the
                        Greek. Burkitt (1904) attributed the Peshitta to <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Rabbula-of-Edessa">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/26">Rabbula</persName>
                        </ref>, the <abbr>bp.</abbr> of Edessa (411–35) who had vigorously suppressed
                        the use of the Diatessaron in the Syriac Church. While Rabbula may have
                        enforced the dissemination of the Peshitta version, the theory that he was
                        responsible for its creation was convincingly challenged by Vööbus (1951)
                        who illustrated how Rabbula’s own writings contained quotations from the Old
                        Syriac Version and the Diatessaron.</p>
                    <p>The Peshitta did not abruptly replace the Old Syriac. M. Black (1953) argued
                        for the existence of an early Peshitta text, which he labelled
                        ‘Pre-Peshitta’, that was closer to the Old Syriac than the later, definitive
                        text of the Peshitta. ‘Genetic variants’ in the Syriac textual tradition,
                        namely, readings that lie between the Old Syriac and the Peshitta, trace the
                        gradual process of revision toward the Greek (Juckel 2009). Still, the
                        Diatessaronic readings that appear in the Peshitta convinced Joosten (1996)
                        that the Peshitta was based on a revised form of the Diatessaron. A precise
                        description of the relationship between the Peshitta and the Old Syriac and
                        Diatessaron will continue to elude scholars until a critical edition of the
                        Peshitta Gospels is published.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Nature of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Translation</label>
                    <p>There has been an extensive debate among specialists of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta on
                        the question of whether those text forms that are closer to the Hebrew text
                        are representatives of an older stage of the Peshitta tradition or products
                        of a revision. Studies on the books of Genesis and Exodus in the <choice>
                            <sic>5th </sic>
                            <corr>5th-</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                        <abbr>ms.</abbr> 5b1 (Brit. Libr. Add. 14,425) eventually showed that a translation very
                        close to the Hebrew model had developed into one that was easier to read and
                        less ambiguous. Some phrases were replaced by more idiomatic Syriac ones or
                        by expressions which better met the prevailing standards of literary Syriac.
                        What is implicit in the Hebrew text and in the original translation was made
                        explicit, for example, by adding the subject. Complicated sentences were
                        clarified by slight additions or omissions, or by changes in word order.
                        Finally, certain passages were harmonized in the process of transmission.
                        All this happened during the first stages of the history of the Peshitta.
                        For other books, it appears that we can discern a comparable first stage.
                        The importance of <abbr>ms.</abbr> 9a1 (Florence, Bibl. Medicea Laurenziana, Or. 58) has
                        been pointed out in this respect. Even though this is a much later <abbr>ms.</abbr>, for
                        some books it still preserves a text comparable to the Genesis and Exodus
                        text of <abbr>ms.</abbr> 5b1.</p>
                    <p>The relative uniformity of <abbr>mss.</abbr> in later stages of the textual history, that
                        is, after the 6th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, suggests some kind of standardization: one text was
                        chosen from a broader spectrum of texts which must have existed in the first
                        stage. Koster’s research made it clear that after this second stage,
                        represented by most <abbr>mss.</abbr> from the 6th until the 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, further textual
                        convergence can be observed. We can speak of a third stage, which he termed
                        that of the <hi rend="italic">Textus Receptus</hi> (others also speak of
                        Standard Text). On the basis of <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Theodoros-bar-Koni">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/783">Theodoros bar
                            Koni</persName>
                        </ref>’s biblical quotations, we can say that the later Standard
                        Text or <hi rend="italic">Textus Receptus</hi> was already available in the
                        East at the end of the 8th <abbr>cent.</abbr> On the other hand, the biblical text of the
                        commentary of the monk <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Severos-Commentary-of-the-monk">Severos</ref> shows us that in the
                        West, variation was still possible up to the end of the 9th <abbr>cent.</abbr>, and that
                        the western biblical <abbr>ms.</abbr> 9a1, which still represents the first stage of the
                        development of the text, was not an isolated case.</p>
                    <p>Another issue that has been debated widely is the influence of other versions
                        on the Peshitta. Some scholars have even suggested that the Peshitta was not
                        a direct translation of the Hebrew, but based on an earlier Targum. It is,
                        however, natural that two translations of the same text have something in
                        common and could combine together against the source text because of the
                        demands of the language or a similarity in interpretation  — all the more so
                        if the two translations are written in dialects of the same language (see
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Aramaic">Aramaic</ref>). There are no external data that prove contact between
                        the Peshitta and the existing Targumim, and all parallels between the
                        Targumim and the Peshitta can be explained as being the result of
                        polygenesis or dependence on a common exegetical tradition. However, for the
                        Septuagint, which is a translation into a completely different language,
                        these explanations do not always suffice. In some books, notably Ezekiel and
                        the Twelve Prophets, we have to assume some literary dependence of the
                        Peshitta on the Septuagint. However, this dependence is not of a
                        systematical nature, and may be the result of changes made in the later
                        tradition.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Nature of the <abbr>NT</abbr> Translation</label>
                    <p>The <abbr>NT</abbr> Peshitta contains twenty-two books; it lacks 2–3  John, 2 Peter, Jude,
                        and Revelation. It also omits John 7:53–8:11 (along with the Old Syriac and
                            <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Harqlean-Version">Ḥarqlean</ref> versions) and a few isolated verses,
                        such as Luke 22:17–18. The history of the Syriac versions of the <abbr>NT</abbr> is
                        characterized by gravitation toward the Greek text. Though, on occasion, the
                        Peshitta preserves a Diatessaronic reading, where the Old Syriac reflects
                        the Byzantine <hi rend="italic">Textus Receptus</hi> (both the Sinaiticus
                        and Curetonian <abbr>mss.</abbr> show signs of revision toward the Greek text), in
                        general the Peshitta is closer than the Old Syriac to the <hi rend="italic">Textus Receptus</hi>. It preserves readings that agree with the Western
                        text type (Codex Bezae and the Old Latin), though many of its readings
                        cannot be linked to any extant Greek witness. The readings unique to the
                        Peshitta argue for its important role in <abbr>NT</abbr> textual criticism (Gwilliam
                        1903). The meticulous presentation of the Peshitta <abbr>mss.</abbr> for the Catholic and
                        Pauline epistles by B. Aland and A. Juckel (1986–2002) reveals the
                        homogeneity of these <abbr>mss.</abbr> The minor differences among them suggest that the
                        Peshitta text of these epistles did not undergo a major revision during its
                        transmission.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">The Importance of the Peshitta</label>
                    <p>The reason why the International Organization for the Study of the Old
                        Testament took the initiative to produce a new edition of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta
                        (see below) is its relevance for the textual criticism of the Hebrew Bible.
                        The edition and the studies based on it have made it clear that the Hebrew
                        model of the Peshitta must have been nearly identical with the so-called
                        Masoretic Text of the Hebrew Bible, the standard form of the text handed
                        down to us by a tradition of Jewish scholars, the Masoretes. The Peshitta
                        even reflects a vocalization of the Hebrew text that stands very close to
                        the vocalization recorded many centuries later by the Masoretes. Thus, the
                        Old Testament Peshitta is a prime witness to the strength and quality of the
                        Jewish tradition since the 2nd <abbr>cent.</abbr> In the small number of instances where
                        the Peshitta can be demonstrated to go back to a text that differs from the
                        Masoretic Text, it can be useful to correct errors in the latter.</p>
                    <p>Another issue of scholarly interest is the language of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta. It is
                        one of the largest and oldest texts written in Syriac. A number of studies
                        into the syntax of the Peshitta have already appeared, and the Leiden
                        Peshitta Institute is conducting major research projects in this field (Van
                        Keulen and Van Peursen 2006).</p>
                    <p>The <abbr>NT</abbr> Peshitta remains an important textual witness to the Greek <abbr>NT</abbr> since
                        some of its readings are unique. <abbr>NT</abbr> textual critics must distinguish the
                        readings that witness to Greek variants from those that witness to the
                        Peshitta’s translation technique and/or exegesis (see, for example, Williams
                        2004). Continued research into the character of the <abbr>NT</abbr> Peshitta as a
                        translation remains a <hi rend="italic">desideratum</hi>. In addition to its
                        text critical value, the <abbr>NT</abbr> Peshitta witnesses to the reception and
                        interpretation of the Greek <abbr>NT</abbr> by Syriac-speaking Christians in the 4th–5th
                        <abbr>cent.</abbr>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Peshitta is, however, not only of interest to scholars. In the first
                        place, it is the Bible of the Syriac Churches, and it has been a source of
                        spirituality to them for ages. It is used in sermons, commentaries, <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Poetry">poetry</ref>, and other genres of literature (see <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Exegesis-Old-Testament">Exegesis, <abbr>OT</abbr>
                        </ref>and <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Exegesis-New-Testament">Exegesis,
                            <abbr>NT</abbr>
                        </ref>). Its interpretations and exegetical traditions have colored
                        the liturgy, and the prayers and hymns of the Syriac Churches follow the
                        choice of words of the Peshitta. Many terms specific to the spirituality of
                        the Syriac Churches have their origins in this ancient and reliable version
                        of the <abbr>OT</abbr> and <abbr>NT</abbr>.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Text Editions</label>
                    <p>The first printed edition of part of the Syriac <abbr>OT</abbr> was the edition of the
                        Psalms that was published in Quzḥayya, Lebanon, in 1610. It was followed in
                        1625 by two more editions of the Psalms: that of the Maronite Gabriel
                        Sionita (<ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Sahyuni-Jibrail">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/712">al-Ṣahyūnī,
                            Jibrāʾīl</persName>
                        </ref>), published in Paris, and that of Thomas van Erpe
                        (Erpenius), a professor of Arabic, printed in Leiden, the Netherlands.</p>
                    <p>The first printed edition of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta as a whole is found in the Paris
                        Polyglot. The Syriac text, edited by Gabriel Sionita, appeared in 1645. It
                        was based on a rather poor <abbr>ms.</abbr>: 17a5 (Paris, Bibl. Nat. Syr. 6). In its
                        turn, the Paris Polyglot became the basis of the London Polyglot published
                        by Brian Walton in 1657. This edition adds a number of variant readings from
                        <abbr>mss.</abbr> present in English libraries, but otherwise just reproduces the Paris
                        text. The text most widely available today goes back to that of Walton, and
                        thus eventually to the Paris <abbr>ms.</abbr> 17a5: in 1823 Samuel Lee published his
                        edition of the Peshitta under the auspices of the British and Foreign Bible
                        Society, adopting the text of the London Polyglot while making some use of
                        the so-called Buchanan Bible (Cambridge, Univ. Libr. Oo. I.1,2 = 12a1). The
                        United Bible Societies have been publishing reprints of Lee’s edition up to
                        this day.</p>
                    <p>Whereas Lee’s edition was printed in the W.-Syr. Serṭo script, the same
                        century also saw two editions in E.-Syr. type: the so-called Urmia (1852)
                        and Mosul (1887–92) Bibles. In parallel columns Urmia gives the text of the
                        Peshitta based on Lee’s edition, corrected in some instances on the basis of
                        <abbr>mss.</abbr> that were available locally, and a new translation of the Hebrew text
                        into neo-Aramaic. It is assumed that the text of the Mosul edition, in its
                        turn, made use of the Urmia edition. The Mosul edition was prepared by <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/David-Clemens-Joseph">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/442">Clemens Joseph David</persName>
                        </ref>, <abbr>Syr. Cath.</abbr> Archbishop of Damascus, and
                        George ʿAbdishoʿ Khayyāṭ, Chaldean Archbishop of Diyarbakır; it was
                        published by the <choice>
                            <sic>
                                <hi rend="bold">Dominican</hi>
                            </sic>
                            <corr>Dominican</corr>
                        </choice> Fathers. This edition also
                        contains the text of the apocryphal or deutero-canonical books.</p>
                    <p>A 19th-cent. edition of a different nature was <ref rend="bold"
                       target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ceriani-Antonio-Maria">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/410">A. M. Ceriani</persName>
                        </ref>’s facsimile publication of <abbr>ms.</abbr> 7a1, the oldest
                        codex containing the complete text of the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta, from the Ambrosian
                        Library in Milan (<abbr>ms.</abbr> B 21 inf.). It was published in the years 1876–83.
                        This publication was a landmark in Peshitta studies. For the first time, a
                        text became available to a scholarly public that differed markedly from that
                        of the Paris Polyglot. The first scientific edition, containing only the
                        Psalms, was published by W. E. Barnes in 1904. He used 7a1 as his base text,
                        but corrected it on the basis of a number of other <abbr>mss.</abbr> With the help of
                        C. W. Mitchell and J. Pinkerton, the same author also published a new
                        edition of the Pentateuch in 1914. This edition gives a corrected version of
                        Lee’s text.</p>
                    <p>It was not until 1959, however, that the International Organization for the
                        Study of the Old Testament decided to start the Peshitta project, which was
                        entrusted to the Leiden Peshitta Institute. In 1972 the first volume of the
                        new edition appeared, under the title <hi rend="italic">The Old Testament in
                            Syriac according to the Peshitta Version</hi>. The Leiden edition does
                        not offer a critical text (one that tries to come as close to the original
                        as possible). It prints a basic text, usually 7a1, with a number of
                        emendations. Readings deemed impossible and readings not supported by two or
                        more <abbr>mss.</abbr> dated before the year 1000 are emended. The <hi rend="italic">critical apparatus</hi>, the list of variant readings, only includes
                        <abbr>mss.</abbr> older than the 13th <abbr>cent.</abbr> The reason for this unorthodox approach,
                        which resulted in a mixed text, was economy. The main text was meant as a
                        point of reference: it should be common enough to guarantee a concise
                        apparatus. This entails that the main text as such has no status. As De Boer
                        writes: ‘The text printed in this edition — it must be stated <hi rend="italic">expressis verbis</hi> — ought to be used in exegetical and
                        textual study together with the apparatuses’ (De Boer, Preface to the
                        Genesis-Exodus volume, p. viii). In other words, the reader cannot just
                        quote the text; he or she should first go over the apparatus and do the work
                        of the textual critic.</p>
                    <p>Notwithstanding the shortcomings that are the result of its edition method,
                        there is no doubt that the Leiden Peshitta edition is the most important
                        tool for the study of the Peshitta of the <abbr>OT</abbr>. The edition will consist of 17
                        volumes, 13 of which have now appeared. The Peshitta Institute intends to
                        publish additional volumes with the variants of biblical <abbr>mss.</abbr> up to and
                        including the 15th <abbr>cent.</abbr> as well as studies of the text of the Syriac
                        fathers, whose witness is considered very important. The main text of the
                        edition is also available in electronic format through the website of the
                        Comprehensive Aramaic Lexicon (http://cal1.cn.huc.edu/).</p>
                    <p>The first printed edition of the Syriac <abbr>NT</abbr> was prepared by Johann
                        Widmanstetter in 1555. A year later Immanuel Tremellius produced another
                        edition. A critical edition of the Gospels (citing forty-two <abbr>mss.</abbr> from the
                        5th–12th <abbr>cent.</abbr>) was prepared by P. E.  Pusey and G. H.  Gwilliam (1901).
                        Pusey and Gwilliam’s provisional text for the rest of the <abbr>NT</abbr> was combined
                        with their edition of the Gospels to produce <hi rend="italic">The New
                            Testament in Syriac</hi> (The British and Foreign Bible Society,
                        1905–20). The minor Catholic letters (2 Peter, 2–3 John, and Jude) and the
                        Book of Revelation in this edition are taken from J. Gwynn (1897 and 1909);
                        these are remnants of the Philoxenian version (see <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Polykarpos">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/35">Polykarpos</persName>
                        </ref>).
                        More recently, G.  Kiraz produced a comparative edition of the Syriac
                        Gospels (Kiraz 1996) that aligns the Siniaticus and Curetonian <abbr>mss.</abbr> with the
                        Peshitta and Ḥarqlean versions. A new critical edition of the Peshitta
                        Gospels is needed, though the quantity of Peshitta <abbr>mss.</abbr> renders this a
                        formidable task. The Institut für Neutestamentliche Textforschung at
                        Münster has produced an edition of the Catholic and Pauline letters (B.
                        Aland and A. Juckel 1986–2002) that aligns Peshitta <abbr>mss.</abbr> with the Ḥarqlean
                        text and quotations from Syriac authors.</p>
                    <label type="subsection">Translation into English</label>
                    <p>The Peshitta has been translated into English by <ref rend="bold" target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Lamsa-George">
                            <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/593">George M.
                            Lamsa</persName>
                        </ref>. Unfortunately, this translation has been assimilated to the
                        Hebrew text in quite a few places, and is not based on a reliable text of
                        the Peshitta. The latter point also applies to Andrew Oliver’s lesser known
                        translation of the Peshitta Psalter. A new English annotated translation of
                        the <abbr>OT</abbr> Peshitta is now being prepared by a group of scholars as one of the
                        Leiden Peshitta Institute’s projects. It will appear under the title <hi rend="italic">The Bible of Edessa</hi>. Portions of the <abbr>NT</abbr> have been
                        translated into English by J. W. Etheridge (1846 and 1849) and by James
                        Murdock (1851).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl">
                    <listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Bibliography</head>
                            <bibl>P. B.  Dirksen, <title rend="italic">An annotated bibliography of
                                    the Peshitta of the Old Testament</title> (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 5; 1989).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>P. B.  Dirksen</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Supplement to an annotated bibliography, 1989’, in <title rend="italic">The Peshitta as a translation: Papers read at the
                                    II Peshitta Symposium held at Leiden 19–21 August 1993</title>,
                                <abbr>ed.</abbr> P. B. Dirksen and A. van der Kooij (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 8; 1995),
                                221–36.</bibl>
                            <bibl>The literature published since 1998, on all Syriac versions as
                                well as the Targumim (Jewish Aramaic versions of the Old Testament),
                                can be found in the ‘Bibliography of the Aramaic Bible’, published
                                in the <title rend="italic">Journal for the Aramaic Bible</title>,
                                since 2003 continued under the title <title rend="italic">Aramaic
                                    Studies</title>. A selection of this material will be published
                                on the website of the Peshitta Institute, together with the data on
                                1995–97.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Editions and Secondary Sources</head>
                            <bibl>B.  Aland (in association with A. Juckel), <title rend="italic">Das Neue Testament in syrischer Überlieferung</title>, vol. I.
                                    <title rend="italic">Die grossen Katholischen Briefe</title>
                                (Arbeiten zur neutestamentlichen Textforschung 7; 1986).</bibl>
                            <bibl>B.  Aland and A.  Juckel, <title rend="italic">Das Neue Testament
                                    in syrischer Überlieferung</title>, vol. II. <title rend="italic">Die Paulinischen Briefe</title>, part 1: <title rend="italic">Römer und 1. Korintherbrief</title>; part 2:
                                    <title rend="italic">2. Korintherbrief, Galaterbrief,
                                    Epheserbrief, Philipperbrief und Kolosserbrief</title>; part 3:
                                <choice>
                                    <sic>
                                        <title rend="italic">1./2 .  Thessaloniche</title>rbrief</sic>
                                    <corr>
                                        <title rend="italic">1./2 .  Thessalonicherbrief</title>
                                    </corr>
                                </choice>
                                , <choice>
                                    <sic>1./2. <title rend="italic">Timotheusbrief, Titusbrief, Philemonbrief
                                    und Hebräerbrief</title>
                                    </sic>
                                    <corr>
                                        <title rend="italic">1./2. Timotheusbrief, Titusbrief, Philemonbrief
                                        und Hebräerbrief</title>
                                    </corr>
                                </choice> (Arbeiten zur neutestamentlichen
                                Textforschung 14/23/32; 1991–2002).</bibl>
                            <bibl>M.  Black, ‘The text of the Peshitta Tetraeuangelium’, in <title rend="italic">Studia paulina in honorem Johannis de Zwaan
                                    septuagenarii</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> C. K.  Barrett <abbr>et al.</abbr> (1953),
                                20–7.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>M.  Black</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘The Syriac versional tradition’, in <title rend="italic">Die alten Übersetzungen des Neuen Testaments. Die
                                    Kirchenväterzitate und Lektionare: Der gegenwärtige Stand ihrer
                                    Erforschung und ihre Bedeutung für die griechische
                                    Textgeschichte</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> K. Aland (Arbeiten zur
                                neutestamentlichen Textforschung 5; 1972), 120–59.</bibl>
                            <bibl>F. C.  Burkitt, <title rend="italic">Evangelion da-Mepharreshe;
                                    the Curetonian Syriac Gospels, re-edited, together with the
                                    readings of the Sinatic palimpsest ...</title> (2 vols.;
                                1904).</bibl>
                            <bibl>S. P.  Brock, <title rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac
                                    tradition</title> (Gorgias Handbooks 7; 2006).</bibl>
                            <bibl>F.  Briquel Chatonnet and Ph.  Le  Moigne (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">L’Ancien Testament en syriaque</title> (<abbr>ÉtSyr</abbr> 5;
                                2008).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. B.  Dirksen, ‘The Old Testament Peshitta’, in <title rend="italic">Mikra. Text, translation, reading, and
                                    interpretation of the Hebrew Bible in ancient Judaism and early
                                    Christianity</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> M. J. Mulder (Compendia Rerum
                                Iudaicarum ad Novum Testamentum 2.1; 1988).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. B.  Dirksen and M. J.  Mulder, <title rend="italic">The
                                    Peshiṭta: Its early text and history. Papers read at the
                                    Peshiṭta Symposium held at Leiden 30–31 August 1985</title>
                                (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 4; 1988).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. B.  Dirksen and A.  van  der  Kooij (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">The Peshitta as a translation. Papers read at the II Peshitta
                                    Symposium held at Leiden 19–21 August 1993</title> (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 8;
                                1995).</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. W.  Etheridge, <title rend="italic">The Syrian Churches: Early
                                    history, liturgies, and literature. With a literal translation
                                    of the four Gospels, from the Peschito</title> (1846).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>J. W.  Etheridge</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">The Apostolical Acts and Epistles, from
                                    the Peschito, or, ancient Syriac: to which are added, the
                                    remaining Epistles, and the Book of Revelation, after a later
                                    Syrian text</title> (1849).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. H.  Gwilliam, ‘The Place of the Peshitto version in the
                                apparatus criticus of the Greek New Testament’, <title rend="italic">Studia biblica et ecclesiastica</title> 5 (1903),
                                187–237.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  Gwynn, <title rend="italic">The Apocalypse of St John, in a
                                    Syriac version hitherto unknown</title> (1897).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>J.  Gwynn</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, <title rend="italic">Remnants of the later Syriac versions
                                    of the Bible ...</title> (1909; <abbr>repr.</abbr> 2005).</bibl>
                            <bibl>K. D.  Jenner <abbr>et al.</abbr>, ‘The New English Annotated Translation of
                                the Syriac Bible (NEATSB): Retrospect and prospect’, <title rend="italic">AS</title> 2 (2004), 85–106.</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Juckel, ‘Research on the Old Syriac heritage of the Peshitta
                                Gospels’, <title rend="italic">
                                    <abbr>Hugoye</abbr>
                                </title> 12.1 (2009),
                                41–115.</bibl>
                            <bibl>J.  Joosten, <title rend="italic">The Syriac language of the
                                    Peshitta and Old Syriac versions of Matthew: Syntactic
                                    structure, inner-Syriac developments and translation
                                    technique</title> (1996).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. S. F. van Keulen and W. Th. van Peursen, <title rend="italic">Corpus linguistics and textual history. A computer-assisted
                                    interdisciplinary approach to the Peshitta</title> (Studia
                                semitica neerlandica 48; 2006).</bibl>
                            <bibl>G. A.  Kiraz, <title rend="italic">Comparative edition of the
                                    Syriac Gospels</title> (1996–2004).</bibl>
                            <bibl>M. D.  Koster, <title rend="italic">The Peshitta of Exodus: The
                                    development of its text in the course of fifteen
                                    centuries</title> (1977).</bibl>
                            <bibl>J. Murdock, <title rend="italic">The New Testament; or, the Book
                                    of the Holy Gospel of our Lord and our God, Jesus the Messiah. A
                                    literal translation from the Syriac version</title>
                                (1851).</bibl>
                            <bibl>W. L.  Petersen, <title rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron. Its
                                    creation, dissemination, significance, and history in
                                    scholarship</title> (Supplements to <abbr>VC</abbr> 25; 1994).</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>W. L.  Petersen</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Problems in the Syriac New Testament and how Syrian
                                exegetes solved them’, in <title rend="italic">The Peshitta: Its use
                                    in literature and liturgy. Papers read at the Third Peshitta
                                    Symposium,</title> 
                        <abbr>ed.</abbr> R. B. ter Haar Romeny (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 15; 2006),
                                53–74.</bibl>
                            <bibl>W. Th.  van  Peursen and R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">Text, translation, and tradition: Studies on the
                                    Peshitta and its use in the Syriac tradition presented to Konrad
                                    D. Jenner on the occasion of his sixty-fifth birthday</title>
                                (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 14; 2006).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. E.  Pusey and G. H.  Gwilliam, <title rend="italic">Tetraevangelium sanctum iuxta simplicem Syrorum versionem ad
                                    fidem codicum, Massorae, editionum denuo recognitum
                              </title> (1901).</bibl>
                            <bibl>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny, ‘The Syriac versions of the Old
                                Testament’, in <title rend="italic">Sources Syriaques</title>, vol.
                                1. <title rend="italic">Nos Sources: Arts et littérature
                                    syriaques</title>, <abbr>ed.</abbr> M. Atallah <abbr>et al.</abbr> (2005), 75–105.</bibl>
                            <bibl>
                        <choice>
                           <reg>R. B.  ter  Haar  Romeny</reg>
                           <orig>idem</orig>
                        </choice>, ‘Hypotheses on the development of Judaism and Christianity
                                in Syria in the period after 70 <choice>
                                    <sic>c.e.</sic>
                                    <corr>C.E.</corr>
                                </choice>’, in <title rend="italic">Matthew and the Didache: Two documents from the same
                                    Jewish-Christian milieu?</title>
                                <choice>
                                    <sic>,</sic>
                                    <corr/>
                                </choice> 
                        <abbr>ed.</abbr> H. van de Sandt (2005),
                                13–33.</bibl>
                            <bibl>R. B.  ter Haar Romeny (<abbr>ed.</abbr>), <title rend="italic">The Peshitta:
                                    Its use in literature and liturgy. Papers read at the Third
                                    Peshitta Symposium</title> (<abbr>MPIL</abbr> 15; 2006).</bibl>
                            <bibl>A.  Vööbus, <title rend="italic">Studies in the history of the
                                    Gospel text in Syriac</title> (2 vols.; <abbr>CSCO</abbr> 128, 496; 1951,
                                1987).</bibl>
                            <bibl>M. P.  Weitzman, <title rend="italic">The Syriac version of the
                                    Old Testament: An introduction</title> (University of Cambridge
                                Oriental Publications 56; 1999).</bibl>
                            <bibl>P. J.  Williams, <title rend="italic">Early Syriac translation
                                    technique and the textual criticism of the Greek Gospels</title>
                                (Texts and Studies, Third Series 2; 2004).</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <byline>
                    <persName>
                  <forename>Bas</forename> 
                  <surname>ter Haar Romeny</surname>
               </persName> and <persName>
                  <forename>Craig E.</forename> 
                  <surname>Morrison</surname>
               </persName>
                </byline>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
