<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../out/odd_GEDSH_draft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1><!-- Mss. not marked. Consider this for cross referencing with the index of mss. -->
            <figure><!-- proofreading of captions from here. UP 18 May 2017 -->
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/1"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 1. Orpheus taming wild animals. Mosaic decorating the tomb of Papa,
                  with Syriac inscription dated 194, and reflecting Greco-Roman culture of the
                  Edessa area under the Abgarids. Dallas Museum of Art. Photo: John F. Healey. See
                  <bibl>J. F. Healey. ‘A new Syriac mosaic inscription’, <title rend="italic"
                     >JSS</title> 51 (2006), 313–27</bibl> as well as <bibl>U. Possekel, ‘Orpheus
                        among the animals. A new dated mosaic from Osrhoene’, <title rend="italic"
                        >OC</title> 92 (2008), 1–35</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/2"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 2. King Abgar receiving the portrait of Jesus. Modern relief in the
                  Syr. Orth. Church of St. George in Aleppo. The two inscriptions contain extracts
                  from the epistolary exchange between Abgar and Jesus. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor,
                        <title rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, vol. 2, 50</bibl> (Photo:
                  Riccardo Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/4"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 4. Alqosh, Iraq. The village in the snow. Photo: Lucas Van Rompay
                  (1971).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/5"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 5. Amid (Diyarbakır). Syr. Orth. Church of Yoldat Aloho. Photo: Hidemi
                  Takahashi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/7"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 7. Armenian inscriptions in the Dayro d-Mor Behnam, main entrance. The
                  upper inscription was left by an Armenian visitor from Sebaste (Sivas) in 1884.
                  Photo: Amir Harrak<choice><sic></sic><corr>.</corr></choice></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/8"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 8. Initial page of the Syriac-Armenian lexicon in ms. Yale Syr. 9.
                  Beinecke Library of Yale University. See <bibl>H. Takahashi and J.J.S. Weitenberg.
                     ‘The Shorter Syriac-Armenian Glossary in Ms. Yale Syriac 9. Part 1’, <title
                        rend="italic">JCSSS</title> 10 (2010) 68–83</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/9"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 9. Basilica of Kharab Shams, Syria, built in the 4th cent. and
                  partially reconstructed in the 5th cent. One of the many abandoned Christian
                  monuments in the region between Aleppo and Antioch. Photo: Annewies van den Hoek.
                  See <bibl>I. Peña, <title rend="italic">The Christian art of Byzantine
                        Syria</title> (1996), 64–65</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/10"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 10. Bema lectern from Bennawi, near Aleppo. Garden of the National
                  Museum Damascus. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden
                        Pearl</title>, vol. 2, 43</bibl> (Photo: Riccardo Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/11"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 11. Mosaic with the female name of Symeonis. From a monastery at Tall
                  Biʿa, near Raqqaʿ, Syria. Deutsche Orient-Gesellschaft, Grabung Tall Biʿa. Photo:
                  Anwar ʿAbd al-Ghafour.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/13"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 13. Bronze incense burner from Tagrit, with scenes from the life of
                  Jesus. In this image the baptism is depicted. Baghdad Iraqi Museum no. 11243/1.
                  Courtesy of Amir Harrak. See <bibl>A. Harrak, ‘The incense burner of Takrit: An
                     iconographical analysis’, <title rend="italic">ECA</title> (2006),
                  47–52</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/14"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 14. Liturgical fan, made for Dayr al-Suryān (Egypt) and containing a
                  Syriac inscription dated 1202/3. Courtesy of the Musée Royal de Mariemont
                  (Morlanwelz, Belgium). See <bibl>B. Snelders, <title rend="italic">Identity and
                        Christian-Muslim interaction. Medieval art of the Syrian Orthodox from the
                        Mosul area</title> (OLA 198; 2010), 105–50</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/15"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 15. Modern Syr. Cath. Church in Zaydal, near Ḥimṣ, Syria. The church is
                  decorated with wall paintings by the Maronite artist and scholar Abdo Badwi, who
                  draws much of his inspiration from earlier Syr. Christian art. Photo: Lucas Van
                  Rompay. See also <ref target="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/86">Fig.
                  86</ref>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/16"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 16. Bahdeidat, Lebanon, Maronite Church of Mar Tadros. Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo:
                  Mat Immerzeel. See <bibl>M. Immerzeel, <title rend="italic">Identity puzzles.
                        Medieval Christian art in Syria and Lebanon</title> (2009),
                  101–5</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/17"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 17. Bahdeidat, Lebanon, Maronite Church of Mar Tadros. St. Stephen:
                  detail of the lower part of the wall painting program in the conch of the apse,
                  with Syriac inscription. Paul van Moorsel Centre for Christian Art and Culture in
                  the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo: Mat Immerzeel<choice><sic></sic><corr>.</corr></choice></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/18"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 18. Autographed ex-libris of Bar ʿEbroyo, preserved in a ms. in
                  Istanbul. Published in A. Sayılı, ‘Khwāja Naṣīr-i Tūsī wa raṣadkhāna-i Marāgha’,
                     <title rend="italic">Ankara Üniversitesi Dil ve Tarih-Coğrafya Fakültesi
                     Dergisi</title> 14 (1956), plate opposite p. 16.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/19"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 19. The Syriac Saint Barṣawmo depicted in the nave of the church of St.
                  Antony’s Monastery, Egypt, with an inscription partly in Syriac and partly in
                  Coptic. Bibliotheca Alexandrina, Alexandria, Egypt. Courtesy of Ahmed Mansour. See
                     <bibl>Kh. Azab and A. Mansour, <title rend="italic">Journey of Writing in
                        Egypt</title> (2008), 158 (Fig.10)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/20"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 20. The tombs of Grigorios Bar ʿEbroyo and his brother Grigorios
                  Barṣawmo Ṣafī in the Dayro d-Mor Matay, with inscriptions in Garshuni and Syriac,
                  probably dating from the 17th cent. Photo: Amir Harrak. See <bibl>Harrak, <title
                        rend="italic">Syriac and Garshuni inscriptions of Iraq</title>,
                     AF.01.05</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/21"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 21. Portrait of Mor Severius Barsoum, the future Patriarch Ignatius
                  Afram Barsoum. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden
                        Pearl</title>, vol. 3, 205</bibl> (Photo: Riccardo Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/22"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 22. Barṭelle, Iraq. Syr. Orth. Church of Mart Shmuni. Photo. Amir
                  Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/23"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 23. Barṭelle, Iraq. Syr. Orth. Church of Mart Shmuni: ancient baptismal
                  font with Syr. inscription, dated 1342/43. Photo: Amir Harrak. See <bibl>Harrak,
                        <title rend="italic">Syriac and Garshuni inscriptions of Iraq</title>,
                     AB.01.01</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/24"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 24. First page of P. Bedjan’s translation into Neo-Aramaic of
                     <bibl>Thomas à Kempis’ <title rend="italic">Imitation of Christ</title>
                     (1885)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/25"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 25. Dayro d-Mor Behnam: entrance to the main building and back side of
                  the martyrium (left). Photo: Lucas Van Rompay (1971).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/26"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 26. Dayro d-Mor Behnam: entrance to the main building, after
                  renovation. Photo: Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/27"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 27. Dayro d-Mor Behnam: martyrium of Behnam and Sarah (left) and
                  entrance building Photo. Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/28"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 28. Dayro d-Mor Behnam: outer gate of the church with Syriac and Arabic
                  inscriptions. Photo taken by the University of Michigan Expedition for the Iraqi
                  Department of Antiquities (in the 1930s). Courtesy of <bibl>Amir Harrak. See
                     Harrak, <title rend="italic">Syriac and Garshuni inscriptions of
                        Iraq</title>, AE.0105</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/29"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 29. Ms. London, Brit. Libr., Add. 14,471. E.-Syr. ms. containing the
                  Four Gospels (the passage reproduced is Luke 11:48–12:10). The ms. was written in
                  Nisibis and is dated only by the regnal year of the Sasanian king Khusrau II
                  (590–628), viz. his 25th year (= 614/5). From <bibl>Hatch, <title rend="italic"
                        >Album</title>, 212 (Plate CLXI)</bibl>. See <bibl>S. Brock, ‘Early dated
                     manuscripts of the Church of the East, 7th–13th century’, <title rend="italic"
                        >JAAS</title>. 21.2 (2007), 10–11</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/30"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 30. Folio from ms. 716 of the Edgar J. Goodspeed Collection of the
                  Special Collections Library of the University of Chicago. Incomplete ms. of the
                  Peshitta New Testament (probably 9th cent.). The passage reproduced is Acts
                  27:33–28:6, with several (secondary) Arabic glosses in the right-hand
                  margin.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/31"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 31. Ms. Duke Special Collections Library, Syr. 1. Incomplete ms. of the
                  Four Gospels (10th or 11th cent.). The passage reproduced is Mark 7:23–30, with
                  the lection heading for the fourth Sunday of Lent.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/33"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 33. The news about the big fire in Chicago as reported in the
                  Neo-Aramaic periodical <title rend="italic">Zahrīre d-Bahrā</title> 1871/12,
                  printed at the press of the American mission in Urmia. See <bibl>H. L. Murre-van
                     den Berg, <title rend="italic">From a spoken to a written language. The
                        introduction and development of Literary Urmia Aramaic in the nineteenth
                        century</title> (1999), 394–97</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/34"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 34. Rubbing of the Luoyang pillar (first half). The pillar was
                  discovered in 2006 and contains Christian texts contemporaneous with the Xi’an
                  stele. Photo: Hidemi Takahashi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/35"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 35. Bālulan, in the Tergawar district, west of Urmia: single-nave
                  church. Photo: Heleen Murre-van den Berg<choice><sic></sic><corr>.</corr></choice></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/36"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 36. Common verse with which the calligrapher <choice><sic>bp.</sic><corr>Bp.</corr></choice> Çiçek often concluded
                  his writing: ‘Just as the sailor rejoices once his ship has reached the shore, so
                  too does the scribe rejoice at the final line of his book.’ From the facsimile
                  edition of the <title rend="italic">Šḥimo</title> (4th printing, 1981), the
                  original of which was handwritten by <choice><sic>bp.</sic><corr>Bp.</corr></choice> Çiçek. See <bibl>S. Brock, ‘The scribe
                     reaches harbour’, <title rend="italic">Byzantinische Forschungen</title> 21
                     (1995), 195–202</bibl> (repr. in <title rend="italic">From Ephrem to Romanos.
                     Interactions between Greek and Syriac in Late Antiquity</title> [1999], ch.
                  XVI).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/37"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 37. Main church of the Coptic Monastery of the Virgin, also known as
                  Dayr al-Suryān, in which for centuries Coptic and Syriac monks lived together.
                  Photo: Lucas Van Rompay.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/38"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 38. Coptic and Syriac coexisting on the capital of a pillar inside the
                  main Church of the Virgin, Dayr al-Suryān. Photo: Karel Innemée.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/39"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 39. Damascus: Bāb Tūmā, one of the city gates around which much of the
                  Christian population and commercial activity are concentrated. Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo:
                  Mat Immerzeel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/40"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 40. Bust of Mor Athanasios Yeshuʿ Samuel (1907–1995), Syr. Orth. bp. of
                  Jerusalem and first bp. of the United States (1957–1995), outside St. Mark’s
                  Cathedral in Teaneck, New Jersey. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title
                        rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, vol. 3, 119</bibl> (Photo: Riccardo
                  Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/41"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 41. Syr. Orth. Church of Mor Gabriel in Kirchardt, Germany. From
                     <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, vol. 3,
                     176</bibl> (Photo: Riccardo Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/42"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 42. Aerial view of the Syr. Orth. Monastery of St. Ephrem in
                  Glane-Losser, The Netherlands. Courtesy of <choice><sic>bp.</sic><corr>Bp.</corr></choice> Mor Polycarpus.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/43"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 43. Tomb of <choice><sic>bp.</sic><corr>Bp.</corr></choice> Dolabani in Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, near Mardin. Photo: Amir
                  Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/44"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 44. Beginning of a <hi rend="italic">Dorekthā</hi> by Yawsep of Telkepe, from a manuscript in
                  the Library of the Dominican Fathers in Mosul (<bibl>Catalogue B. Sony [2006], 81</bibl>). The
                  pencil note in the margin is by Jacques Rhétoré. Courtesy of Rev. Father<!-- I though it is either 'the Rev. N. M, or Father N.M., but not sure. --> Najeeb
                  Michaeel and Bruno Poizat.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/45"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 45. Aerial view of the side of Dura-Europos with the Euphrates river in
                  the background (taken in 1932). Courtesy of the Yale University Art
                  Gallery.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/46"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 46. Eddé, Lebanon, Church of Mar Saba. General view. Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo:
                  Mat Immerzeel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/47"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 47. Edessa (Urfa), Pool of Abraham (Birket Ibrahim), with sacred fish.
                  According to legend, the pool is the site where Abraham landed when Nimrod threw
                  him down from the top of the citadel. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic"
                     >Hidden Pearl</title> vol. 2, 51</bibl> (Photo: Riccardo Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/48"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 48. Eight of the so-called Nine Saints (the missing Saint, Yemʾata, is
                  depicted in an adjacent mural). Cupola, ca. 15th cent., in a small church near the
                  village of Guh (Gheralta district, Tigre province). Photo: Jan Tromp
                  (2005).<!-- it might help to add the country. From the entry to which it belongs it might be clear where this is, but not so much if one only reads the caption. UP --></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/50"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 50. Beginning of Eusebius of Caesarea’s Letter to Carpianus, in which
                  he explains the use of the Gospel canon tables. Ms. Florence, Biblioteca
                  Mediceo-Laurenziana, Pluteus I,56, f. 2v. See Rabbula Gospels.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/51"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 51. Father J-M. Fiey (standing in the second row, third from right) and
                  the French instructors, Dominican Fathers, at the Seminary of St. John, Mosul, in
                  the school year 1963–1964. Courtesy of Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/52"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 52. Bell-tower and entrance (below) of the church in the Monastery of
                  Mor Gabriel. Photo: Helen Brock (ca. 1978).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/53"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 53. Monastery of Mor Gabriel: view of the house of Malfono ʿIsa Gülten,
                  taken from the Nuns’ quarters. Photo: Helen Brock (1972).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/54"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 54. Early evidence of Garshuni from a historical note in ms. Florence,
                  Biblioteca Mediceo-Laurenziana, Pluteus I,56 (Rabbula Gospels), f. 7v. See <bibl>A.
                  Mengozzi, ‘The history of Garshuni as a writing system: Evidence from the Rabbula
                  Codex’, in <title rend="italic">CAMSEMUD</title> 2007 (Proceedings of the 13th Italian meeting of Afro-Asiatic
                  linguistics) (2010), 297–305</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/55"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 55. Ruins of Ḥarran. Photo: Hugo Lundhaug.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/57"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 57. Monastery of Rabban Hormizd near Alqosh. Burial place with tomb
                  stones of several patriarchs. Photo: Amir Harrak. See <bibl>A. Harrak, ‘Patriarchal
                  funerary inscriptions in the Monastery of Rabban Hormizd: Types, literary origins,
                  and purpose’, <title rend="italic">Hugoye</title> 6.2 (2003)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/58"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 58. ‘Mirror inscription’ in the main church of Dayr al-Suryān,
                  mentioning the name of ‘Quryaqos, patriarch of Antioch’, whose tenure was 793–817.
                  Photo: Karel C. Innemée. Drawing by Lucas Van Rompay.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/59"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 59. Syriac inscription on a pillar at the entrance to the Church of the
                  Holy Sepulcher in Jerusalem, mentioning ‘Sargis the monk, from Ḥaḥ’. This Sargis
                  is also known as a scribe, and he became metropolitan bp. of Ḥaḥ in 1505. Above
                  Sargis’s name are Armenian inscriptions. Photo: Lucas Van Rompay. See <bibl>S. Brock, H.
                  Goldfus, and A. Kofsky, ‘The Syriac inscriptions at the entrance to the Holy
                  Sepulchre, Jerusalem’, <title rend="italic">ARAM</title> 18–19 (2006-2007), esp. 417–18.</bibl></figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/60"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 60. Mosaic inscription from a hermitage near Jericho. The inscription
                  gives the names of the E.-Syr. founders of the hermitage, two of whom are known to
                  belong to the 7th cent. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden
                     Pearl</title>, vol. 2, 46</bibl> (Photo: Riccardo Grassetti). See <bibl>J.-M. Fiey, Rabban
                  Bûya de Shaqlâwâ et de Jéricho”, <title rend="italic">POC</title> 33 (1983), 34–38</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/61"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 61. Dayr Kaftun, near Kaftun, Lebanon. Greek-Orthodox Church of Sts.
                  Sergius and Bacchus. Paul van Moorsel Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the
                  Middle East, Leiden University. Photo: Mat Immerzeel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/62"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 62. Dayr Kaftun, near Kaftun, Lebanon. Greek-Orthodox Church of Sts.
                  Sergius and Bacchus. Detail of 13th-cent. wall painting representing the Communion
                  of the Apostles: Philip and Mark, with Syriac inscriptions. Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo:
                  Mat Immerzeel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/63"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 63. Maʿad, Lebanon, Church of Mar Charbel. Wall painting depicting the
                  Dormition of the Virgin, detail: mourning apostle. Paul van Moorsel Centre for
                  Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo: Mat
                  Immerzeel. See <bibl>M. Immerzeel, <title rend="italic">Identity puzzles. Medieval
                     Christian art in Syria and Lebanon</title> (2009), 105–8</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/64"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 64. Wooden reliquary cross in the Malabar Catholic (or Syro-Malabar)
                  Church of Pallippuram. According to tradition the cross was carved by St. Thomas
                  and has miraculous power. This type of cross may be called the St. Thomas cross in
                  contrast to the Persian cross. The cross is being held by Fr. Ignatius Payyappilly
                  Photo: István Perczel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/65"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 65. Baptismal font in the church of Kanjoor (Malabar Catholic). Photo:
                  István Perczel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/66"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 66. Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church of Thiruvithancode (the present
                  construction is probably from the 16th cent.): the nave. Photo: István
                  Perczel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/68"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 68. Ms. London, Brit. Libr. Add. 17,236. Melkite ms. of an Eklogadion,
                  or collection of verse texts for select fixed commemorations in the liturgical
                  year (here, St. Peter and St. Paul, 29th June). The ms. is dated 1283/84 and was
                  written in the Monastery of Mary, the Mother of God, on the Kaftun river. From
                  <bibl>Hatch, <title rend="italic">Album</title>, 241 (Pl. CXC)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/69"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 69. Jerusalem, Old City, entrance to the Syr. Orth. Monastery of St.
                  Mark. From <bibl>Brock and Taylor, <title rend="italic">Hidden Pearl</title>, vol. 2, 55</bibl>
                  (Photo: Riccardo Grassetti).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/70"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 70. Tombs of Priest Ragheed Ganni and <choice><sic>bp.</sic><corr>Bp.</corr></choice> Bulus Faraj Rahho (Chaldean
                  bishop of Mosul), who fell victim to violence against Christians in Iraq in 2007
                  and 2008, respectively. Karamlish, Chald. Church of Mar Addai. Photo: Amir
                  Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/72"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 72. Ms. London, Brit. Libr. Add. 12,138. E.-Syr. Masora. The ms. was
                  written in Ḥarran in 899. From <bibl>Hatch, <title rend="italic">Album</title>, 217 (Plate CLXVI)</bibl>. See <bibl>S. Brock,
                     ‘Early dated manuscripts of the Church of the East, 7th<choice><sic>-</sic><corr>–</corr></choice>13th century’, <title rend="italic">JAAS</title> 21:2
                  (2007), 18–20</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/73"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 73. Dayro d-Mor Matay after its recent renovation: front façade with
                  main entrance. Photo. Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/74"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 74. Beth Qadishe in Dayro d-Mor Matay, with several tombs. Photo: Amir
                  Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/75"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 75. Note written by Michael Rabo on the last folio of ms. London, Brit.
                  Libr. Add. 14,599. This ms. (dated 568/9) contains Cathedral Homilies 31–59 of
                  Severus of Antioch and was borrowed by Michael from Egypt and kept in his
                  patriarchal cell, where it was made available to the monks for reading. See <bibl>F.
                  Nau, ‘Sur quelques autographes de Michel le Syrien, patriarche d’Antioche de 1166
                  à 1199’, <title rend="italic">ROC</title> 19 (1914), 394–95</bibl>. © The British Library Board.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/78"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 78. Monastery of Mor Abrohom, in the vicinity of Midyat. Photo: Hidemi
                  Takahashi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/80"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 80. Syr. Orth. monk depicted on the Gate of double baptism (<choice><sic>i.e.</sic><corr>i.e.,</corr></choice> by
                  water and blood) in the Church of Mor Behnam’s Monastery. Photo: Amir Harrak. See
                  <bibl>B. Snelders, <title rend="italic">Identity and Christian-Muslim interaction. Medieval art of the Syrian
                  Orthodox from the Mosul area</title> (OLA 198; 2010), 310–18</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/81"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 81. Syr. Orth. nuns in Ṭur ʿAbdin, in the village of Kfarbe (in the
                  vicinity of the Monastery of Mor Gabriel). Photo: Naures Atto.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/82"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 82. Mosul, Syr. Orth. Church of Mar Tumo. Photo: Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/83"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 83. Mosul, Syr. Cath. Church al-Ṭāhira (Old Church): Iconostasis with
                  inscription dated 1744. Photo: Amir Harrak. See <bibl>Harrak, <title rend="italic">Syriac and Garshuni
                  inscriptions of Iraq</title>, AA.08.06</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/84"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 84. Mosul, Chaldean Church of al-Ṭāhra: tripartite arcade of the
                  sanctuary. Photo: Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/86"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 86. Dayr Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashī: an angel belonging to the scene of Jesus’
                  Baptism, in the north aisle of the church (layer 2, 1095). Paul van Moorsel Centre
                  for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo: Mat
                  Immerzeel. See also <ref target="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/15">Fig. 15</ref>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/87"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 87. Dayr Mār Mūsā al-Ḥabashī: south-eastern pier spandrel in the nave
                  of the church. The evangelist Matthew is writing the first words of his Gospel,
                  which he copies from a tablet in heaven (layer 3, ca. 1200). Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo:
                  Mat Immerzeel. See <bibl>E. Cruikshank Dodd, <title rend="italic">The Frescoes of Mar Musa al-Habashi</title> (2001),
                  57</bibl>, as well as <bibl>J. den Heijer et al., ‘Deir Mar Musa. The inscriptions’, <title rend="italic">ECA</title>
                  (2007), 144–46</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/89"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 89. The name of Mushe of Nisibis written in an inscription on a wooden
                  door in the main church of Dayr al-Suryān. The inscription refers to the building
                  of the altar space under Mushe’s tenure and is dated 926/27. Photo: Lucas Van
                  Rompay.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/90"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 90. Coptic inscription in the central dome above the khurus of the main
                  church of Dayr al-Suryān, mentioning, ‘Papa Moses the hegoumenos’, who may
                  possibly be identified as Mushe of Nisibis. Photo: Karel Innemée. See <bibl>J. van der
                  Vliet, ‘History through inscriptions: Coptic epigraphy in the Wadi al-Natrun’, in
                  <title rend="italic">Christianity and monasticism in Wadi al-Natrun</title>, ed. M. S. A. Mikhail and M. Moussa
                  (2009), 336–37</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/91"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 91. The city of Nineveh as background for the sleeping prophet Jonah.
                  Ms. Florence, Biblioteca Mediceo-Laurenziana, Pluteus I,56 (Rabbula Gospels), f.
                  6r (detail).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/92"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 92. Nusaybin (Nisibis): the Syr. Orth. Church of Mor Yaʿqub, which
                  houses the baptistery that contains a Greek inscription dated 359 as well as the
                  tomb of Yaʿqub of Nisibis. Photo: Hidemi Takahashi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/93"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 93. Malfono Abrohom Nuro (lower corner on the right) with students of
                  the Syriac evening school in Aleppo, and some guests (in the 1960s). <bibl>From A. Nuro,
                  <title rend="italic">My tour in the parishes of the Syrian Church in Syria and Lebanon</title> (1967),
                  84</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/94"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 94. Front of P. Dura 28, describing the sale of a female slave dated 9
                  May 243. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/95"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 95. Ms. London, Brit. Libr. Add. 14,512, a famous palimpsest ms.
                  containing in its lower writing portions from the biblical book of Isaiah (Leiden
                  Peshitta Institute: 5ph1), dated 459/60 (which makes this ms. the oldest dated
                  biblical ms. that is known) and in its upper writing services for the feasts of
                  the liturgical year. At the top right the middle of Is. 16:8 is clearly visible.
                  From <bibl>Hatch, <title rend="italic">Album</title>, 53 (Plate II)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/96"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 96. Papyrus fragment preserved in Dayr al-Suryān, Egypt, probably 9th
                  cent. Photo: Lucas Van Rompay. See <bibl>Fr. Bigoul El-Souriany and L. Van Rompay,
                     ‘Syriac papyrus fragments recently discovered in Deir al-Surian (Egypt)’, <title rend="italic">Hugoye</title>
                  4.1 (2001)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/97"/>
               <figDesc>Fig.97. Pawlos of Kallinikos, mentioned as bp. in an inscription, dated 509,
                  uncovered in Tall Biʿa, near Raqqaʿ, Syria. Deutsche Orient-Gesellschaft, Grabung
                  Tall Biʿa. Photo: Anwar ʿAbd al-Ghafour.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/98"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 98. Table of the alphabet from <bibl>J. A. Widmanstetter, <title rend="italic">Syriacae linguae
                  prima elementa</title> (1556)</bibl>, published shortly after his first edition of the Syriac New
                  Testament (1555).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/99"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 99. Bible in Neo-Aramaic. Printed on the press of the American
                  missionaries in Urmia (edition of 1893). The image shows Psalm 1.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/100"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 100. Title page of E.-Syr. missal: the proper of the mass. Printed on
                  the press of the Dominican Fathers in Mosul (1901). See <bibl>J. F. Coakley and D. G. K.
                  Taylor, ‘Syriac books printed at the Dominican Press, Mosul’, in <title rend="italic">Malphono w-Rabo
                  d-Malphone</title>, ed. Kiraz (2008), 101–2 (no. 58)</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/101"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 101. Qara, Syria, Church of Sts. Sergius and Bacchus. Detail of wall
                  painting: the nursing Virgin, with Greek and Syriac inscription. Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University. Photo:
                  Bas ter Haar Romeny.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/102"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 102. Qara, Syria: Dayr Mar Yaʿqub, main entrance. Paul van Moorsel
                  Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, Leiden University.
                  Courtesy of Mat Immerzeel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/103"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 103. Qaraqosh, Syr. Cath. Church of the Mother of God. Photo: Amir
                  Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/105"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 105. Recently discovered inscription containing the name of <choice><sic>bp.</sic><corr>Bp.</corr></choice>.
                  Rabbula, dated 425/26 (‘In the year 737, in the days of Mar Rabbula the Bishop’).
                  Courtesy of Françoise Briquel-Chatonnet, Alain Desreumaux, and Joseph Moukarzel.
                  See their <bibl>‘Découverte d’une inscription syriaque mentionnant l’évêque Rabbula’, in
                  <title rend="italic">Malphono w-Rabo d-Malphone</title>, ed. Kiraz (2008), 19–28</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/106"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 106. Portrait of Syr. Cath. Patr. Ignatius Ephrem II Raḥmani in the
                  reception hall of the Monastery of Sharfeh, Lebanon. Photo: Jean Fathi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/107"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 107. Dayr al-Ṣalīb, monastery 30 km. northeast of Midyat: general view.
                  Photo: Hidemi Takahashi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/108"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 108. Addai Scher, Chald. bp. of Siirt, and Syriac scholar, assassinated
                  in 1915. From <bibl>A. Nuro, <title rend="italic">My four in the parishes of the Syrian Church in Syria and
                  Lebanon</title> (1967), 84</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/109"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 109. Father Joseph Omez and a class of students in the Seminary of St.
                  John, Mosul, in 1963–64. Courtesy of Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/110"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 110. Severus of Antioch, as depicted in inlaid ivory (most of which is
                  lost) and identified with his Greek name, on a panel of the wooden door that
                  separates the altar space from the <hi rend="italic">khurus</hi> in the main church of Dayr al-Suryān
                  (dated May 914, under abbot Mushe of Nisibis). Photo: Karel Innemée (after 2010
                  conservation).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/111"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 111. Syr. Cath. Monastery of Sharfeh, to the northeast of Beirut.
                  Entrance of the Monastery. Photo: Jean Fathi.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/112"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 112. Qalʿat Simʿān (northern Syria): the basilica built around Shemʿun
                  the Stylite’s pillar. Photo: Lucas Van Rompay.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/113"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 113. Dayr al-Suryān, Wadi al-Natrun, Egypt, in winter. Photo: Lucas Van
                  Rompay.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/114"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 114. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal Residence and Seminary in Maʿarrat
                  Ṣaydnāyā, 35 km. north of Damascus. Photo: Amir Harrak.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/115"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 115. Seal of Athanasios, metropolitan of Tagrit (late 9th cent), in the
                  form of a cross, of which three edges contain a Syriac inscription, found in
                  Athanasios’s tomb in Tagrit. Baghdad, Iraqi Museum. Courtesy of <bibl>A. Harrak. See A.
                  Harrak, ‘Recent archaeological excavations in Takrit and the discovery of Syriac
                  inscriptions’, <title rend="italic">JCSSS</title> 1 (2001), esp. 23–24</bibl> as well as <bibl>Harrak, <title rend="italic">Syriac and Garshuni
                  inscriptions of Iraq</title>, FA.01.04</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/116"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 116. Representation of a reliquary St. Thomas cross flanking the
                  entrance to the Malabar Catholic Church at Kanjoor. It is carved in granite.
                  Photo: István Perczel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/117"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 117. Teaching infant Jesus. Rare teak-wood statue from St. Mary’s
                  Church at Kanjoor (Malabar Catholic). The sculpture, a fine product of
                  Indo-Christian art and reflecting Buddhist influence as well, is difficult to
                  date. Catholic Art Museum, Ernakulam. Courtesy of the museum’s curator, Fr.
                  Ignatius Payyappilly. Photo: István Perczel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/118"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 118. Granite columns from the façade of the Kanjoor Malabar Catholic
                  church. The columns closely resemble those of Hindu temples but contain Christian
                  symbols. Photo: István Perczel.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/119"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 119. Ms. Piramadam Syr. 25, f. 41v–42r. Colophon of a copy of the
                  Revelations of Gregory the Theologian (= Pseudo-Gregory of Nazianzus), translated
                  from Arabic into Syriac by Mor Ivanios Ḥidayatallah, bp. of Nineveh and Antiochian
                  Patriarchal Delegate in Malabar, in Kadamattam, in the year 1689/90. This is one
                  of the two copies of this work known to date. Courtesy of the Project for
                  Preserving the Manuscripts of the Syrian Christians in India (SRITE).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/121"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 121. Beth Ṣlutho in Ḥaḥ, Ṭur ʿAbdin. Photo: Helen Brock
                  (1978).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/124"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 124. Children’s poem about the rain. Ṭuroyo in Latin transcription.
                  From <bibl>Y. Ishaq, <title rend="italic">Toxu Qorena</title> (1983), 49</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/125"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 125. The Assyrian Missionary Cemetery, situated on a mountain
                  overlooking Urmia. Photo: Heleen Murre-van den Berg.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/126"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 126. Urmia, Iran: Church of Mart Maryam. Photo: Heleen Murre-van den
                  Berg.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/127"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 127. Detail from the Xi’an stele (right side), with names of Church
                  officials, in Syriac and Chinese. After the rubbing included in <bibl>H. Havret, <title rend="italic">La
                  stèle chrétienne de Si-ngan-fou</title> (Variétés sinologiques 7; 1895)</bibl>. See also <bibl>P.
                  Pelliot, J. Dauvillier, and A. Guillaumont, <title rend="italic">Recherches sur les Chrétiens d’Asie
                  Centrale et d’Extrême-Orient</title>, II.1. <title rend="italic">La stèle de Si-gnan-fou</title> (Œuvres posthumes de
                  Paul Pelliot; 1984), esp. p. 60 (text and FT) and 73–74 (commentary)</bibl>. On the
                  second line (left), the last word in Syriac script is a transliteration in Syriac
                  of a Chinese term. Pelliot argued that the underlying Chinese term is <hi rend="italic">shàng-zu</hi>ò,
                  ‘upper seat’, the name used for an elder in Chinese Buddhist literature, which may
                  be the equivalent of ‘abbot’. See <bibl>H. Takahashi, ‘Transcribed proper names in
                     Chinese Syriac Christian documents’, in <title rend="italic">Malphono w-Rabo d-Malphone</title>, ed. Kiraz
                  (2008), 643</bibl>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <graphic url="http://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/fig/128"/>
               <figDesc>Fig. 128. Yaʿqub Burdʿoyo as imagined by Elias Zayat, a modern painter in
                  Damascus. Courtesy of Elias Zayat.</figDesc>
            </figure>

         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
