<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>List of Contributors</head>
            <p>1. <persName>Joseph P. Amar</persName> is Director of Syriac and Arabic Studies and the Program in Early Christian Studies at the University of Notre Dame, Indiana.</p>
            <p>2. <persName>Mor Polycarpus Augin Aydin</persName> is the Syriac Orthodox Archbishop of The Netherlands, with residence in the Monastery of St. Ephrem at Glane-Losser. He is currently finishing his Ph.D. dissertation at Princeton Theological Seminary.</p>
            <p>3. <persName>Adam H. Becker</persName> is Associate Professor of Classics and Religious Studies, and Director of the Religious Studies Program, at New York University.</p>
            <p>4. <persName>George A. Bevan</persName> is Assistant Professor in the Department of Classics at Queen’s University, Canada.</p>
            <p>5. <persName>Monica J. Blanchard</persName> is Curator of the Semitics Collections at the Institute of Christian Oriental Research of the Catholic University of America, Washington, DC.</p>
            <p>6. <persName>Françoise Briquel-Chatonnet</persName> is Directrice de recherche at the French Centre National de Recherche Scientifique (Orient et Méditerranée, Études sémitiques anciennes), Paris.</p>
            <p>7. <persName>Sebastian P. Brock</persName> is Emeritus Reader in Syriac Studies at Oxford University.</p>
            <p>8. <persName>Erwin Buck</persName> is Professor of New Testament at Lutheran Theological Seminary (University of Saskatchewan), Saskatoon, Canada (retired) and serves as the Content Coordinator of the Eleventh Assembly of the Lutheran World Federation in Geneva, Switzerland.</p>
            <p>9. <persName>David D. Bundy</persName> is Associate Provost for Library Services and Associate Professor of History at Fuller Theological Seminary in Pasadena, California.</p>
            <p>10. <persName>Samuel Burleson</persName> received his M.A. degree in Religion from the Department of Religion of Duke University in Durham, North Carolina, in May 2010. His main interest is in Syriac and Coptic Christianity.</p>
            <p>11. <persName>Aaron M. Butts</persName> is Lector of Semitics in the Department of Near Eastern Languages and Civilizations at Yale University.</p>
            <p>12. <persName>Thomas A. Carlson</persName> is a Ph.D. candidate in the History Department at Princeton University.</p>
            <p>13. <persName>Marica Cassis</persName> is Assistant Professor of History at Memorial University of Newfoundland, Canada.</p>
            <p>14. <persName>Jeff W. Childers</persName> is Professor of New Testament and Early Christianity in the Graduate School of Theology, Abilene Christian University, Abilene, Texas.</p>
            <p>15. <persName>James F. Coakley</persName> teaches Syriac at Cambridge University, United Kingdom.</p>
            <p>16. <persName>Brian Edric Colless</persName>, Ph.D. and Th.D., was formerly a lecturer in Religious Studies and is now a research scholar attached to the School of History at Massey University in New Zealand.</p>
            <p>17. <persName>Riccardo Contini</persName> is Professor of Semitic Philology at the University of Naples ‘L’Orientale’, Italy.</p>
            <p>18. <persName>Khalid Dinno</persName> (Ph.D. Engineering) is a Ph.D. candidate in the Aramaic-Syriac Program in the Department of Near and Middle Eastern Civilizations at the University of Toronto.</p>
            <p>19. <persName>Erica Cruikshank Dodd</persName> is Adjunct Associate Professor in the Department of History in Art, and Associate Fellow in the Centre for the Study of Religion and Society, University of Victoria, B.C., Canada.</p>
            <p>20. <persName>Maria E. Doerfler</persName> is a Ph.D. candidate in the field of Early Christianity at Duke University, Durham, North Carolina.</p>
            <p>21. <persName>Robert Doran</persName> is Samuel Williston Professor of Greek and Hebrew in the Department of Religion at Amherst College, Massachusetts.</p>
            <p>22. <persName>Jean Fathi</persName> is preparing an edition in the field of Syriac studies for the Diplôme de l’École Pratique des Hautes Études, Paris, France.</p>
            <pb n="XIV"/>
            <p>23. <persName>John R. K. Fenwick</persName> is a former ecumenical secretary to the Archbishop of Canterbury and was for a time co-secretary of the internal Anglican-Orthodox dialogue. He has been a regular visitor to South India, researching the history of the St. Thomas Christian community. He is currently a Diocesan Bishop in the Free Church of England.</p>
            <p>24. <persName>Emanuel A. Fiano</persName> is a Ph.D. student in the field of Early Christianity at Duke University, Durham, North Carolina, focusing on Syriac and Coptic Christianities.</p>
            <p>25. <persName>Jan J. van Ginkel</persName> holds a Ph.D. degree from the University of Groningen (1995) and subsequently worked as a postdoctoral researcher in Syriac studies at the University of Leiden, The Netherlands.</p>
            <p>26. <persName>Sidney H. Griffith</persName> is Professor and Chair of the Department of Semitic and Egyptian Languages and Literatures at the Catholic University of America in Washington, DC.</p>
            <p>27. <persName>Bas ter Haar Romeny</persName> is Professor of Old Testament and Eastern Christian Traditions at Leiden University, The Netherlands.</p>
            <p>28. <persName>Mary T. Hansbury</persName> is an independent scholar of Syriac studies and an iconographer in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.</p>
            <p>29. <persName>Amir Harrak</persName> is Professor of Aramaic and Syriac in the Department of Near and Middle Eastern Civilizations of the University of Toronto, Canada.</p>
            <p>30. <persName>Susan Ashbrook Harvey</persName> is the Willard Prescott and Annie McClelland Smith Professor and Chair for the Department of Religious Studies at Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island.</p>
            <p>31. <persName>John F. Healey</persName> is Professor of Semitic Studies at the University of Manchester, England. His main interest is in Syriac and Nabataean Aramaic inscriptions and in the history of writing.</p>
            <p>32. <persName>Bo Holmberg</persName> is Professor of Semitic Languages at the Centre for Languages and Literature of Lund University, Sweden.</p>
            <p>33. <persName>Mat Immerzeel</persName> is Director of the Paul van Moorsel Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East at Leiden University, The Netherlands.</p>
            <p>34. <persName>Thomas Joseph</persName> is the Senior Manager of Information Architecture at one of the largest US-based investment management firms. He is also a Syriac enthusiast, a member of the Board of Directors of Beth Mardutho [<ref target="http://www.betmardutho.org">www.bethmardutho.org</ref>], technical editor of <title rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title> [<ref target="http://bethmardutho.org/index.php/hugoye/about-hugoye.html"><choice><sic>bethmardutho.cua.edu/Hugoye</sic><corr>bethmardutho.org/index.php/hugoye/about-hugoye.html</corr></choice></ref><!-- What do we do if this link no longer works! -->], as well as Web Master of Syriac Orthodox Resources [<ref target="http://sor.cua.edu/">sor.cua.edu</ref>].</p>
            <p>35. <persName>Andreas Juckel</persName> is Research Associate at the Oriental Department of the Institute for New Testament Textual Research, University of Muenster, Germany.</p>
            <p>36. <persName>Hubert Kaufhold</persName> is Honorarprofessor für Antike Rechtsgeschichte, insbesondere das Recht des Christlichen Orients, at the Juridical Faculty of the University of Munich, Germany. He is also co-editor of the periodical <title rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</title>.</p>
            <p>37. <persName>Grigory Kessel</persName> is research assistant at the Seminar für Ostkirchengeschichte of the Philipps Universität in Marburg, Germany.</p>
            <p>38. <persName>George A. Kiraz</persName> is the President of Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute and editor-in-chief of Gorgias Press, Piscataway, N.J.</p>
            <p>39. <persName>Robert A. Kitchen</persName> is Minister of Knox-Metropolitan United Church in Regina, Saskatchewan, Canada.</p>
            <p>40. <persName>Naomi Koltun-Fromm</persName> is Associate Professor of Religion at Haverford College, Pennsylvania. She specializes in comparative Jewish and Christian biblical exegesis.</p>
            <p>41. <persName>David Lane</persName> passed away on 9 Jan. 2005. Between 1971 and 1983 he taught Aramaic and Syriac at the Department of Near Eastern Studies of the University of Toronto and subsequently joined the staff of the College of the Resurrection in Mirfield, United Kingdom.</p>
            <p>42. <persName>Michael Lattke</persName> is Emeritus Professor of New Testament and Early Christianity at The University of Queensland, Australia.</p>
            <p>43. <persName>Clemens Leonhard</persName> is Professor for liturgical studies at the Faculty for Catholic Theology of the Westfälische Wilhelms-Universität in Münster, Germany.</p>
            <p>44. <persName>Jonathan Loopstra</persName> is an Assistant Professor of History at the American University of Iraq, Sulaimani.</p>
            <p>45. <persName>Edward G. Mathews, Jr.</persName>, is Recurring Visiting Professor of Early Christian Languages and Literatures and Director of Research at St. Nersess Armenian Seminary in New Rochelle, New York.</p>
            <pb n="XV"/>
            <p>46. <persName>Alessandro Mengozzi</persName> teaches Semitic Philology at the University of Turin, Italy. His main interest is in Neo-Aramaic and in late and modern East-Syriac poetry.</p>
            <p>47. <persName>Volker L. Menze</persName> is Associate Professor of Late Antique History in the Department of Medieval Studies of the Central European University, Budapest, Hungary.</p>
            <p>48. <persName>David A. Michelson</persName> is Assistant Professor of Late Antiquity and Ancient History in the History Department of the University of Alabama at Tuscaloosa, Alabama.</p>
            <p>49. <persName>Craig E. Morrison</persName> is Associate Professor in Syriac language and literature at the Pontifical Biblical Institute in Rome.</p>
            <p>50. <persName>Ray Jabre Mouawad</persName> is Professor at the Lebanese American University of Beirut and researcher at the Center Louis Pouzet for Medieval Studies at St. Joseph University.</p>
            <p>51. <persName>Heleen Murre-van den Berg</persName> is Professor in the History of Modern World Christianity, especially in the Middle East, in the Institute for Religious Studies, Faculty of Humanities, of Leiden University, The Netherlands.</p>
            <p>52. <persName>Andrew N. Palmer</persName> teaches Greek and Latin at a school in Meppel, The Netherlands. He is a Research Associate at the Institute of Eastern Christian Studies in Nijmegen and at Manchester University, United Kingdom.</p>
            <p>53. <persName>Michael Penn</persName> is Associate Professor of Religion at Mount Holyoke College in South Hadley, Massachusetts. His current research focuses on Syriac Christian reactions to the rise of Islam.</p>
            <p>54. <persName>William L. Petersen</persName> passed away on 20 Dec. 2006. He was Professor of New Testament and Christian Origins in the Religious Studies Program and also Professor in the Department of Classics and Ancient Mediterranean Studies at Pennsylvania State University in University Park, Pennsylvania.</p>
            <p>55. <persName>Peter E. Pormann</persName> is Associate Professor at the Department of Classics and Ancient History, University of Warwick, United Kingdom. He is mainly interested in Greek-Syriac-Arabic translations and in the transmission of medicine and philosophy.</p>
            <p>56. <persName>Ute Possekel</persName> received her Ph.D. from Princeton Theological Seminary in 1997. She taught History of Christianity at St. John’s Seminary in Boston from 1998 to 2004 and currently teaches part-time in the History Department of Gordon College in Wenham, Massachusetts.</p>
            <p>57. <persName>Gerrit J. Reinink</persName> is Associate Professor emeritus of Aramaic and Syriac at the University of Groningen, The Netherlands.</p>
            <p>58. <persName>Barbara Roggema</persName> is Adjunct Assistant Professor of History at John Cabot University, Rome, Italy.</p>
            <p>59. <persName>Stephen D. Ryan, O.P.</persName>, is Associate Professor of Sacred Scripture at the Pontifical Faculty of the Immaculate Conception in the Dominican House of Studies, Washington, DC.</p>
            <p>60. <persName>Alison G. Salvesen</persName> is a University Research Lecturer at the Oriental Institute, University of Oxford, and Polonsky Fellow in Jewish Bible Versions at the Oxford Centre for Hebrew and Jewish Studies.</p>
            <p>61. <persName>Bas Snelders</persName> is a research fellow at the Paul van Moorsel Center for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle East, of Leiden University, The Netherlands. He is co-editor of the periodical <title rend="italic">Eastern Christian Art</title>.</p>
            <p>62. <persName>Jan-Eric Steppa</persName> holds a Ph.D. from the University of Lund (2001) and continues to conduct research in the field of Late Antique studies. He presently works as a funeral director in Lund, Sweden.</p>
            <p>63. <persName>Columba Andrew Stewart</persName> is Professor of Theology and Executive Director of the Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript Library, Saint John’s University, Collegeville, Minnesota.</p>
            <p>64. <persName>Hidemi Takahashi</persName> is Associate Professor in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences at the University of Tokyo.</p>
            <p>65. <persName>Jack Tannous</persName> is the Post-Doctoral Teaching Fellow in Byzantine History at Dumbarton Oaks and George Washington University.</p>
            <p>66. <persName>David Taylor</persName> is University Lecturer in Aramaic and Syriac at the University of Oxford, United Kingdom.</p>
            <p>67. <persName>Herman G. B. Teule</persName> is Professor of Eastern Christianity at the Radboud University Nijmegen, The Netherlands and at the Catholic University Leuven, Belgium. He is the Head of the Institute of Eastern Christian Studies at the Radboud University.</p>
            <p>68. <persName>Lucas Van Rompay</persName> is Professor of Eastern Christianity in the Department of Religion at Duke University, Durham, North Carolina.</p>
            <pb  n="XVI"/>
            <p>69. <persName>Baby Varghese</persName> is Professor of Liturgical Studies and Syriac Language and Literature at the Orthodox Theological Seminary, Kottayam, India and Saint Ephrem’s Ecumenical Research Institute (SEERI), Kottayam.</p>
            <p>70. <persName>Joel T. Walker</persName> is Associate Professor of History (Late Antiquity) at the University of Washington in Seattle. His research focuses on the Church of the East.</p>
            <p>71. <persName>Timothy Scott Wardle</persName> earned his Ph.D. in New Testament from Duke University in 2008. He presently teaches as an Adjunct Assistant Professor at Wake Forest University and Elon University, North Carolina.</p>
            <p>72. <persName>John William Watt</persName> is Reader in the School of Religious and Theological Studies, Cardiff University, Wales.</p>
            <p>73. <persName>Dorothea Weltecke</persName> is Professor für die Geschichte der Religionen und des Religiösen in Europa at the University of Konstanz, Germany.</p>
            <p>74. <persName>Lionel R. Wickham</persName> was until his retirement Lecturer in the Faculty of Divinity at Cambridge University, United Kingdom.</p>
            <p>75. <persName>Witold Witakowski</persName> is Associate Professor of Semitic Languages in the Department of Linguistics and Philology, Uppsala University, Sweden.</p>
            <p>76. <persName>Ilya Yakubovich</persName> holds a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago (2008) and is currently a researcher at the Institute of World Culture of Moscow State University, Russia.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
